Ho ho ho
And welcome to the 24th and final door
of our MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
Today is a special day for many
We will avoid burdening your brain
with modelling topics today
Instead, we will end by in
lighting up our Christmas tree
This can also be done much
more amazing with more effort
Model simulations can be
provided with graphical interfaces
In order to play around with
the system at an early stage
before anything has been implemented
Finally here's a little gift from us
Our MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree model
You can download it as a Cameo model
or as an XMI model from our website
mbse-podcast.rocks
And you can play around
with it by yourself
Next year we will see and hear you again
in the usual way
We will soon announce the first dates
with new exciting topics via our website
and social media channels
Facebook, LinkedIn, Instagram, and Twitter
We wish you all a Merry Christmas
A Happy New Year
And stay healthy
Bye-bye
Goodbye