ho ho ho and welcome to the 24th and
final door of our mbse podcast advent
calendar
today is a special day for many
we will avoid burdening your brain with
modelling topics today
instead we will end by in lighting up
our christmas tree
this can also be done much more amazing
with more effort
model simulations can be provided with
graphical interfaces in order to play
around with the system at an early stage
before anything has been implemented
finally here's a little gift from us
our mbse podcast cruising stream model
you can download it as a camera model or
as an xmi model from our website
mbse-podcast.rocks
and you can play around with it by
yourself
next year we will see and hear you again
in the usual way
we will soon announce the first dates
with new exciting topics via our website
and social media channels facebook
linkedin instagram and twitter
we wish you all a merry christmas
a happy new year
and stay healthy
bye bye
goodbye