Hello
Behind the 3rd door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
we take a quick look at
Requirements modeling
There is and has been a lot to say
about Requirements modelling
We will limit ourselves to
one special feature
which is also the learning gift of
today the reuse of Requirements
This is a bit unusual but is supported
by SysML with a special relationship
and the relationship is not
yet used that often
In the Christmas tree business
there is the important "International
Christmas Tree Standard" abbreviated "ICS"
The specific "ICS 242526-12" standard
contains a list of Requirements
for Christmas trees
We import the standard to our
model as a model library
So, let's have a look at our model
As an example the
following table contains
three of the Christmas Tree
Standards in our library
So, it's here in the library
package and here is the table
And they are for example
The "Tree Shape" shall be
complied with the "ICS" standard
The "Tree kinds" the tree shall be a
fir tree and the "Tree Height"
The tree shall be at least 150 centimeters
and maximum 200 centimeter high
Our MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree project
would like to use exactly these
Requirements from the library
However, we would like to have a
different numbering schema
And also add additional properties like
obligation, priority, or the stakeholder
Therefore we use the system
a copy relationship
to create copies of the
Requirements in our model
We have here an example for the tree
which is located in the Base Architecture
There's the tree and the Requirement of
the tree and here is our diagram
The Requirement height
of the tree is a copy
of the standard Requirement tree height
The relationship assures that the
text of the copied Requirement
is always identical to the master
all other properties can be different
The following table shows some of our
MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree Requirements
with the properties
ID, name, text, obligation
priority, stakeholder
and the master of the
Requirement if it is a copy
So, let's open the table
it's here in the requirements package
system Requirements and here's the table
The Requirements are in
different packages of the model
some of them are located in the package
structure of the related component
for example here those for the tree
So much for the 3rd door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 3rd of December
Goodbye
Bye-bye