welcome to a new episode of our mbse
podcast so where christian and i
talk about topics around mbse
if you want to learn more about us visit
our website mbse
podcast.rocks and
or follow us on facebook linkedin
instagram and twitter
today we have another episode from our
series mbse around the world
in which we visit a country to visit um
and to find out how mbse is used there
and in the past we have been
visiting
the uk
china
or sweden
and this time we visit another nordic
country we talked to rico samino about
mbse in finland
so rico welcome and it's great that you
are here and please introduce yourself
good evening and
thank you for inviting me to to this
podcast and of course welcome to finland
so um my name is riku sarminen
and i'm an engineering management
consultant
and
my company
suse
is
providing training and consultancy
services
mainly here in finland for for my
customers for my finnish customers
companies and and also
other organizations
and and the services
are very much based on systems
engineering principles methods and tools
and
my background
is from defense domain
i worked many years
for the for the defense material command
for of the finnish defense forces
uh and nowadays
people know that that organization has a
logistics
logistics command so new name but uh
but i think that most most the same
organization
and i i had a very unique opportunity at
that time
to to spend
one year at uh
studying systems engineering and master
of science degree in systems engineering
in in cranfield university
uk and and
that was uh
that was a lot of work but uh but i have
to say that i
i learned a lot and and i think that
that's probably
the reason why
why i'm i'm doing what i'm doing after
at the moment so so that's that's was
probably some kind of
driver or or major
milestone in my
in my life and of course in my career
and uh
after that i i continued working for the
finnish defense forces for the
procurement projects
and and also with the little life cycle
support of defense equipment
and
after some years
there i
took a position at the the other side of
the table as as you could say so i i
i started to work for the for the
defense industry
so i
it was also a good opportunity to see
see the other other way of defense
projects and
and learn learn the the industry side
and maybe that has been the
that's the the side that i have been
mainly working scenes and and the last
eight years i have been working as a
as a as a consultant and
and and trainer within my own
own company
okay
thank you
and welcome also from my side rico
um
yeah
when i think of sweden uh of sweden yeah
when i think of finland
i'm thinking of wood
and i'm thinking
of nokia
so
can you tell us what are the typical
industries in finland and
which of those are already used to use
uh systems engineering or even
model-based systems engineering
um
yes we
a long time ago we we used to say that
finland
lives from forests so so
we we had a big part of our
export coming from
wood and
and paper industry so that's that's
probably a
and and
it is still somewhat but uh
in general i think that the
the role of paper industry has has been
reducing quite a lot a lot in finland
and uh another traditional uh industry
area has been uh
and it still is ship building
so
so there was
some years ago a little bit
down
time for for the ship building but i
think again there are
there are uh
big ship building companies and and and
that's that has been
has been a a big
industry area
and as you mentioned
uh nokia was probably a
a big change in the in in the finnish
industry so
especially in in 1990s when
when when i when i graduated or
at first started at the end of eighties
and then and graduated
at 1990 so nokia was was very big player
and big employer
for for for the
for the people here in finland and uh
and those mobile phones and and and
networks they were
they they kind of uh
build up
uh kind of this kind of modern
technology industry and
and especially
electrical industry that that we
still have of course it's not a group of
much smaller companies but i think the
the people that that where
were trained and and and uh
work worked in at nokia are now working
for many other companies
so that has been of course had a major
impact on
on on finnish industry
about systems engineering and and uh
and uh
model based systems engineering i i
think that
it has been mainly
uh
that the traditional area of systems
engineering which is in in many
countries defense industry that is also
the same in finland so that
but also the the customer the finnish
defense forces and and of course the
other
other customers for the for the finnish
defense industry they are they are kind
of requiring
to you to use the systems engineering so
that is that is of course one driver for
for the defense industry and and
and lately there has been also interest
and a lot of
already
implemented systems engineering methods
and tools in in the nuclear
nuclear power domain so so personally
also i have been working there
there as a as a consultant so i can see
that they are they are really
really putting some effort effort on on
that part and
some other
domains
i know healthcare
technology companies they they are doing
some some some systems engineering but
but in in in general i think that um
that
we we have still still quite a lot to do
in finland for for for improving the
the awareness and knowledge of systems
engineer
and
what would you estimate how well then is
model-based systems engineering used in
in fitland
um
i i think our this is my
my personal view i i
i i'm not claiming that i i'm aware of
all
all activities of all
for finnish companies that's not
possible but
but
it seems that uh the finnish industry
has not
yet been adapting
systems engineering to their way of of
of work or model based systems
engineering to their way of work
uh i i know that uh in in the finnish
academia or universities
there are
uh
research research done in the area of
model-based systems engineering and and
i know that some companies have been
been evaluating
the possibilities of of model-based
systems engineering but
as i said my current understanding is
that model-based systems engineering is
not currently used
in in the atmosphere in in finnish
companies so i don't know i don't know
maybe i'm wrong but but
maybe if
if i'm wrong please please let me know
that that i'm wrong and
if somebody
in the fitness industry is already using
mbs just contact me and
absolutely or leave a comment below this
video and give us a thumbs up and don't
forget
yeah to subscribe to this channel to not
miss out any
other
podcast episode yeah rico um do you have
any idea why that is
or why you
why do you have this feeling that it was
evaluated by many but not really applied
again
this is this is just just a personal
personal view but but i think that there
might be might be two reasons uh so
at least my experiences the the in many
companies and in many many industry
domains
the system architecture work is not
really
up there yet so so
it is
it is uh
not
done at all of course
you always have some kind of
architecture
but but you might not really be be aware
of it or you might not be documenting it
or analyzing it and and
and
or or you could just doing partial
partial architecture work so some some
architectures especially the kind of
speciality engineering areas like like
integrated logistics support there you
need to do
some some of the the functional
architecture views for for for that part
but but it could be that
those views are not then used for
for for other purposes
so it in
i i think this is kind of worst case
scenario but in in worst case you could
have different teams
in the same project uh
developing kind of architecture
views uh even same
view that and ending up with a bit
different
different results and not kind of
sharing it as a common
common view and and
and so
that might be the reason so without kind
of uh
an architect description a good
architecture description or at least
awareness of how to work with an
architecture
it might be difficult to start working
with them
with model based systems engineering i i
know that that you could also say that
that using
model-based systems engineering tools
and methods they that could help you to
start
start doing the architecture work
properly so of course there is that that
that
will be also so it could be could be
other way around also but
that might be
that might be one reason and
and the second reason is because you you
are
of course
advocates of of model-based systems
engineering so uh
i'm not sure if you like this but but uh
it might be that the second reason is
the
the high level of skills needed for
using the the current
mbsc methods and tools so so
it could be that the investment for for
skills
is considered too high at the moment so
of course
you you need
need to
need to kind of feel some
pain
usually before you before you kind of
make a decision for
for doing investment so so uh
whichever if you are doing process
development or competence development or
or developing methods and tools so
usually you usually you have to have big
enough a problem before you make the
decision that you you make the
investment and start doing something so
it could be that that people are just
managing with the
or coping with the with the current
methods and tools
yeah that would be interesting if the
the finnish companies don't feel the
pain or don't have the pain
to apply
mbs e so
you need a purpose to do mpse um and
maybe it's not not there or not the
pressure is not high enough for for some
reasons that's i think that's quite
interesting
and of course the investment is very
high
and it costs time
it's not
which time is also money
but
yeah you cannot introduce mbse methods
and tools in a in a single short-term
project or so that cost months or years
to really effectively apply it that's
interesting
yeah speaking of pain
if people work with mbse
they also feel some pain have questions
how to do this and then they
typically organize themselves in
working groups uh uh things like this so
is there a working group in the local
chapter of in cozy or
is there a local chapter in cozy
yes yes we we have a local chapter of
incosi
the finnish chapter is is called finse
so finnish systems engineering
association in english
and it's it has been
going on quite a long time already but
uh but uh we have
uh quite quite uh low number of
of of members in finca but uh but we
anyways we have tried to try to organize
uh
events uh
some events few events every every
year and and
and also this topic of model based
systems engineering has has been
uh
kind of raised by the by the by the
members and and that's that's something
that we have been discussing that that
we should
organize at at least some kind of
of of event discussing this this topic
but at the moment
there are no no working groups within
within
our
local
local uh chapter and i'm i'm not not
really aware of of any other
uh finnish organizations or that that
might have
have uh
any any kind of interest groups in in
model based systems engineering so
that is the that is the current current
status as as i know so again if i'm
wrong just contact me and
and tell me i'm happy happy to say that
i i was wrong okay
yeah
so question
uh yeah the one one area was was that i
i i forgot to mention was this uh
these um
these uh i i know that there are these
um
interest groups or working groups uh
related to to kind of modeling and
simulation
in general so so so
about to my understanding they are they
are focusing on
on uh
domain specific modeling not
system level modeling so
okay okay got it got it
um but of those few you know that who
are practicing mbse or se
um
what are the typical challenges for them
in finland
uh
i i think that um
you know overall
if you think about uh the the for
example that in cosi the finnish chapter
in cozy here in finland what what up
what is
what is our problem or or or
my my company uh
the kind of the the business challenges
for
for trying to
trying to to promote
systems engineering is is the
the
general uh
unawareness
of systems
engineering here in finland so so that
is probably
the the biggest challenge that that
it is it is very difficult to start
talking about systems engineering and
people don't have might not have
uh
idea of what what it is usually it's
it's they are thinking that it's
something related to software
and
so
i i know that there are companies that
have
good
knowledge and skills of systems
engineering but
overall it's
it has been a challenge
to to to
to start promoting systems engineering
um
of course
some companies are doing part of part of
the
part parts of systems engineering
but they might call it something else so
that's that's also one way to
start discussing about systems
engineering but um
that is that is probably the challenge
and that is
the reason why
myself i i am not
i am not a systems engineering
consultant or systems engineering
trainer by by name because i i have
chosen to use more general term
engineering management
so it's probably
much easier to to to kind of understand
that if we talk about engineering
management
of course it's it's not one-to-one with
with with systems engineering but i i
think it's it has been a little bit
easier for using using that kind of
umbrella
but
the the challenge for the mbsc i think
it's it's the general lack of
understanding of systems engineering so
i think that for me
model-based systems engineering is
systems engineering it is
kind of methods and tools for doing
systems engineering and and if if you
don't have kind of the
the starting point there if you don't
have understanding of systems
engineering then it might be
might be a little bit uh difficult to
to to start
start
implementing or even start discussing
about model based systems engineering so
that that might be the
might be the
the biggest challenge
for mbsc in finland
so well one action to increase the
awareness is to talk about systems
engineering
again and again so um
and well there's the nordic systems
engineering uh
uh last week the tour
was uh yeah we had the tour only
virtually uh so it was not the real tour
but um well you are one of the
organizers of the tour um as part of the
finnish chapters so
can you briefly explain the concept of
the tour and
report a bit of the tour last week
yes thank you
yes the
nordic systems engineering tour i think
it's a quite unique concept
uh usually when when you organize
conferences you you uh
uh select uh some kind of a bigger city
somewhere and and and bring all the
speakers and and and the audience there
and and uh then it tooks a lot of
traveling for for the for the
participants and and uh it might be
quite expensive to to to visit this kind
of conferences but for the nordic
systems engineering tour the concept has
been
kind of turned uh around so we we try to
bring the the speakers to to the
audience so so the the idea of the tour
is that that
we select
uh
several uh
good speakers several interesting themes
and and uh then we organize uh a
kind of conference tour
uh
for example
lately it has been like starting from
from helsinki then to stockholm
then to um copenhagen or or oslo and and
and even some uh
year we we also had poland and warsaw as
one of the one of the destinations so so
and and then
then the speakers have have the the the
challenge of of touring around and and
then presenting in every
every location and and uh the
participants have them a little bit
less traveling and it's it's easier than
for them to participate and also the the
cost for participation is is lower and
and
of course for us for for the finnish
chapter of incosive has been a
very um
good opportunity for for having this uh
this cooperation with the the the other
other incosi chapters because we are we
are a small chapter as i said and it's
very difficult for us to organize
big events so this this one is is is
quite easy event for us so that we can
we can kind of be part of the the bigger
organization and and and it provides for
our members a good opportunity to get
get the speakers all around the world to
to to to come to finland and and present
their
topics but uh as you mentioned uh
this uh
this uh pandemic situation has been
causing
some problems so last year we we had to
cancel the
the the whole tour
and uh this year we were planning to
organize it uh as a as it has been
earlier but then we
had to
have to uh make a decision that that
okay we cannot make a make a real
physical tour if there were two too high
risks of canceling
cancellations and and so on so we we
decided then to have a online
event and it was only for usually it's a
one day event in every country but did
now it was just one online event where
we had people from
from from different countries and and we
had four speakers
and and various topics and and
there were
around 100 people uh
joining the
the conference this year which i thought
was was really
really good amount of people and i i
think that there were
even people from from countries that are
not part of the the tour stops regular
tour stops so i think that provided also
opportunity for
for those people to participate so i
think that was that was really good
so we had we had really nice nice events
so i think that even even though we
didn't manage to do it as as as we we
planned so uh i think the online event
was
was uh was still a good good event for
for for us and hopefully also for the
participants
and hopefully next year the tour will
hit the road again
and it will be a real physical tour
yeah
yeah i'm hoping that too
and christian it was also part of the
tour right
two years ago three years ago yeah but
unfortunately in this year we did not
have a stop in finland
we were in hamburg copenhagen
lynch shopping
and that
that was it
yeah i i think that finland became part
of the tour only
2015 so so we haven't been there from
the beginning
yeah
okay so
go on
yeah but uh as i said great event for
for for absolutely finnish uh in cozy
and
and its members so i think that that's
uh that's uh and we are we are
hopefully
kind of uh
willing to to to put some effort also
for the future years to be part of this
this this event yeah the two also
supported the the foundation of the
danish chapter in 2013 or 14 or so i
remember when the tour stopped there
uh there was during the foundation phase
of the chapter and it was very good for
them uh that they had already had a
systems engineering event then and uh it
was the same for the polish chapter so
it was very helpful for them so systems
engineering the chapter was very small
and poland was still this i don't know
um and was also very good for them i
think it was there twice in poland
that's great and there's another
tour in
southern europe the southern europe
systems engineering tour so that's the
name of italy spain
italy spain france and switzerland
yeah great and david long i think if i
remember correctly also tried to copy it
in in the us there was a eastern coast
tour so oh
east coast tour yes i think something
like that
yeah i think that the concept is very
interesting and as as we see there are
there are already
copies of it and i think that it's it's
we are very happy that that people are
using the concept yeah
yeah so great uh oh we yeah we have a
few minutes left so finally let's talk a
little bit more about you not about
finland and the two of us uh about you
so
you already told us a bit that you
are our consultant um
and so what's your daily job then in
system setting when you consult a
customer
yes as i said said that my my studies
there at frankfurt university was kind
of a
life changer and career changes so so
since then i have been more or less
used to systems engineering
daily in my work and and
last eight years i have been
i have been running this this small
small company and and
i'm trying to help my
my customers
using systems engineering and what i
have been doing mainly is i have been
working mainly with
with with requirements so with
stakeholder and system requirements
definition
and and i have done quite a lot of work
for
helping to define and building up
processes and and uh and tools for for
requirements and also configuration
management which are of course
important part when when if when you are
doing
doing uh
systems engineering in in general and
and of course
related processes so so when you work
with
with requirements as trying to capture
the the needs and
and
requirements so it includes also the
the architecture work that i i already
mentioned
you work also with the integration
planning of integration
activities and and of course at the same
time planning of verification and and
validation
depending on on the needs of the of the
customers and and uh and of course the
current phase of the of the life cycle
of the system of inter interest
whichever whichever system of interest
you are working with so quite uh varying
scope
scope of consulting
contacts consulting
activities there and
and then the other part is is
maybe not daily but but weekly
activities are related then to
to these
training courses
engineering management training courses
as we call them but
they they are based on
very much on on systems engineering
systems engineering principles and and
for that it's it's kind of a
regular uh entrepreneur work that i'm
trying to do sales and
and marketing of for the courses and and
practical hands-on stuff for preparing
the courses materials and
and venues and and so on so uh you can
you can do quite varying tasks as a
working in a small company
and of course then delivering the
courses in
either
online or or hopefully in the future
also also again at the classroom
it even sounds like it's pretty
plm related depending on where the
customer is at the moment
yeah that's that's true yeah yeah i
think that
that
i i always
uh
when you talk about the the the
kind of the
product
life cycle product information i i for
for me it's it's every everything is
related to configuration management so i
think
my right my umbrella term for for that
is but of course you need different
different uh methods and tools for for
implementing that that those those
configuration management
processes and methods that that you are
defining so of course you end up usually
working with
with with product data management
systems and and
and so on so that's that's
that's where you you do the
implementation part
okay
so
well i think time is up
uh
so
it was very interesting rico thank you
very much
thank you for joining our podcast
and uh we've got some insights and mbse
systems in general in in finland
um
now we're at sweden finland now we need
denmark and norway
northern and european countries yeah yes
right
yeah but uh well the next topic uh the
next episode is not mbse around the
world um
next time we
look on the
framework the unified architecture
framework uaf and our guest will be
already used from the soul
who is one of the masterminds behind
uaf um which is developed and maintained
by the automogee
and we already have this time we have a
date
october the 15th so in around three
weeks uh around about three weeks
um
yeah so
i hope you join us uh same time um
seven o'clock first entry ukraine time
yeah and then well
christian no do not forget
trust us
we are systems engineers
right
goodbye