welcome to a new episode of the mbse
podcast
today we will
have a meeting on the west coast of the
united states so to say so good morning
to our guest chris delp who is a group
supervisor nasa jpl
so that jet propulsion laboratory if you
don't know it
and one of the masterminds behind
openmbe
we know chris very well from various omg
meetings but please chris introduce
yourself first
yeah i think i think you covered it i
work at the jet propulsion laboratory
i'm the group supervisor for the
software systems solutions engineering
group and our group
produces the systems engineering
environment led by robert carban who's a
another mbse celebrity
um
and uh for for the missions that we
produce at jpl
and i was also part of the original team
that came up with openmb at jpl
yeah great so great to have you on the
show chris and
well probably not everyone knows openmbe
so the first question is what is openmb
what does it stand for and well how did
it come about
so openmb stands for the open model
based engineering environment uh and the
the general premise of openmb is that
it's firstly a community in the open
source world
around model-based engineering practices
models and software that support
model-based engineering
so you have to know a little bit about
what model-based engineering is there's
probably some debate around what that is
i think in the openmb community we're
less about defining what that is
um and more about
just you know enabling the practices and
helping the whole concept and evolve so
whatever your model is
uh
openmb wants to talk about it
the
products that exist are i'm sorry as an
open source project you're supposed
about projects so the projects that
exist in openmbe
are principally
the open se cookbook which was
contributed by robert carbon
the
model the model management system which
is the core
uh server product around managing
engineering models
the view editor which is a web
application that allows uh document
based interactivity around
it's a model based document application
is maybe a better way to say it
that allows you to integrate the
descriptions of
different models
um
and then the mdk
collection which is the model
development kit so various tools
uh
that perform different kinds of modeling
we have an architecture called the mdk
the most famous one is the magic draw i
guess now cameo
model development kit which integrates
magic draws to smell
uh bpmn etc into the openmb
open source environment so
these products exist
they don't but they don't necessarily
limit the definition of what openmb is
openmb is firstly a community uh like i
said so
um
some some misunderstandings are oh well
if i don't have anything that integrates
with nms view editor then i'm not part
of openmb that's definitely not the case
but anybody who has open source models
open source practices anything they want
to bring and contribute to openmb as
that open source community that's really
the
beach head that we're
trying to forward of things along on
and chris can you
give us a little bit more uh historic
information so what what was the
motivation to do something like
it's a huge thing sure in
mean time
sure it has it i think it has kind of an
interesting origin story um
and the word part of the origin story
comes from
iso and robert carbon who i mentioned a
few times so he'd have to tell the eso
side
but the jpl side
occurred when i was early in my career
at jpl model-based systems engineering
was very new
and i think the prevailing premise at
the time was that
documents are bad and documents are
going to go away and someday everybody
will just be working with models
um
in retrospect probably a bit naive uh
especially considering that probably
lots of software developers had similar
uh hopes of that someday their code
would just be self-documenting
yeah so we started uh on a project at
jpl to modernize
mission operations with modeling
um
and
what we what we found initially is that
and kind of organically was that
while the while the models were great
for solving engineering problems we had
a difficult time communicating them um a
lot of people in systems engineering
traditionally
uh build
uh documents right and
so for folks who were interested in
models they couldn't reconcile the
models they were making with the
products that they were being asked to
produce
um
and so we started connecting the two up
how can we you know take these models
and generate the products that people
need uh and that's where the first
kernel of openmb of the jpl side was
born
called doctrine so doctrine built an
executable modeling language
to generate the actual the document to
query the model
and and basically linearize a particular
story or viewpoint into how the
uh
how the how the model is describing
something and that's when we discovered
ieee 1471
whereas it's i think now referred to as
iso 4 2010 which is the standard for our
systems architecture description
and that talks about view and viewpoints
um and that was a real game changer
because the model could now be unified
with the products that that systems
engineers needed to make
and they suddenly had a whole new avenue
of controlling the quality of the
technical content
so the thought experiment i always give
in this part is kind of like you know if
you have
uh somebody who's got like a really
great simulink model and it can answer
all kinds of questions about the system
or maybe in today's speed could be more
of a cst model the next cable system
model or a delica model or something um
and you've got your requirements and
doors or whatever
uh
and then you've got um
um
the presentations you have to give right
and in these powerpoint decks so um
you've got all this rich technical
content
um
but how do you get it into
something that people can consume in
these reviews so
um
you can imagine having
having the live connection to all that
information would be a much richer
experience so that
that kind of became the goal um
we started generating the documents
magic draw is a desktop tool so suddenly
everybody's desktop was filling up with
documents we created a platform called
doc web which basically just
automated the production of those
documents and stored them on the web so
that you could browse them
and users just loved it and the first
question they asked was where's the edit
button and then uh view editor and mms
were born out of that so
um
and it's so it's a lot of it is built
around
web-based concepts and bringing that
information to the web
and also for me personally kind of
reconciling that idea
that no
not everybody's going to use models
and that really there's still a
communication practice and systems
engineering that has to take place where
we can linearize the story and
communicate these views
across disciplines
and pull
pull people's uh
disparate models in in together to that
story earlier
um and that leads of course to the
digital twin and perpetual you know
continuous integration and all that
stuff so
uh if i understood it correctly you
started with system a right you
mentioned magic draw models and so so
you starting with system models
and which other kind of models are
can also be integrated in in the mms
so today's mms
comes in
today's released mms comes in a flavor
where you can publish the json format of
any model into the mms
um
so
what you get out of the box today uh
pretty much anything that can interact
with web services like python or
mathematica or something like that
can produce and consume models in this
way
um
and of course we have the magic draw
integration
and i believe i believe there is
somebody who has contributed an early
papyrus integration but i haven't seen
it yet
um
and there there are there are other
contributions coming that i can't talk
about yet um
but the the the next version of mms
is ms5 is completely transformational
the
a long
a long sought technology that we waited
a long time to mature was the graph
database
i think we we all in this sphere have
seen the significance of graphs in in
how models are
handled in technology
um
but when we built the first version of
the mms such things were
fantasy only
even the even the fledgling
things that existed out there even the
things you could buy were were
difficult to scale there were no
standard interfaces
you know things like gremlin tinker pop
didn't exist the semantic web community
existed but they didn't have the
uh technology horsepower to build
horizontally scalable web services that
could handle
millions of millions of elements you
know if you
look at the amount of model elements and
then something something from like
boeing who's one of the openmb
contributors i mean they have
more model elements that i could ever
even have dreamed
and we were stunned when they were able
to put them all into mms we're like wow
we didn't
we had no idea that it could scale
okay that sounds uh
very very interesting and promising so
um
maybe we should
tell the people how they can try it by
their own so how how can i get openmbe
is this a web service is it something i
can download
it it's both actually so and that's a
that's a good question so
openmb is open source um
and it's available on openmb.org
and for the mms in particular
i think the cautionary tale that always
comes here is
it's it is a web service so you so in
order to get it working
you will either have to know how to
install and administrate
a linux server essentially
and so sometimes that that definitely
catches people by surprise they download
them onto their laptop and then they
can't figure out what to do
so yeah it's not a standalone desktop um
there is a host and environment
provided by the so that
is used by the omg and some other
activities
so you can at least test
test it out yourself and and test taste
it if you like
um
and kind of see how it works
so those are the two options there are
uh the opensc cookbook of course you can
download and load that into magic draw
or read the documents of it um
and the magic drop the magic drop plugin
for openmb does allow you to do things
with doctrine and and stuff like that
locally in your magic draw desktop
sessions without connecting to mms um
so yeah that's that's kind of a high
level uh picture and of course you can
also attend the openmp community
meetings which happen uh every two weeks
um
and the upcoming openmb workshop at the
coc you can cociw this weekend
or monday technically
so
what would you recommend a real
industrial project uh if they would like
to use openmpe so what well is it
recommendable for for a real project to
use it or
uh well you need support and things like
that so what what were the first steps
or what would you recommend for them
and that's that's an interesting thread
of discussion as well um
the use of open source software in
various
industrial scale organizations
runs the spectrum on earth today
some some companies obviously like
google or
maybe spacex are
are hawkishly
forward-looking in this space
more traditional defense industry folks
are more reluctant and of course with
open source in general there's a
range of misnomers
i think the log for j issue recently
helps people understand that just
because you buy something from a vendor
doesn't mean you're not using open
source
it just means
it just means you're paying for it so um
so for somebody starting out like that i
mean i think firstly it's kind of a
an
introspective in the company
like how does that company use open
source what kind of resources do they
have um for for companies that have very
old school i.t departments where they
mostly host file servers and license
servers and haven't gotten into web
services yet it'll it'll be
uh
more of it i won't say necessarily more
of a challenge but it'll be more effort
so
because using using the mms in
particular means you're potentially
pushing on the company's posture towards
a shift towards web services from
traditional
computing services
um
and mms4 is horizontally scalable it
runs if you run it on docker so
um
it'll it'll
it'll it potentially could use a lot of
computers so um
and
that so that's kind of where it starts
and then from there you know then the
main thing is are you are you ready to
put something like that together um
and so
how that's worked
from an experiential standpoint i mean
if you look at how boeing deployed
openmb
they have a
really really big enterprise i.t system
and they were able to
you know make those deployments
work they contribute back code they're
they're fully in
um but they had to go through their own
stuff so that that would that probably
that might not be a bad podcasting day
to get them to talk about
what they can talk about um
whereas if you look at uh
i won't
if you look at like how how ford is
initially set it up uh i think they
started as kind of with a kind of a
small r d
effort just to kind of see what it did
as part of how they were investigating
mbsc in general
um
so and then
the
the corporate side as well because i
mentioned vendors specifically
uh some vendors have adopted openmv
technology into their product as well um
one of them of course the most famous
one of course being no magic now just so
um
they pulled aspects of it into their
products so
and then the main the main pieces of
openmb use uh
the apache 2 license which is commercial
friendly
so
vendors can some vendors have taken
openmv technology and chosen not to
disclose
that they've done it
um
and that's
they're fine to do so
uh
the
the sound bite i always give on this is
you know jpl's participation in this was
we we couldn't buy what we needed to do
what we needed to do at the time and so
we built it
but that didn't signal that we were
ready to move into
uh
building software products instead of
space missions really
we open sourced it
as a way to communicate the requirements
of what we need
and what happened is this you know along
with how with eso and and then later
boeing this turned into this uh
you know movement of different points of
view around how open source can work
with engineering environments and models
and so forth so
cool
so let's assume i
download the thing install it and
i like it um how can i get in touch with
the openmbe community you already
mentioned that there will be a workshop
on the
international workshop from ecosi next
week
and
i guess there is a public select channel
isn't it
correct yeah if you go to openmb.org you
can click the participate link at the
top and you'll see the slack channel
you'll see the google group
the github repo
um the the the folks in openmb for
example who are developers
tend mostly to communicate on github
they're not
not chatty folks you can ping them on
slack channel but as tim has seen
sometimes it takes some uh
nudging to get them to respond um
and uh the google group of course and
then we have a
a community presentation meeting every
every month a couple times a month and
the leadership meeting so and it's
entirely open anybody can participate in
the leadership meeting
or the community meeting uh provided
that ever there's a consensus that the
topics they're bringing up are are part
of our scope and charter so
there's no formal organization behind
openmb there's no the openmpe limited so
it's just a group of people mainly
stuff by by people from nasa jpl then
that's correct
it is
the the community itself is
is i would say
at the moment there are folks from ford
boeing
lockheed
um
i believe there's still some folks
showing up from raytheon
uh from the academic side there's folks
from georgia tech and stevens
uh and of course jpl and we have had
other nasa folks show up outside jpl 2
occasionally
um
the
software portion the the asset portion
of openmb is
sponsored by num focus which is an open
source software foundation similar to
apache or clips or something like that
and the main service they provide is
uh
indemnification
so
they are there to help open source
projects protect their assets because
one of the reasons we chose the apache 2
license is because there are cases where
other open source licenses or even no
open source license published with the
code
has allowed folks to patent it and then
sue the creators for possessing it
so
um at least that's what i was told
i don't have a specific example for that
that's that's that was one of the uh uh
highlights that we got from folks in
apache about why the apache 2 license is
good so but num focus protects you know
the openmp name trademark uh copyright
all that kind of stuff so that
um
we have that that so
yeah but the community at large is is
um
it's kind of the community at large so
it's intended to be open we do publish a
uh
a code of conduct i think we use the
inner source con the open source commons
i think it's called source conduct so um
but it's a yeah open source communities
are largely self-governing uh funding is
you know
there's no no you ask
there's no owner of openmp no
the owner of the open open is the
community
that's correct
and and it's licensed as such so
um
yeah any any
anybody can fork it own it use it and
you know it's in some ways it's like a
new way of standardizing things right so
um
but code is a little more complex than
documents so
and uh if i'm a vendor and i would like
to contribute
an integration to my tool
um
is this
is this possible in an easy way and
is it still my code how does that work
sure no that's a really good question i
mean if if a vendor wanted to
integrate with openmd there's no
requirement that they contribute any of
that code um
they they would they could build a
completely commercial integration
um
and
yeah
and if they if that's how they choose to
do it that's how they choose to do it
they could open source
uh
the integration as well um and maintain
it through openmbe
um
yeah i think that's
that's
a pretty open
uh
situation
about how daso has done it is they took
portions of the openmb code integrated
it into their product and then they sell
that commercial product um
and i think that's fine i call this kind
of the technical morality case right i
think the openmb community is concerned
with the
technical correctness of
a model based engineering environment
and the code that supports it
so in that respect somebody who's
offering that as a service is i think
absolutely welcome to
commercialize that and take advantage of
that
like so many
organizations have with open source
software like ibm's recent acquisition
of red hat for example linux kernel
still open source so and now you have to
pay well i guess you always have to pay
for red hat at some level but yeah it
seems like it's getting a little tighter
now
no more centos the same way it used to
be so is there already a
full service provider for openmb a
professional one or do you think that
there will be some service providers in
the future where i can as a company just
buy it like i can buy teamwork cloud
server today
um i think
i i haven't seen anybody that's offering
that um
directly um i know of cases where
vendors or contractors have made such
arrangements with organizations
um
so but no there isn't like a
a commercial enterprise as yet that has
appeared
to provide openmb as a product
um
like you might like red hat or something
like that
um
but
hey i think i think actually sysiml 2
will will really push on that so the
the key the key feat the key future
features of the openmb software are
really aiming towards the system l2
world um
as well as kind of a unified graph world
too so if you look at the architecture
description that's published for mms
five
it really paints a clear path for how
the mms will support the system l2
service api
but also how it will be capable of
providing
support for
other
model based formats like graphql or oslc
or such like that
and and provide have the facilities
behind the scenes to have a scalable
unified graph
of information behind it so
um
i think i think that's where the future
is
is coming and it will
it'll be more and more of a
heterogeneous enterprise so
i do know that boeing certified their
their open their
uh
deployment of openmb to the dl178
standard so it is qualifiable in that
respect
and can you name some other projects or
companies that already use openmv you so
you mentioned boeing and i guess nasa
also uses
openmpe
but there are there other ones
um
yeah i think uh i think i think ford is
going to do their pre do a presentation
on it um
at the workshop so that'll be something
to see i know stevens has done a lot
with it in the research and educational
community as has georgetech
um and i think one of the videos on
uh
youtube
actually shows a piece part of the
presentation shows
so highlights some of the organizations
that use it and of course as we were
talking about earlier uh some parts of
the omg are starting to use it
the sysml2 spec
team
is actually using it to generate the
system l2 specification um using system
l one and two i guess
um
so it's uh
yeah there are there are others not
everybody that i know about has
explicitly authorized me to
tell that story for them so
in some cases they've explicitly asked
me not to um so
yeah
but the the that that video has has the
the list
uh okay robert put it together in his
methodical way so
um
yeah i guess we will provide the link in
the description of the video here
and people can look it up we also said
um
yeah that we will
oh we already have linked the openmbe
youtube channel from our channel you can
switch over
a lot of interesting stuff there
yeah yeah you can get a demo without
installing it
yeah it's good to see that but i think
what's also emerged
as the most novel feature of view editor
is this notion of transclusion so
the inventor of the hyperlink whose name
escapes me at the moment
also invented this this concept called
transclusion which is like a reverse
hyperlink
where you dereference the content behind
the link and display it in place
um so in terms of
software application novelty the heart
of view editor is this ability to
transclude or as we locally refer to it
as cross-reference
pieces of the model in the document to
make it communicatable so
um
and that that simple principle pervades
all aspects of the software so
yeah and you can also edit the model
through the view editor right so some
some elements
correct
correctly that's
that's that's part of that notion
actually that because it's
cross-referenced
when you go to edit it you're actually
editing with the actual model element
and the repository not
not a wiki page that talks about it and
lets it get out of sync and stuff like
that so when you when you edit it in one
view
those edits will show up in all your
documents because it's using this
transclusion feature to be referenced
the content from a central location
cool
pretty cool
so now i can store many different models
in in the mms there can be a system
model bpmn
modelica or whatever everything can be
in mms and are these models in mms all
mix up or can can jump from one model to
another or
are they still insiders in the mms
so it's a big question so the key to
this interpolability issue
right right no the so the organizational
uh
schema if you will of mms is similar to
github so we have uh an org and a
project and then within that project you
can have multiple models
uh each of the models are are version
controlled um
and the uh
and and you can branch and stuff like
that
um
in in
in mms4 it doesn't have the greatest
merge capability
largely because
um
in modeling like
the the notion of of diff and merge is a
lot more sophisticated than it is in uh
um
in software code yeah exactly and i
think that i think actually the libra
libra folks
have uh included mms now in there i
should have thought of that on your
earlier question i think they've
included mms now in their lemon tree
product
um
that that that so you can buy that
additional capability there but yeah all
the models will go in there it's it's a
it's got a lot of the basic get features
around being able to branch
um and it keeps version history and
stuff like that so um that's the basic
organizational ski schema the key
difference between mms4 and mms 5
is the semantics of the model
in mms4 would still need to be added if
you wanted the service to understand
them so the service right now stores the
model but it doesn't really know about
the meaning of the model so like magic
drop for example extracts it but we rely
on the magic drop client to understand
it um
so and if you're working like python or
something like that then similarly you'd
have that situation an mms5 however with
the introduction of the graph database
uh you'll have those semantics stored in
the graph as part of what the model is
um so
that's the key distinction there
yeah and a very challenging technical
uh
activity
yes
sounds promising now
so i think we
will keep up with this topic and i guess
this would not be the last episode about
it
yeah chris uh then i would say
thank you very much for all the
information um
it was a pleasure uh having you on the
show
um tim what's our next topic
uh the next topic is model based product
line engineering and our guest will be
marco valengiri from airbus
and
that's scheduled for february the 7th
this monday
and same time
cool
yeah so
go ahead
yeah i i just wanted to remind uh all
our listeners who did not subscribe to
the youtube channel yet to do so chris
did uh some some weeks ago i saw
and yeah so you don't miss any other
episode
okay and so finally
our last words do not forget
trust us
we are systems engineers
okay bye-bye
bye chris