Welcome behind the 8th door of
our MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
We take a look at the
Domain Knowledge Model
For the object flows in
the Use Case Activities
We have defined the
types of flowing objects
These are mostly blocks and value types
of the Domain Knowledge Model
Or put in another way
The Domain Knowledge Model
defines the types of objects
that the system uses in its functions
So, let's take a look
at the model
and look again on the Use Case Activity
"Enjoy Christmas tree"
There are only a few object
types in this diagram
like "SI_Power", "HI_Light" and
"Flashing Program"
The prefix "SI_" indicates that
this is an object type
that occurs in a system
interface to another system
In the prefix "HI_" indicates that
this is an object type
that occurs in a systematic
phase to a human
These types are defined besides others
in the Domain Knowledge Model
which is partially depicted in
the following block definition diagram
The value type "Centimeter" is a
specialization of the primitive type
"Integer" from the SysML library
It is our decision that we take
"Integer" values for "Centimeter"
an alternative for example
would be "Real"
SysML also explicitly supports
the modeling of units
However we did not use
that for simplicity
Of course, all these types from
the Domain Knowledge Model
are good candidates
for a modern library
The Domain Knowledge represents
the knowledge of your system
If you ask your system do you know
the concept of "Flashing Program"
it can answer
"Sure, of course I know this"
"I know it like it's defined
in the domain block"
If you ask the system
about "Christmas Gifts"
it has no clue what
you are talking about
So much for the 8th door of
our MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 8th of December
Goodbye
Bye-bye