welcome behind the eight door of our
mbse podcast advent calendar we take a
look at the domain knowledge model
for the object flows in the use case
activities we have defined the types of
flowing objects
these are mostly blocks and value types
of the domain knowledge model
or put in another way the domain
knowledge model defines the types of
objects that the system uses in its
functions
so let's take a look at the model and
look again on the use case activity
enjoy christmas tree
there are only a few object types in
this diagram like si power hi light and
flashing program
the prefix si indicates that this is an
object type that occurs in a system
interface to another system
in the prefix hi indicates that this is
an object type that occurs in a
systematic phase to a human
these types are defined besides others
in the domain knowledge model which is
partially depicted in the falling block
definition diagram
the value type centimeter is a
specialization of the primitive type
integer from the system library
it is our decision that we take integer
values for centimeter an alternative for
example would be real
system l also explicitly supports the
modeling of units however we did not use
that for simplicity
of course all these types from the
domain knowledge model are good
candidates for a modern library
the domain knowledge represents the
knowledge of your system
if you ask your system do you know the
concept of flashing program it can
answer sure of course i know this i know
it like it's defined in the domain block
if you ask the system about christmas
gifts is has no clue what you are
talking about
much for the eight door of our mbse
podcast advent calendar and we wish you
a great 8th of december
goodbye
bye