okay so good evening and welcome to our
mbse podcast and this time christian and i
are doing a new episode of our series mbse
around the world after sweden and then china
this time we visited the united kingdom and
we want to see how mbse is doing there we
are happy to have Jon Holt as our guest and
i think no one can tell us better about it
so and w ho Jon is uh he will tell you best uh
himself so please join introduce yourself okay
thanks very much tim and uh first of all thanks
to tim and christian for inviting me along it's a
it's a pleasure and an honor to be with you so for
people who don't know who i am my name is Jon Holt
and um i've been doing mbsc for my
whole career now so for almost 30 years
i work for a company called scarecrow consultants
limited uh we're based in the uk i'm personally
based in wales in the uk so for those of you in
europe wales is the slightly wet country to the
left of england for those of you in america it's
near london somewhere i'm also um a professor of
systems engineering at cranfield university here
in the uk and if people are aware of in cosi the
international council on systems engineering i'm
the current technical director of new incosy uk
and i've offered 17 books on model-based
systems engineering and its application
in over over the years so that's a
that's a very brief introduction to me
wonderful yeah thank you Jon so also from
my side a very warm welcome and yeah as
the technical director uh you for sure can
tell us in which industries in the uk is
systems engineering or maybe already
model-based systems engineering used
well it's interesting because i think the same as
many countries historically systems engineering
and therefore model-based systems engineering
has been very strong for decades in aerospace
and defense but what we're seeing now is lots of
other uh different industries coming on board and
i think one of the biggest ones at the moment is
automotive so you know from about five or seven
years ago all of a sudden uh automotive has become
massive and and i think this is important because
i think um what's important about some uh well all
industries in particular automotive i use those
as the example is because of the the complexity of
the vehicles of the systems that they're producing
has increased so dramatically over the last few
years in particular in areas like uh everything
is now connected so every device we buy now is
now connected everything is potentially part of a
wider system of systems and all of a sudden we've
seen this sort of this step change in complexity
because of that and because of the different
technologies involved and because of things
like constraints so safety security standards and
so on and also shifts in technology so getting
automotive away from internal combustion engines
over to electric it's been a massive change and a
shift in complexity and i think in order to cope
with this complexity the i think the techniques
we were using 10 20 30 years ago a document based
approach and don't get me wrong there's nothing
wrong with a document-based approach it's not
incorrect but i think a document-based approach
that worked 10 or 20 years ago is no longer
adequate for the job because the complexity has
increased so much and i think as the complexity
of our systems that we're developing increases
therefore the complexity of the approach that
we're taking to develop those systems must also
increase and we've seen lots of other areas as
well so automotive is a very good example but
also medical devices we see now the last couple
of years we've been involved in that um energy as
well so uh right from the whole spectrum from sort
of nuclear fusion and we're even doing some work
in steam power at the moment so we're covering
uh both ends of the spectrum of of energy though
but yes certainly we've seen more and more
diverse industries uh adopting model-based
systems engineering and very importantly because
it's the need that's there it's not because it's
the flavor of the month or it sounds good
it sounds exciting it's because there's a
genuine need there to cope with this increased
complexity that we're seeing in all of our systems
well yeah and for what what purposes mbse use now
you can use it for for different purposes you can
increase the communication between the team
and you can use it to specify things or you can
satisfy assessors with tons of generated documents
now you can do already simulation stuff and
other cool things so is there um a special focus
in the uk well i mean we work with uh we work with
all different industries and lots of different
companies academia and government and it's been
used in all sorts of different areas and one
of the things that i mean one of the things
about model-based systems engineering is if you
do a google search on the benefits of model-based
systems engineering what comes up is lots of tool
vendors say look what my tool does look what my
tool does and they're not really the benefits of
mbsc they're things that the tool will do and i
think that the benefits of our sort of context
dependence it really depends on the stakeholders
you're talking to so we can deal with the same
organization and if we deal with the engineers we
can say it's great it's going to improve your your
specification your design your requirements and so
on but if we say that to a manager they're
not interested so if we talk to a manager
we'll focus on well it will improve your cost
timing resource estimates and if we're dealing
with somebody at board level we've got to focus on
things like return on investment and improvement
of the quality attributes of the systems so
it does vary enormously but i think all of the
all of the topics that you mentioned uh there
tim are definitely uh you know we've seen it
used in all of those areas um but it really
does vary and as i say we work with some
organizations where different teams are getting
different benefits from using nbc ranging from
you know one company we want to half up
our development time you know we want to
go from a six year cycle to a three year cycle and
whereas others are we want to improve our quality
but what is interesting is we find in that
particular industries are interested in uh or
and this is a very broad generalization but
tend to be interested in different aspects of it
so it's interesting you mentioned quality
when we deal with medical devices company
their main emphasis seems to be on can we
comply with the standards and the legislation
because if we can't we can't sell our products
so for them that's the most important thing
we deal with sort of aerospace type companies
with typically long life cycles and they're
more more interesting can we shorten our life
cycles so it really depends on the you know
the stakeholders we're talking to but we do see
these trends in industries and we see a lot more
collaboration now between organizations you know
whereas historically uh people were more insular
we see a lot more collaborations and that's
where areas like tim you mentioned the improved
communication between the different stakeholders
and we're seeing that an awful lot as well now so
yeah it's and i think it's because we work in
lots of different industries that we can see these
different applications being used and i think if
you were taught if you were to talk to somebody
who worked in a single organization which is most
people let's face it they would give you a more
definitive answer this is how we use it this
is how we use it and one of the big areas that
we do use it for across industry is in defining
an approach to model-based systems engineering
so actually using the modeling using an mbse
approach to understand what their business
business needs are to help them change the
business and you know my personal philosophy is
when it comes to deploying mbse i treat that
like a system so of course i'm going to apply
mbse to do that and and that's that's a really
interesting area that's a lot more prevalent now
than we saw um you know just just a few years ago
and uh can you estimate how well mbse is used in
the different industries so is uh defense and
space still decades ahead or is it changing no
i i really don't think they are anymore and and
i think that one of the reasons for this is if we
take industries like automotive uh medical devices
the life cycles are far shorter and so they need
to get in quicker and get the returns far quicker
so you know some of the automotive companies we
deal with they're going from a blank piece of
paper to a car rolling off the production line in
under two years you know you you look at a typical
aerospace project they haven't even looked at
the requirements in the first two years let alone
produced anything so we've seen these far shorter
time scales but i also think the the maturity
as a with the adoption of mbse has increased
dramatically as well so as i said i've been doing
this for my whole career even though it wasn't
called nbse many many years ago but i remember
the first thing cozy event i went to i attended
was the international symposium in 1999 so it
wasn't even this millennium that's how long ago
it was and it was in brighton and in the uk and
um and that's when i first got involved in INCOSE
but i used to speak at a lot of conferences so
we go we're going back 20 22 years now and the
the big argument i would have with people and
the big point i was trying to convince people
is modeling is a good idea and that and people
would throw things at me and then argue with
me and it was it got very heated but it was and
the first book i wrote which was very very slim
it was actually it's pretty sml it was called uml
for systems engineering it was applying uml to um
and people were getting very cross about that but
the whole point of the book the emphasis was on
this is why you should model this is my model is
a good idea and then we found about probably 15
years ago the question changed and it went from
why should we model to how should we model and
so there was a lot more acceptance about modeling
so uh so if you look at the books that we write
in 10 years ago we've got one called the monster
which is like a thousand pages long that weighs
more than the fat baby essentially it's an
enormous great uh book and because the question
had changed or what people wanted to know then is
how do we model efficiently and effectively and
so there were a lot more interesting things like
frameworks and processes and these kind of and the
and the art of modeling as well and what we
found in the last probably three to five years is
the question the emphasis has changed
again and now the emphasis is very much on
well how do we now deploy this in our organization
so i think the maturity and the adoption of mbse
has increased enormously over the last couple of
decades and i think and as the adoption increases
and the maturity increases then the needs of the
people using it also increase so now it's a lot
more about well how do we deploy it on a project
that's already running you know there's all that's
that's midway through a project can we still get
benefit uh how do we um how do you deal with other
people processing tools um no so so i think the
question has changed but certainly the adoption
is far more widespread and in terms of the the
number of people is certainly increased but again
i mentioned INCOSE again and i using cozy in the
uk as a good indicator if you went about 10 or 15
years and you looked at the the the companies
typically attending our what's now called the
annual systems engineering conference the asec
and i'm sure you you'd see a similar pattern
across the world it was 80 90 percent aerospace
and defense and it's no longer the case anymore
we've seen all sorts of uh different companies
getting involved now and getting involved with
INCOSE so we have the uk advisory board here
and that's a group of about 40 companies who are
almost like a steering committee for INCOSE uk and
you look at the diversity on those companies now
we've got civil engineering companies we've got
i.t companies as i said automotive medical power
a lot more academia involved now so certainly
the adoption has become far more widespread and
because of that the questions that are being asked
have become more a lot more widespread as well
um and i'll say that that's certainly the picture
we see in the uk at the moment and certainly just
in terms of the number of clients that
we have now in the diversity of them
certainly increased yeah it's interesting that
in your new book you only need 445 pages to
systems engineering yeah well the reason for
that you see we we wrote the monster and uh
which was enormous and then people were saying
yeah we like it but i can't show that to anybody
there's just too much just too much it so then
we wrote a thing called don't panic which is a
very slim book which is only 50 pages long which
which there's now a whole series of these books
published by encode uk so that was aimed at
the the new people and the managers so that
the demystified kind of sits between the two
so it's more detailed than the um don't panic
but it's not quite as mind-numbing as the
thousand-page monster and of course if you've
got somebody operates at board level we've got a
book for them as well which is the children's book
that's aimed at eight-year-olds to 11 year olds
which is more and if they don't if they don't
understand the engineering they can just color it
in so that's aimed more at people at a ceo level
but there we go but yeah so the the demystified
book's an interesting one and i was approached
to write that by an indian publisher and
again it's interesting because although
it sold across the world obviously the demand
was coming from uh india and it's interesting
we were talking before about india and
china and and you know the adoption of
engineering um in in certain countries and
yeah we've just seen a far wider audience
and also because of who i am if somebody
asked me to do something as you as you know
know i can't say no i have to just agree to it
because my ego won't let anybody else do it so
this is why i ended up taking a lot of these
projects and committing to all sorts of weird
talks and things that that i wouldn't ordinarily
so when they approached me to do it and they said
it was aimed at this particular market and
people who are new to the field but wanted
uh some detail and wanted a case study going all
the way through it so there was quite um not that
strict but they had a very good set of criteria
that had come from their marketing department and
again that was interesting because the marketing
was predominantly done as i said in in sort of
india so and it's interesting seeing this these
these countries really take on board um systems
engineering and in particular model-based systems
engineering so i think that's a very encouraging
picture for mbse globally i i bought your book
but i must i bet i haven't read it yet i don't
demystifying systems engineering
sounds a little bit like you again
try to answer the the why question so
why should i do assistant editing um
the demystified is really that that's more from
the publisher it's i think it's a good title
obviously but they they do a series of books
called demystified um which are aimed at this
particular and it's kind of like so INCOSE uk
now we have the don't panic books which are you
know set at a higher level but yeah so when they
approached me they said you know this and they
sent me examples of what some of the other ones
were but they were all about coding so i couldn't
really read them but they were so that um so yeah
so the title of that and um that was one of the
things that they uh kind of came up with but apart
from that they gave me quite a lot of freedom in
the book to to write what i wanted so it was a
very good process working with them yeah writing
work i took a short look into it and uh it was
interesting for me that you are referring at the
end or the beginning of every chapter to how
does it comply to iso 15 to 88 well i think
to me the the the provenance of engineering
is very important and i think demonstration
compliance is very important i think increasingly
for a number of industries now and you know i'm
the first to admit things like iso standards
aren't perfect but it gives us a good it gives us
a good target to aim for and one of the problems
you'll get is with model-based systems engineering
people want to say well how does it relate to the
way that we do things already or you know how can
it solve these problems for us so that was a very
deliberate part of the book is wherever possible
are related and it's something that
we reflect in our working philosophy
philosophy anyway we try and relate it to
what's what's acknowledged as sort of best
practice and in the world today so the two big
standards we use in the book are obviously 15
to 88 which is more of the process side of
things but also the 42010 and the associated
standards which are more about architecture and
architecture framework um but we use those as
a central part obviously of all the modelling
that we do because when we do modeling a large
part of the book is advocating creating a good
framework for the model and so again we want to
reference that to best international practice
and i think the two standards work well together
as i said then the standards aren't perfect by
any means but they're a really good best practice
model they're acknowledged across the world and
it just gives you that extra level of credibility
um because i know from experience people will
say yeah but we do things like this already
how does mbse help us so it's kind of he's trying
to preempt that question if you like and say well
here's your best practice model you can use it
to do this you can use it to do this but what's
what what that also allows you to do which is very
interesting is you know i don't need to tell you
two about things like reuse but for lots of
people who don't have a modeling background
this is quite big news to them and when you
can say well actually for this part of the iso
standard remember that thing we did a while back
and we produced these views in this model we can
reuse those for this part as well so things that
we did in requirements and we'd be doing scenario
modelling and things like that we can reuse those
now as part of our acceptance testing that we're
now using as part of our vnv and so it allows
you to to do things like that and to make these
references back and and i think that's that's very
important as well because i don't want to get too
much into reuse but reuse is one of those things
that i remember back in the sort of mid-80s and
early 90s everything was about reuse and object
orientation and there were a lot of myths and a
lot of expectations that weren't quite met but
from a modeling point of view i think reuses is
very very possible when it's done properly and
so i think that was an important point that we
wanted to make as well and again the use of
standards is a good gives us a good mechanism
to show that particularly when it came to so
there's one chapter on management for example
and almost all the views that we create in
management are based on the engineering views
and and that that was a that's a nice exercise to
do and that's a point that we're often trying to
make to people as well is why do we have these two
completely separate disciplines that won't talk to
one another when actually we're all looking at the
same thing and i think this is a classic problem
that we have in systems engineering to me one of
the biggest problems that we have with systems
engineering is the word engineering because it
scares people away because people will say well
i'm not an engineer i can't possibly understand
what you're talking about we do things differently
whereas if you say systems thinking or a systems
approach oh everybody wants a systems approach
everybody wants new systems thinking but yeah you
say systems engineering and people people run for
the hills screaming so which can be a problem yeah
i also have more and more customers asking for iso
i think iso provides some stable more stable
areas in this very dynamic environment so it
feels a little bit more safe so many people ask
me how to map this mod to iso and the system
ellen iso standard and this is standard and so
on and it is and people like the the comfort
of iso as well we used to have an expression
in the uk i'm sure it was worldwide that said
nobody ever got fired for buying ibm right i won't
comment on how valid that is as a statement now
but it's that same philosophy which is well if
you're referencing iso you're not going to get
into trouble for you know complying with an
iso standard oh that was my cat just leaking
up then making it he he's not a big fan of iso
as soon as i mentioned that he leaves the room
um yeah i think i thought oh sorry it was also
very interesting what you said about the maturity
of mbse um and i think well in the past tools and
methods could do much more than the people needed
but i think now we are in a change and today
people need more than the tools and methodologies
can provide so i i couldn't agree to more with you
tim absolutely and and i think for so many years
uh this i will say now this is my personal opinion
and not aimed at any particular tool vendor um but
for so many years we had tools that were doing
so so much stuff that nobody would ever use and
it was never required i mean who's
ever wanted shadows on their lines
and this sort of insanity and all these different
techniques and all these that um people marketing
people tried to convince us we needed and we
you know just give us the basic functionality um
but i think for many years with all the tools
were way ahead of the game and would be providing
functionality that you know people weren't using
but i think suddenly now the last five years so i
i agree i think now the tools are playing
catch up and i think in some cases they're
focused on the wrong areas um but i think also
like i said we're living in a connected world
i think this idea of a single vendor people who
finally realizing is not particularly realistic
particularly when you work in a big organization
when you work in a large company you're going to
be using multiple tools from different vendors
and i think one of the biggest issues at the
moment is tool interoperability so actually
you're using a requirements tool for one vendor
you're using a system or modeling tool from
another vendor we've then got a plm environment
that somehow sticks holders together we've got
the mathematics and the simulation side of things
and we need all these things to work together and
i think at the moment most of the tools that i see
on the market are shockingly bad in this area of
tool interoperability and i think particularly in
areas like the visual world of snl compared to the
the formal mathematical world of simulation and
you know we've got mechanisms in csml that give
us that bridge you know so things like parametrics
give us a natural bridge into those but i think
many of the tools at the moment are terrible
to be quite frank in that area and i think this
is an area that needs to have a lot of improvement
and i also think that you look at some tools
and the usability of them um if you if you
went back 10 or 15 years it was it was the same
with many industries but software in particular
um software was telling you what you wanted
the vendors were saying no no you should do
that you want to do it like this you want to do
it like this people aren't that willing to accept
that anymore and i think using something we did
speak about briefly earlier to him but you know
using a tool with an interface that's 20
or 30 years old and hasn't really moved on
is is no longer good enough and and i don't think
some of the vendors realize that usability is such
a big issue at the moment because it really is and
again i would rather the vendors focused on making
the core functionality very usable user-friendly
and compatible with other tools and so on
than having the equivalent of windings on a
uh on a modeling tool which is essentially
what they they're doing in many cases um but
but yeah and you think any other software if
it had an interface that old you wouldn't
uh you know you wouldn't go near it but um
but but but i really think that's a big issue
to my mind that i think they're the two biggest
issues i have with them the first one at
the moment is the the whole interoperability
of the tools um and also the usability of
them and these things aren't cheap either
you know as we've just discussed before um and
they seem to be getting more more expensive as
time goes on and i think the the responsibilities
on the vendors now to actually produce something
that's more fit for purpose and many of the tools
are that's as diplomatic as i can be about tools
yeah we have two comments in the live chat this
time so um okay one recommendation for your book
that it's a great book by the way and we have a
comment from thanks mum she always joins in on
these podcasts we have a comment from mark
who suggests that we just have to rewrite
the standards as models well this is a really
important point and it's something that i've been
i've spoken to iso too i've been involved with
iso for a number of years for years and years and
years on and one of the ways that we demonstrate
compliance is we model the standards and again
anybody with any modeling knowledge will know that
just the very act of modeling gives you a very
good indication on how well-written something
is and if something's very well written and
well specified in your model it the model just
falls out and it's it's easy if it's difficult
to do the modeling if there's a lot of ambient it
tells you about how badly written the the source
information is and we've been doing this for
years and years we've uh in fact one of the first
um what we now refer to as the sort of frameworks
we use and so on uh one of the first ones that
that we produce back in if in fact i'll tell
you how long it was i mentioned the first
INCOSE conference i went to is in 1999 the paper
i presented was on using uml to model standards
right so and because standards were so com look
at standards look at best practice models there's
hundreds of them they're very complex they all
use different language they're difficult to
communicate with people people don't understand
them it's the perfect candidate for modeling
you know it takes all the modeling boxes
why you need to model and we why people
don't define standard using models is beyond me
and i've spoken to not just i said to different
standards bodies before as well to say you know
you should be doing them like this because it
it makes them far less ambiguous it makes
them easy to communicate you can translate
into different languages far easier and uh yeah i
think that's a so mark i love you mark that was an
excellent point and i i couldn't agree with you
more but also when it comes to compliance if we
model our own processes and frameworks using the
same technology modeling techniques that we then
model our standards within our best practice
models the compliance we can build into the
models in and we can actually import them into the
tools and the compliance is then built into our to
our overall model so and to me it's so obvious yet
so few people do it you know and i think that's a
a really really good observation there from by the
way we started um creating a document generation
from the model for the sysworld1 specification and
we found many inconsistencies in the specification
and the previous as well one versions
and also the uml versions are
well partly they are modeled but most of the stuff
is pure text document and yeah and you see this in
in so many standards and particularly if you do
any working frameworks and um you know things
like the the the defense-based architectural
framework so that the the modafs the dodas the
zindas the nafs and so on if you you just do
the most basic of modelling on those and they
they expose themselves for the bag of spanners
that they really are so yes but model absolutely
model standards model best practice references
whether it's in-house procedures whether it's
framework definitions and it will give you
all sorts of insights into what you're doing
and it gives you just a really good
indication of how good the source material is
yeah we have a very interesting discussion in
the chat about interoperability and i guess we
have to have it as an own topic on another
day but definitely definitely absolutely
but for now i would like to change the topic
a little bit on your professorship so you're
teaching systems engineering you're teaching at
a at a university is it the only worst university
where you can have systems engineering lessons
or is it wider spread and what do i do when
i mean it's clear it's clear it's the best taught
systems engineering in the uk if not the world but
apart from that we've seen an increase in the
number of universities that are offering systems
engineering and more important that we've seen a
big increase in the quality and i think it's fair
to say if you went back 10 years and you looked
at universities not all but some universities
they they would look at systems engineering
well we'll just take a bit of mechanical a
bit of electrical a bit of civil a bit of software
or a bit of management we'll mix it all together
and out comes the systems engineering degree for
example and so what we're seeing now is actually
and to me that that's kind of a master of nom
kind of approach you know but what we're really
seeing now the last sort of five or ten years is
universities creating these courses from scratch
and then bringing in other modules obviously
reusing from other as and when but actually um
they're really holding very well together as um
as systems engineering courses when it comes to
modeling and a problem that i've often had with
with uh which is good news for me because one of
the things i do in scarecrows i teach modelling
is people are leaving university and they've been
taught something like uml or sisuml but they've
been taught by somebody who's never used it in
anger they've been taught somebody who's read the
spec and understands it and understands modeling
but but you know as you'll as you'll both
know there's a big difference between
understanding what the diamond means and should it
be colored in an opera and actually applying this
onto a real project and and i think that that's
very interesting and that's what we've seen a
lot of now and i think also to be fair it's it's
why i was offered my position in the first place
or one of the reasons it was offered uh apart
from the good looks was because i had lots of
industrial experience and they wanted to bring
that they wanted to bring that into the course
and and i think that's very important as well
so we've seen a lot more uh systems engineering
being adopted and we're also seeing a lot more
now that the default is modelling is involved in
it somehow even if it's not you know full what i
call sort of stage five mbse this modeling is is
an increasingly important part of what we're doing
um when it comes to systems engineering so i think
the the education system is uh is improving we do
in and we have some working groups within encode
uk to look at this and in fact i do work with i've
mentioned very briefly the children's book that we
wrote but i do we have what we call stem in the
uk so stemi science technology engineering and
mathematics and so it's really promoting things
like engine for me obviously it's all stem but
secretly the e part of the stem to school children
so i'm also involved in doing um well i'll say i'm
involved i haven't been for the last 15 months for
obvious reasons but i used to do a lot of sort of
evening lectures and science festivals music
festivals i've got a music festival coming up
at the end of july so what i also do which uh you
probably most people don't know is sources well
i do uh i'm also a magician um as well as being
an assistant engineer so i do uh science and
music festivals where i use magic to communicate
uh systems engineering to people so we can talk
about things all the things we talk about in
modelling good communication looking at things
from different points of view visualization all
these kinds of things so visualization the things
that we would think about in sml we can use as a
basis for doing memory acts and things like that
so i can memorize a deck of cards using the same
visualization techniques i use i used to model
you know a car or an airplane or a medical system
so so there's a lot more work being done trying
to get into younger uh to convey um engineering in
particular systems engineers obviously my emphasis
to the younger generation as well and because
obviously you want to get them before they go
to universities to try and get them excited and
kind of inspired in some way and and i think
that's very important and we're starting to see
some of that come through now and uh and it's also
as a sign of getting old as well when when i meet
some when i meet an enormous man for example or or
a full grown woman and they say to me oh i saw you
when i was a child at a school it makes me feel
happy inside but old on the outside when that
sort of thing happens so i think it's important
that we we can yes get it into universities
and yes improve the way we're doing that
but i also think it's important that we can we can
go before that and get children uh you know
a younger age because everybody's naturally
curious about things and you know you mentioned
engineering people um people switch off you
mention problem solving everybody gets excited
you know what's engineering if not problem solving
and we do it by you know at the simplest level
drawing pictures of stuff and that's naturally how
people work that's naturally how people think and
for some reason that gets driven out of people's
minds to naturally think in images and visualize
things as we go through the education system
um would you say that there's something
special about mbse in the uk compared
to other countries except Jon Holt
this is what i get special um i don't know if
it's particularly special in the uk um i think
many countries it's a big
stereotype but many companies
have a particular mentality as well in the
way that i go about in the way they go about
things and what i've seen in the uk is these
mentalities can be associated with industries
so again i'm engineering space if they were
early adopters of systems engineering and
model-based systems engineering but they again
broad generalization far less open to new ideas
than you get automotive medical devices that you
know they're coming to the party late but they're
having a very good time when they get there you
know and they're a lot more receptive to try and
change the way that they work and so on um and i
think that's the big thing to me the big blocker
with mbse it's the people you know we often talk
about people processing tools it's the people side
of things and it's winning that battle with people
it's getting them to be able to see for themselves
rather than just tell them do it this the way you
do it this way it's great getting them to see for
themselves and realize that actually this is a
good way to do things and there are benefits in it
for different people so it's that
attitude change and i found that that's
more to do with the industries than sort of
geographically where we go um and it can also be
you know a younger generation coming through tend
to be more open to new ideas than and i include
myself in this old white middle-aged straight men
essentially which is what the industry is full of
at the moment but as we see more diversity from
you know in all different areas coming through um
coming through engineering because i still
think we're behind on this but i think a
natural emergent property of diversity is people
having a more open mind and people being more
receptive to you know maybe slightly different or
newer ideas than people of older generations um
and i think that's very important so
i think the future's very bright and
i think that's what we've got to focus on
is look at the future and say yeah can we
inspire the next generation of engineers and wow
what can what is it possible they can achieve
that just with a more open mindset and with you
you know open up the rise to these different
techniques so things that have been taking me 30
years to show to people who finally get them to
commence you know what about people who don't
have to do that who can just try out these new
ideas new areas and that the potential has got to
be enormous across the you know across the world
yeah one one very funny thing is if you
follow scarecrow consultants on linkedin
is that you publish every week
a riddle a scissor millenary on
song titles expressed in a sml diagram so so
we've um i i like puzzles i like terrible jokes
uh i like music i like film so there's a game
there's a very popular sort of parlor game
this called pictionary which is like
picture dictionary so you draw pictures
that represent films and so on and so he
started off as a bit of a joke where it was well
when i do courses and comments and things and
i and i would say oh you can represent any any
information using modeling because it's just a
way to visualize things and so people would say
oh can you do this can you do this so it started
off as a bit of a joke doing things like that but
no we do it every friday night so it's usually
a film or a uh or a song um so if it's a film it
might be the film title or it might be so this
week we we've actually got a scene from a film
that we've we've done with a sequence diagram and
so we use sysaml to uh to visualize either the
title or some of the lyrics of a song or whatever
um occasionally we'll do it for people uh very
occasionally we'll do it for a type of cheese
so it really depends on what we do but we've
got quite a big following on this now and it's
it's interesting wherever i i say wherever i go
wherever i used to go and will hopefully be going
again soon people come and approach me and uh you
know i was in america for example a few years ago
and rick stein came up to me and he says every
friday we gather the whole research group round
and uh we all see who can get it first there's a
bit of a competition going on and it's really
fascinating you just go what really that that
that terrible puzzle that we do every week um but
it but it's great and it gets people interested
and very occasionally people say they learn a bit
of sml from it as well but i think it's getting
people thinking in an abstract way it's not just
about designing the new aeroplane the new car the
train or whatever you can use these techniques to
convey any kind of information and in fact it was
rick stein that said to me which really stuck in
my mind he said well you can only truly master any
language if you can express humor in it and he and
he said and that's what system element does so he
uses that as an example for some of his students
and i think that's very important so if you do go
onto our linkedin page and you do this you have
to go with an open mind and bear in mind there
are some terrible terrible misinterpretations
of song titles and things like that on it so uh
but yeah so we do that every friday it's a good
fun thing to come along and uh and join in if you
do and if you're very lucky you might even have
it dedicated to you one week that's that's the uh
that's the goal tim yeah last week
it reminds me of a great film well
very good um is it correct that is that you
published some of them in a book i think
when we go to conferences and things
so we'll collect like a year together
and just print them in a book and we can uh well
we normally give them out uh just as like a free
thing and people tend to like it and then we give
match prizes and things like that as well but then
we we print them through an online uh publishing
uh company and um so just just for a joke simon
one of my colleagues where i write a lot of the
books with he said oh we'll just put it up for
five pounds and see if anybody's stupid enough
to buy it somebody in canada bought 50 copies
okay it's full with money as they say ain't
hardly a fall at all but but no so we we do the
so people want the hard copy just send me an email
we will send you some out so we give those away at
conferences and things like that we don't normally
charge for those but it's normally just like the
last year that we've done and put together and
it's kind of nice uh just to have them in you and
you can copy it from from linkedin so yeah yeah
so come come and see us at the next conference and
uh and you can have a a signed copy with a
personalized message in sicil especially for you
what's your next conference the next uh the next
face-to-face one i'm doing is hopefully the INCOSE
uk annual systems engineering conference in
november of this year uh that obviously takes
place in the uk um i'm heavily involved in that
i'm the technical director so i'm responsible for
getting your papers reviewed and all the technical
content so that'll be the next one that we're at
i'm appearing at some uh quite a few online ones
over the next 12 months as well i've got quite
a few german events coming up actually you're the
first of many german events that are coming up so
um so if you like this come and see me said the
others i'll be saying the same thing but with a
slightly different hat on maybe or something like
that but but yeah so there's quite a few coming
up i mean one of the good things about covert is
it's i get invited to a lot more international
conferences than i used to uh it's not quite as
nice sat on my sofa and imagining that i'm in
paris indies oh i was supposed to go to paris as
one of the keynotes in december um at christmas
time i thought that would be great and um take my
girlfriend we'll have a lovely time and we didn't
instead we sat here and drank red wine on that
evening and pretended that we were in paris so
not quite the same yeah sounds good great okay so
we are live for now 42 minutes time correct and i
have i have still three tasks for our listeners
uh the one is give us a thumbs up on youtube
so you can support the channel don't forget to
subscribe to the channel so you don't miss out
the next live stream and last but not least by
the book of Jon yes the new book not just that
one all of them also all of them are all seventeen
okay so but buy one i'll give you a free system
great yeah and tim well then the next topic is um
not planned yet um we have some ideas
but we have no next topic no date yet
and also a little bit summer break time um
but well we will do something pretty sure um
and well i think that's it well i'd just like
to say thanks thanks to both christian and tim
for inviting me on it's been a delight
and i'd also like to say very sincerely
good luck in the football tomorrow night
to you two and everybody in germany
so now you have to watch the youtube video
if you are just listening on it to see what
Jon really meant yeah we could also
could spoil the result for tomorrow
i know it
yeah Jon also from my side of was an honor to have
you here thank you very much thank you very much
okay i look i look forward to seeing you both
in person in the next year so yeah yeah okay
okay so and well then do not forget
trust this is we are suspicious good