Okay, so good evening
And welcome to our MBSE Podcast
And this time
Christian and I are doing a new episode of
our series MBSE around the world
after Sweden and then China
This time, we visited the United Kingdom
And we want to see
how MBSE is doing there
We are happy to have
Jon Holt as our guest
And I think no one can
tell us better about it
and who Jon is
He will tell you best himself
Please Jon, introduce yourself
Okay, thanks very much Tim
First of all, thanks to Tim and
Christian for inviting me along
It's a pleasure
and an honor to be with you
For people who don't know
who I am, my name is Jon Holt
And I've been doing MBSE for my
whole career now, for almost 30 years
I work for a company called
Scarecrow Consultants Limited
We're based in the UK
I'm personally based in Wales in the UK
For those of you in Europe
Wales is the slightly wet country
to the left of England
For those of you in America
it's near London somewhere
I'm also a professor of
systems engineering
at Cranfield University here in the UK
And if people are aware of INCOSE
the International Council
of Systems Engineering
I'm the current technical director
of new INCOSE UK
And I've offered 17 books on
model-based systems engineering
and its application
in over the years
That's a very brief
introduction to me
Wonderful!
Thank you, Jon
Also from my side
a very warm welcome
And as the technical director
you can tell us in which industries
in the UK is systems engineering
or maybe already model-based
systems engineering used
It's interesting
because I think the same as many countries
historically systems engineering
and therefore model-based
systems engineering
has been very strong for decades
in aerospace and defense
But what we're seeing now is lots of
other different industries coming on board
And I think one of the biggest ones
at the moment is automotive
From about 5 or 7 years ago
all of a sudden
automotive has become massive
And I think this is important
because I think what's important
about all industries
in particular automotive
I use those as the example
is because of the the complexity
of the vehicles of the systems
that they're producing
has increased so dramatically
over the last few years
In particular, in areas like
everything is now connected
every device we buy now is now connected
everything is potentially part of
a wider system of systems
And all of a sudden, we've seen this sort
of this step change in complexity
because of that and because of
the different technologies involved
and because of things like constraints
safety/security standards and so on
And also, shifts in technology
so getting automotive
away from internal combustion
engines over to electric
it's been a massive change
and a shift in complexity
And I think in order to
cope with this complexity
the techniques we were using
10, 20, 30 years ago
a document based approach
don't get me wrong
there's nothing wrong with
a document-based approach
it's not incorrect
but I think a document-based approach
that worked 10 or 20 years ago
is no longer adequate for the job because
the complexity has increased so much
And I think as the complexity of our
systems that we're developing increases
therefore the complexity of the approach
that we're taking to develop those
systems must also increase
And we've seen lots of other areas as well
automotive is a very good example
But also medical devices we see
now the last couple of years
we've been involved in that
Energy as well
From the whole spectrum
from sort of nuclear fusion
And we're even doing some work
in steam power at the moment
We're covering both ends
of the spectrum of of energy though
Certainly we've seen
more and more diverse industries
adopting model-based systems engineering
And very importantly
because it's the need that's there
It's not because it's
the flavor of the month
or it sounds good
it sounds exciting
It's because there's
a genuine need there
to cope with this increased complexity
that we're seeing in all of our systems
And what purposes MBSE use now?
You can use it for different purposes
You can increase the communication
between the team
And you can use it to specify things
Or you can satisfy assessors with
tons of generated documents
Now you can do already simulation
stuff and other cool things
Is there a special focus in the UK?
We work with all different industries
and lots of different companies
academia and government
And it's been used in
all sorts of different areas
And one of the things about
model-based systems engineering is
if you do a google search on the benefits
of model-based systems engineering
what comes up is lots of tool vendors say
"Look what my tool does!"
They're not really the benefits of MBSE
They're things that the tool will do
And I think that the benefits of
our sort of context dependence
it really depends on
the stakeholders you're talking to
We can deal with the same organization
And if we deal with the engineers
We can say it's great
it's going to improve your specification
your design, your requirements, and so on
But if we say that to a manager
they're not interested
If we talk to a manager
we'll focus on
it will improve your cost
timing, resource estimates
And if we're dealing with
somebody at board level
we've got to focus on things
like return on investment
and improvement of the quality
attributes of the systems
It does vary enormously
But I think all of the topics that
you mentioned there are definitely
we've seen it used in all of those areas
But it really does vary
And as I say, we work with some
organizations where different teams
are getting different benefits
from using MBSE arranging from
one company we want to
half up our development time
we want to go from a six year
cycle to a three year cycle
and whereas others are
we want to improve our quality
But what is interesting is we find in that
particular industries are interested in
and this is a very broad generalization
but tend to be interested in
different aspects of it
It's interesting, you mentioned, quality
when we deal with medical devices company
their main emphasis seems to be on
"Can we comply with the standards
and the legislation?"
Because if we can't
we can't sell our products
So for them
that's the most important thing
We deal with sort of aerospace type
companies with typically long life cycles
And they're more and more interesting
"Can we shorten our life cycles?"
It really depends on
the stakeholders we're talking to
But we do see these trends in industries
And we see a lot more collaboration
now between organizations
whereas historically people
were more insular
we see a lot more collaborations
And that's where areas like
Tim, you mentioned
the improved communication
between the different stakeholders
And we're seeing that
an awful lot as well now
I think it's because we work in
lots of different industries
that we can see these
different applications being used
And I think if you were taught
if you were to talk to somebody
who worked in a single organization
which is most people let's face it
they would give you
a more definitive answer
"This is how we use it"
And one of the big areas that
we do use it for across industry is
in defining an approach to
model-based systems engineering
Actually using the modeling
using a MBSE approach
to understand what their business
business needs are to help
them change the business
And my personal philosophy is
when it comes to deploying MBSE
I treat that like a system
I'm going to apply MBSE to do that
And that's a really interesting area
That's a lot more prevalent now
than we saw just a few years ago
Can you estimate how well MBSE
is used in the different industries?
Is defense and space still
decades ahead, or is it changing?
No, I really don't think they are anymore
And I think that one of
the reasons for this is
if we take industries like
automotive, medical devices
the life cycles are far shorter
And they need to get in quicker
and get the returns far quicker
Some of the automotive
companies we deal with
they're going from a blank piece of paper
to a car rolling off the production
line in under 2 years
You look at a typical aerospace project
they haven't even looked at the
requirements in the first 2 years
let alone produced anything
We've seen these far shorter time scales
But I also think the the maturity
with the adoption of MBSE
has increased dramatically as well
As I said, I've been doing
this for my whole career
even though it wasn't called
MBSE many years ago
But I remember the first INCOSE
event I went to and I attended
was the international symposium in 1999
It wasn't even this millennium
that's how long ago it was
It was in Brighton in the UK
That's when I first got involved in INCOSE
But I used to speak
at a lot of conferences
We're going back 22 years now
The big argument I would have with people
and the big point I was
trying to convince people
is modeling is a good idea
And people would throw things at me
and then argue with me
and it got very heated
And the first book I wrote
which was very slim
It was actually pretty SysML
It was called
"UML for Systems Engineering"
It was applying UML too
And people were getting
very across about that
But the whole point of the book
the emphasis was on
This is why you should model
This is why my model is a good idea
And then we found about
probably 15 years ago
the question changed
And it went from "Why should we model?"
to "How should we model?"
There was a lot more
acceptance about modeling
If you look at the books
that we write in 10 years ago
we've got one called the "Monster"
which is like a thousand
pages long that weighs
more than the fat baby
Essentially it's an enormous great book
And because the question had changed
what people wanted to know then is
"How do we model
efficiently and effectively?"
There were a lot more interesting things
like frameworks and processes
and these kinds
and the art of modeling as well
And what we found in the last
probably three to 5 years is
the question, the emphasis
has changed again
And now the emphasis is very much on
"How do we now deploy
this in our organization?"
I think the maturity and the adoption
of MBSE have increased enormously
over the last couple of decades
And I think as the adoption increases
and the maturity increases
then the needs of the people
using it also increase
So now
it's a lot more about
"How do we deploy it on a project
that's already running?"
That's all
That's midway through a project
"Can we still get benefit?"
"How do you deal with other
people processing tools?"
I think the question has changed
But certainly the adoption is
far more widespread
And the number of people
is certainly increased
But again, I mentioned INCOSE again
I used INCOSE in the UK
as a good indicator
If you went back 10 or 15 years
and you looked at the companies
typically attending
what's now called the annual systems
engineering conference, the ASEC
And I'm sure you'd see a similar
pattern across the world
it was 80 to 90 percent
aerospace and defense
And it's no longer the case anymore
We've seen all sorts of different
companies getting involved now
and getting involved with INCOSE
We have the UK advisory board here
And that's a group of about 40 companies
who are almost like a steering
committee for INCOSE UK
And you look at the diversity
on those companies now
We've got civil engineering companies
we've got IT companies
As I said, automotive, medical power
a lot more academia involved now
Certainly the adoption has
become far more widespread
And because of that
the questions that are being asked have
become more a lot more widespread as well
And I'll say that that's certainly the
picture we see in the UK at the moment
And certainly just in terms of the
number of clients that we have now
in the diversity of them
it's certainly increased
It's interesting that in your new book
you only need 445 pages to
demystify systems engineering
The reason for that, we wrote the
"Monster" and which was enormous
And then people were saying we like it
but I can't show that to anybody
This it too much
just too much it
So then, we wrote a thing
called "DON'T PANIC"
which is a very slim book
which is only 50 pages long
which there's now a whole series of
these books published by INCOSE UK
That was aimed at the new
people and the managers
The "Demystified" comes
to sit between the two
It's more detailed than "DON'T PANIC"
But it's not quite as mind-numbing
as the thousand-page "Monster"
And of course, if you've got
somebody operates at board level
we've got a book for them as well
which is the children's book
that's aimed at eight-year-olds to
eleven-year-old which is more
If they don't understand
the engineering
they can just color it
That's aimed more at
people at a CEO level
But there we go
The "Demystified" book
is an interesting one
And I was approached to write
that by an Indian publisher
It's interesting because although
it sold across the world obviously
the demand was coming from India
And it's interesting
we were talking before
about India and China
and the adoption of engineering
in certain countries
And we've just seen a far wider audience
And also because of who I am
if somebody asked me to do something
I can't say "No"
I have to just agree to it
Because my ego won't
let anybody else do it
this is why I ended up taking
a lot of these projects
and committing to all sorts of weird talks
and things that I wouldn't ordinarily
When they approached me to do it
they said it was aimed at
this particular market
And people who are new to the field
but wanted some detail and wanted a case
study going all the way through it
They had a very good set of criteria that
had come from their marketing department
And again, that was interesting
because the marketing was
predominantly done in sort of India
It's interesting seeing this
these countries really take on board
systems engineering and, in particular
model-based systems engineering
I think that's a very encouraging
picture for MBSE globally
I bought your book but I must bet
I haven't read it yet
I don't care
Change buy, Tim
The title "Demystifying Systems
Engineering" sounds a little bit like
You try to answer the the why question
"Why should I do the systems engineering?"
The "Demystified" is really
that's more from the publisher
I think it's a good title obviously
But they they do a series of
books called "Demystified"
which are aimed at this particular
And it's kind of like INCOSE UK
Now we have the "DON'T PANIC" books
which are a set at a higher level
But when they approached me
they sent me examples of what
some of the other ones were
But they were all about coding
so I couldn't really read them
So the title of that
And that was one of the things
that they came up with
But apart from that
they gave me quite a lot of
freedom in the book
to write what I wanted
It was a very good process
working with them
I took a short look into it
And it was interesting for me that
you are referring at the end or the
beginning of every chapter to
"How does it comply to ISO 15288?"
I think the the provenance
of engineering is very important
And I think the demonstration of
compliance is very important
I think increasingly for a
number of industries now
I'm the first to admit things
like ISO standards aren't perfect
But it gives us a good target to aim for
And one of the problems you'll get
is with model-based systems engineering
People want to say "How does it relate
to the way that we do things already?"
"How can it solve these problems for us?"
That was a very deliberate part of the
book is wherever possible are related
And it's something that we reflect
in our working philosophy anyway
We try and relate it to what's
acknowledged as sort of best practice
And in the world today
the two big standards we use
in the book are obviously
15288 which is more of
the process side of things
but also the 42010
the associated standards
which are more about architecture
and architecture framework
But we use those as a central part
obviously of all the modelling that we do
Because when we do modeling
a large part of the book is advocating
creating a good framework for the model
We want to reference that
to best international practice
And I think the two standards
work well together
The standards aren't perfect by any means
But they're a really good
best practice model
They're acknowledged across the world
And it just gives you that
extra level of credibility
Because I know from my
experience, people will say
"But we do things like this already
how does MBSE help us?"
He's trying to preempt
that question if you like
"Say well, here's your
best practice model"
"You can use it to do this"
"you can use it to do this"
But what that also allows you to do
which is very interesting, is
I don't need to tell you two
about things like reuse
but for lots of people who don't
have a modeling background
this is quite big news to them
And when you can say
actually for this part of the ISO standard
remember that thing we did a while back
and we produced these views in this model
We can reuse those for this part as well
Things that we did in requirements
and we'd be doing scenario
modelling and things like that
We can reuse those now as
part of our acceptance testing
that we're now using as part of our V&V
It allows you to to do things like that
and to make these references back
And I think that's very important as well
because I don't want to
get too much into reuse
but reuse is one of those things
that I remember back in the
sort of mid-80s and early 90s
everything was about
reuse and object orientation
And there were a lot of myths, and a lot
of expectations that weren't quite met
But from a modeling point of view
I think reuses is very possible
when it's done properly
I think that was an important point
that we wanted to make as well
Again, the use of standards is a good
It gives us a good mechanism to show that
Particularly when it came to, there's one
chapter on management, for example
And almost all the views that
we create in management
are based on the engineering views
And that's a nice exercise to do
And that's a point that we're often
trying to make to people as well is
"Why do we have these two
completely separate disciplines
that won't talk to one another?"
When actually we're all
looking at the same thing
and I think this is a classic problem
that we have in systems engineering
To me one of the biggest problems
that we have with systems engineering is
the word "Engineering"
Because it scares people away
Because people will say
"Well, I'm not an engineer
I can't possibly understand what you're
talking about, we do things differently"
Whereas if you say systems
thinking or a systems approach
everybody wants a systems approach
everybody wants a systems thinking
But you say systems engineering
people people run for the hills screaming
So, which can be a problem
I also have more and more
customers asking for ISO
I think ISO provides more stable areas
in this very dynamic environment
It feels a little bit more safe
Many people ask me how to
map SYSMOD to ISO
SysML to ISO standard
And this is standard and so on
People like the the comfort of ISO as well
We used to have an expression in the UK
I'm sure it was worldwide
That said, "Nobody ever got
fired for buying IBM"
Right?
I won't comment on how valid
that is as a statement now
But it's that same philosophy which is
if you're referencing to ISO
you're not going to get into trouble
for complying with an ISO standard
Oh, that was my cat just
leaking up then making it
He's not a big fan of ISO as soon as
I mentioned that he leaves the room
I think it was also very interesting
what you said about the maturity of MBSE
I think in the past
tools and methods could do
much more than the people needed
But I think now we are in a change
and today people need more than
the tools and methodologies can provide
I couldn't agree to more with you, Tim
Absolutely
And I think for so many years
I would say this is my personal opinion
not aimed at any particular tool vendor
But for so many years
we had tools that were doing so much
stuff that nobody would ever use
And it was never required
I mean who's ever wanted
shadows on their lines on the dark
And this is the sort of insanity
And all these different techniques
And marketing people tried
to convince we needed
Give us the basic functionality
But I think for many years, all tools
were way ahead of the game
and would be providing functionality
that people weren't using
But I think suddenly
now the last 5 years
I agree, Tim
I think now the tools
are playing catch up
And I think in some cases
they're focused on the wrong areas
But I think also like I said
we're living in a connected world
I think this idea of a single vendor
people who finally realizing
is not particularly realistic
Particularly when you work
in a big organization
when you work in a large company
you're going to be using multiple
tools from different vendors
And I think one of the biggest issues
at the moment is tool interoperability
So actually, you're using a
requirements tool for one vendor
You're using a system or modeling
tool from another vendor
We've then got a PLM environment
that somehow stakeholders together
we've got the mathematics and
the simulation side of things
And we need all these
things to work together
I think at the moment
most of the tools that I see on
the market are shockingly bad
in this area of tool interoperability
And I think particularly
in areas like the visual world of SysML
compared to the the formal
mathematical world of simulation
We've got mechanisms in SysML
that give us that bridge
things like parametric gives us a
natural bridge into those
But I think many of the tools
at the moment are terrible
to be quite frank in that area
I think this is an area that needs
to have a lot of improvement
And I also think that you look at
some tools and the usability of them
If you went back 10 or 15 years
it was the same with many industries
but software in particular
software was telling you what you wanted
the vendors were saying
"No, no, you should do that"
"You want to do it like this"
People aren't that willing
to accept that anymore
And I think using something
we did speak about briefly earlier
using a tool with an interface
that's 20 or 30 years old
that hasn't really moved on
is no longer good enough
I don't think some of
the vendors realize that
usability is such a big issue at the
moment because it really is
I would rather the vendors focused on
making the core functionality
very user-friendly and compatible
with other tools and so on
than having the equivalent of
windings on a modeling tool
which is essentially what
they're doing in many cases
But you think any other software
if it had an interface that old
you wouldn't go near it
But I really think that's a
big issue to my mind that
I think they're the two biggest
issues I have with them
The first one at the moment is the
whole interoperability of the tools
And also the usability of them
And these things aren't cheap either
as we've just discussed before
They seem to be getting more
expensive as time goes on
And I think the the responsibilities
on the vendors now
to actually produce something that's more
fit for purpose and many of the tools are
That's as diplomatic as
I can be about tools
We have two comments
in the live chat this time
One recommendation for your book
that "It's a great book by the way"
Thanks, mum!
She always joins in on these podcasts
We have a comment from Mark
who suggests that we just have to
rewrite the standards as models
This is a really important point
And it's something that I've been
I've spoken to ISO too
I've been involved with
ISO for a number of years
for years and years and years on
And one of the ways that we demonstrate
compliance is we model the standards
anybody with any modeling knowledge will
know that just the very act of modeling
gives you a very good indication on
how well-written something is
If something's very well written
and well specified in your model
it the model just falls out
And it's easy
If it's difficult to do the modeling
if there's a lot of ambient
it tells you about how badly written
the the source information is
And we've been doing this
for years and years
We've in fact one of the first
what we now refer to as the sort of
frameworks we use and so on
One of the first ones
that we produce back in
If in fact I'll tell you how long it was
I mentioned the first INCOSE
conference I went to is in 1999
the paper I presented was on
using UML to model standards
Right?
And because standards were so complex
look at standards
look at best practice models
there's hundreds of them
they're very complex
They all use different language
They're difficult to
communicate with people
People don't understand them
It's the perfect candidate
for modeling
It takes all the modeling boxes
why you need to model
And why people don't define standard
using models is beyond me
and I've spoken to
not just I said to different
standards bodies before as well
You should be doing them like this
because it makes them far less ambiguous
it makes them easy to communicate
You can translate into different
languages far easier
I love you, Mark
That was an excellent point
I couldn't agree with you more
But also when it comes to compliance if we
model our own processes and frameworks
using the same technology
modeling techniques
that we then model our standards
within our best practice models
The compliance we can build
into the models in
and we can actually import
them into the tools
And the compliance is then
built into our overall model
To me, it's so obvious
Yet so few people do it
that's a really good observation
By the way, we started creating
a document generation
from the model for
the SysML 1 specification
And we found many inconsistencies
in the specification
And the previous SysML 1 versions
and also the UML versions are
partly they are modeled
But most of the stuff
is pure text document
In so many standards and particularly
if you do any working frameworks
things like the defense-based
architectural framework
So that, the MODAFs, the DoDAFs,
the DNDAFs, the NAFs, and so on
If you just do the most basic of
modelling on those
they expose themselves for the bag of
spanners that they really are
The model standards, model
best practice, references
whether it's in-house procedures
framework definitions
it will give you all sorts of insights
into what you're doing
And it gives you just a
really good indication
of how good the source material is
We have a very interesting discussion
in the chat about interoperability
And I guess we have to have it
as an own topic on another day
Definitely
Absolutely
But for now
I would like to change the topic
a little bit on your professorship
You're teaching systems engineering
You're teaching at a university
Is it the only university where you can
have systems engineering lessons?
Or is it wider spread?
And what do I do when I'm a professional?
It's clear
It's the best taught
systems engineering in the UK
if not the world
But apart from that
we've seen an increase
in the number of
universities that are offering
systems engineering
And more important that we've
seen a big increase in the quality
And I think it's fair to say
if you went back 10 years
and you looked at universities
not all but some universities
they would look at systems engineering
We'll just take
a bit of mechanical
a bit of electrical
a bit of civil
a bit of software
or a bit of management
We'll mix it all together
And outcome's the systems
engineering degree for example
And what we're seeing now is actually
And to me, that's kind of a
master of none kind of approach
But what we're really seeing now
in the last 5 or 10 years
is universities creating
these courses from scratch
And then, bring again the modules
obviously reusing as and when
But actually
they're really holding very well together
as systems engineering courses
When it comes to modeling, and a
problem that I've often had with
which is good news for me
because one of the things
I do in Scarecrows
I teach modelling is people
are leaving university
And they've been taught
something like UML or SysML
But they've been taught by somebody
who's never used it in anger
They've been taught by
somebody who's read the spec
and understands it
and understands modeling
But as you both know, there's a big
difference between understanding
what the diamond means and
what should it be colored in an opera
And actually applying
this onto a real project
And I think that's very interesting
And that's what we've seen a lot of now
And I think also to be fair
it's why I was offered my
position in the first place
or one of the reasons it was offered
apart from the good looks
That's because I had lots of
industrial experience
And they wanted to bring that
they wanted to bring that into the course
And I think that's very important as well
we've seen a lot more
systems engineering being adopted
and we're also seeing a lot
more now that the default is
modelling is involved in it somehow
even if it's not full what
I call the stage 5 MBSE
This modeling is an increasingly
important part of what we're doing
when it comes to systems engineering
I think the education system is improving
We do in and we have some working
groups with INCOSE UK to look at this
And in fact, I do work with
I've mentioned very briefly
the children's book that we wrote
But I do we have what
we call STEM in the UK
STEM is Science, Technology
Engineering, and Mathematics
And it's really promoting
things like engineering
For me obviously
it's all STEM but secretly
the 'E' part of the STEM
to school children
So, I'm also involved in doing well
I'm involved, I haven't been for the
last 15 months for obvious reasons
But I used to do a lot of
sort of evening lectures
science festivals
music festivals
I've got a music festival
coming up at the end of July
What I also do which you
probably most people don't know
Sings in SysML for me?
I'm also a magician as well as
being a systems engineer
I do science and music festivals
where I use magic to communicate
systems engineering to people
We can talk about things, all the
things we talk about in modelling
good communication looking at
things from different points of view
visualization all these kinds of things
Visualization, the things that we
would think about in SysML
we can use as a basis for doing
memory acts and things like that
I can memorize a deck of cards
using the same visualization techniques
I used to model a car or
an airplane or a medical system
There's a lot more work being
done trying to get into younger
to convey engineering in particular
systems engineers obviously
My emphasis to the younger
generation as well
and because obviously you want to
get them before they go to universities
to try and get them excited
and kind of inspired in some way
And I think that's very important
And we're starting to see some
of that come through now
And it's also as a sign
of getting old as well
when I meet an enormous man
for example or a full grown woman
They say to me, "Oh, I saw you
when I was a child at a school"
It makes me feel happy inside
But old on the outside when
that sort of thing happens
I think it's important that
we can get it into universities
and improve the way we're doing that
But I also think it's important that
we can go before that and get children
A younger age because everybody's
naturally curious about things
And you mentioned "Engineering"
people switch off
You mention "Problem solving"
everybody gets excited
What's engineering if not problem solving?
We do it by at the simplest level
drawing pictures of stuff
That's naturally how people work
That's naturally how people think
For some reason that gets
driven out of people's minds
to naturally think in images
and visualize things
as we go through the education system
Would you say that there's something
special about MBSE in the UK
compared to other countries
except Jon Holt?
This is what I get special
I don't know if it's particularly
special in the UK
I think many countries
it's a big stereotype
but many companies have
a particular mentality
as well in the way that I go about
in the way they go about things
What I've seen in the UK is
these mentalities can be
associated with industries
So again, I'm engineering space
if they were early adopters
of systems engineering
and model-based
systems engineering
but they broad generalization
far less open to new ideas
than you get automotive, medical devices
that they're coming to the party late
But they're having a very good
time when they get there
They're a lot more receptive to try and
change the way that they work, and so on
And I think that's the big thing to me
the big blocker with MBSE
It's the people, we often talk
about people processing tools
It's the people side of things
And it's winning that battle with people
It's getting them to be able
to see for themselves
rather than just tell them
"Do it this the way", "Do it this way"
it's great getting them
to see for themselves
and realize that actually this is
a good way to do things
And there are benefits in
it for different people
It's the attitude change
And I found that that's more
to do with the industries
than sort of geographically where we go
And it can also be
a younger generation coming through
tend to be more open to new ideas
than, and I include myself in this
old white middle-aged straight men
essentially, which is what the industry
is full of at the moment
But as we see more diversity in all
different areas coming through engineering
because I still think
we're behind on this
But I think a natural emergent
property of diversity
is people having a more open mind
and people being more receptive
to maybe slightly different or newer
ideas than people of older generations
And I think that's very important
I think the future's very bright
I think that's what we've got to focus
on is look at the future and say
"Can we inspire the next
generation of engineers?"
"What is it possible they can achieve?"
That's just with a more open mindset
and with open up the rise to
these different techniques
Things that have been taking me 30 years
to show to people who finally
get them to commence
what about people who
don't have to do that
who can just try out these
new ideas and new areas
And that the potential has got to
be enormous across the world
One very funny thing is
if you follow Scarecrow
Consultants on LinkedIn
is that you publish every week
a riddle "SysML-anary" on
song titles expressed in a SysML diagram
Fancastic!
I like puzzles
I like terrible jokes
I like music
I like films
There's a game
There's a very popular sort of parlor game
This called "Pictionary" which
is like picture dictionary
You draw pictures that
represent films and so on
And we started off as a bit
of a joke where it was well
When I do courses and
comments and things
I would say, "You can represent
any information using modeling
because it's just a way
to visualize things"
And people would say
"Can you do this?"
It started off as a bit of a joke
doing things like that
But now we do it every Friday night
it's usually a film or a song
If it's a film, it might
be the film title
Or it might be, this week we've
actually got a scene from a film
that we've done with a sequence diagram
And we use SysML to visualize
either the title or some of
the lyrics of a song or whatever
occasionally we'll do it for people
very occasionally we'll
do it for a type of cheese
It really depends on what we do
But we've got quite a big
following on this now
And it's interesting
wherever I used to go
and will hopefully be going again soon
people come and approach me
And I was in America
for example a few years ago
Rick Steiner came up to me
and he says every Friday we gather
the whole research group round
And we all see who can get it first
there's a bit of a competition going on
And it's really fascinating you just go
what really that terrible puzzle
that we do every week
But it's great, and it gets
people interested
And very occasionally people say
they learn a bit of SysML from it as well
But I think it's getting people
thinking in an abstract way
It's not just about designing the new aero
plane, the new car, the train, or whatever
You can use these techniques to
convey any kind of information
And in fact it was
Rick Steiner that said to me
which really stuck in
my mind, he said
"You can only truly master any language
if you can express humor in it"
And he said that's
what SysML does
He uses that as an example
for some of his students
And I think that's very important
if you do go onto our
LinkedIn page and you do this
you have to go with an open
mind, and bear in mind
There are some terrible
misinterpretations
of song titles and
things like that on it
But we do that every Friday
It's a good fun thing to come along
And join in if you do
And if you're very lucky
you might even have it
dedicated to you one week
That's the goal, Tim
Last week it reminds me of a great film
Very good
Is it correct that you published
some of them in a book?
When we go to conferences and things
we'll collect like a year together
And just print them in a book
We normally give them out
just as like a free thing
And people tend to like it
And then we give match prizes
and things like that as well
But we print them through
an online publishing company
And so just for a joke, Simon
one of my colleagues where
I write a lot of the books with
He said "Oh, we'll just put
it up for 5 pounds
and see if anybody's
stupid enough to buy it"
"Somebody in Canada bought 50 copies!"
Okay, it's full with money as
they say ain't hardly a fall at all
But people want the hard copy
just send me an email
We will send you some out
We give those away at conferences
And things like that we don't
normally charge for those
But it's normally just like the last year
that we've done and put together
It's kind of nice just to have them
No need to copy it from LinkedIn?
Yeah, come and see us
at the next conference
And you can have a signed copy
with a personalized message
in SysML especially for you
What's your next conference?
The next face-to-face one
I'm doing is hopefully
the INCOSE UK annual systems engineering
conference in November of this year
That obviously takes place in the UK
I'm heavily involved in that
I'm the technical director
I'm responsible for getting your papers
reviewed and all the technical content
That'll be the next one that we're at
I'm appearing at some quite a few online
ones over the next 12 months as well
I've got quite a few German
events coming up actually
You're the first of many German
events that are coming up
If you like this, come and see me
say to the others
I'll be saying the same thing
but with a slightly different hat
on maybe or something like that
But so there's quite a few coming up
I mean one of the good things
under COVID is
I get invited to a lot more
international conferences than I used to
It's not quite as sad as much so far
and imagining that I'm in Paris in this
I was supposed to go to Paris as one of
the keynotes in December at Christmas
I thought that would be great and take
my girlfriend we'll have a lovely time
and we didn't instead, we sat here,
and drank red wine on that evening
and pretended that we were in Paris
Not quite the same
Sounds good
Great, okay!
We are live for now 42 minutes
I have still three tasks for our listeners
The one is give us a thumbs up on YouTube
You can support the channel
Don't forget to subscribe to the channel
You don't miss out the next live stream
And last but not least
buy the book of Jon
Yes!
Not just that one!
All of them, all 17 books!
If you buy all 17 books
I'll give you free "SysML-anary"
Great!
And Tim
Then the next topic is not planned yet
We have some ideas but we have
no next topic, no date yet
And also a little bit summer break time
But we will do something pretty sure
And I think that's it
I'd just like to say thanks to
both Christian and Tim
for inviting me on
It's been a delight
And I'd also like to say very sincerely
Good luck in the football tomorrow night
To you and everybody in Germany
Now you have to watch the YouTube video
if you are just listening on it
to see what Jon really meant
We could also spoil
the result for tomorrow
I know it
Jon, also from my side
was an honor to have you here
Thank you very much
I look forward to seeing you both
in person in the next year
Yeah
Okay, so and well then
Do not forget
Trust us we are Systems Engineers