welcome to another draw of the mbse
podcast advent calendar you have the
13th store we take a look at the
physical architecture
in the last days we presented the
functional architecture
as a reminder let's open the internal
block diagram of the functional
architecture in the tool
we also have created a physical
architecture of our mbse podcast
christmas tree which specifies the
physical entities that implement the
functional entities from the functional
architecture
the physical architecture is a
specialization of the base architecture
in this diagram the element with a
system stereotype with the name the mbse
podcast christmas tree
it inherits most of the parts from the
system element tmpct base architecture
as we have seen before we used
illustrations in this case instead of
the block notation which makes it easier
for unexperienced users to understand
the diagram
the blocks from our functional
architecture are allocated to the blocks
of the physical architecture the
allocation specifies which physical
block implements which function block
let's see how we manage the allocations
in a matrix
the rows list the function blocks the
columns the physical blocks and the
cells the allocate relationship
some functional blocks are mapped to
more than one physical block and some
physical blocks have more than one
allocated functional block it is a
rather rough mapping so for example if a
functional block is allocated to
multiple physical blocks it is not clear
whether it is redundantly allocated
are only parts of the functional block
however this is usually sufficient in
the model
more details if required can be
introduced by extending the allocate
relationship with a stereotype
as with the functional architecture the
more interesting part is the internal
structure of the physical architecture
with ports and connections
that we will cover tomorrow
so much for the 13th store of our mbse
podcast event calendar and we wish you a
great 13th of december
bye goodbye