Welcome to another door of the
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
Behind the 13th door, we take a look at
the Physical Architecture
In the last days, we presented
the Functional Architecture
As a reminder, let's open
the internal block diagram
of the Functional Architecture in the tool
We also have created
a Physical Architecture
of our MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree
which specifies the physical entities
that implement the functional entities
from the Functional Architecture
The Physical Architecture is a
specialization of the Base Architecture
In this diagram the element with a
"system" stereotype with the name
The MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree
It inherits most of the parts from the
system element TMPCT Base Architecture
As we have seen before we
used illustrations in this case
instead of the block notation
which makes it easier for unexperienced
users to understand the diagram
The blocks from our Functional
Architecture are allocated
to the blocks of the Physical Architecture
The allocation specifies which physical
block implements which function block
Let's see how we manage
the allocations in a matrix
The rows list the function blocks
The columns the physical blocks
And the cells the allocate relationship
Some functional blocks are mapped to
more than one physical block
And some physical blocks have more
than one allocated functional block
It is a rather rough mapping
So for example if a functional block is
allocated to multiple physical blocks
it is not clear
whether it is redundantly allocated
are only parts of the functional block
However, this is usually
sufficient in the model
More details if required can be introduced
by extending the allocate
relationship with a stereotype
As with the Functional Architecture
the more interesting part is the internal
structure of the Physical Architecture
with ports and connections
that we will cover tomorrow
So much for the 13th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 13th of December
Bye-bye
Goodbye