[Music]
welcome to a new episode of the mbse
podcast
today we again have a very special guest
we
have invited david endler and
maybe you know david served for two
years as a cozy technical director
and is a member of ozen like tim
and an independent consultant and
trainer in the field of mbse and se
he can give us excellent information
about iso 5288 um as he is the lead
editor for the current version or
revision
as well as the lead editor for
24748-2 the guide to
15-88
welcome david
it's engineering
ah that was right my my first job so
when i left university i studied physics
here at the university of hamburg and i
was involved in a project at airbus
which was back in 2002 so i this year
i'm having my 20th anniversary in
systems engineering
because on the very first day on i apply
systems engineering to all my my
professional work
and in the meantime yeah so to say also
applied in some of my uh so to say
private endeavors
and uh how would you describe your
current role
um my current role is that i'm working
as a as a coach as a trainer or an
independent consultant on systems
engineering
uh doing some some minor consultancy
work but now mainly giving trainings on
systems engineering
for people who either just want to get
more proficient in systems engineering
or want to get certified either to the
incosi standard or to the se3 standard
which was developed here in germany
and well as a freelancer how do you
ensure that you can provide benefits to
your customers
um
i'm always
trying to be on
on top of things the same which means
that i'm trying to to learn as much as
possible
and as an as a freelancer of course i
must sort of say educate must help and
be up to date
and this is by by ensuring so to say is
a for volunteer work you know either for
in cozy or for for isil um just
discussing with all of the experts in
the area of systems engineering so this
is the way how i ensure so to say that
i'm then i'm up to date in order to
provide the maximum benefit for for my
customers
yeah great
so um
we are together here today mainly for
iso 5288 and we prepared some questions
and to all our live listeners if you
have questions for david just use the
live chat feature from youtube so you
can ask
questions and
we will
ask them to dub it
yeah david first question
uh
you're working or volunteering for iso
how did you come to iso
i otherwise there was a couple of years
ago when i was serving as the technical
director for the for the german chapter
of incosi and we had a very interesting
um talk at our presentation
at one of the national symposia from the
gfse the german chapter of inkosi
and it was introduced here that there
you can meet some some experts to
discuss so let's say the uh the current
divisions or in future revisions of uh
systems editing standards
so i volunteered yeah through gfse to
become a member of dean yeah which is
german national body for standardization
and um
and when i was just
getting more and more involved
the nkosi asked me if i'd be interested
in becoming their technical director
so i said okay i'm a freelancer so it's
i can do either or but i cannot do both
at the same time yeah because i also
must earn some money yeah so and then i
said
okay let's uh let's quote it so to say
on hold
the work for dean and iso
and after i served for four years in
total on the in cosi board of directors
so let's say i was just right in time to
become uh involved again
in the standardization work for the new
update of 1528
which was then kicked off someone last
year so there was a slight overlap
but it was still okay because i was
already preparing my retirement from
from ecosystem
so
we just call it 1528 and sometimes we
call it iso 5288 but the full name is
iso iec ieee 1528
so but is it an iso standard or is it an
iec standard or is it an ieee standard
and
but who is iso and
why can they publish standards and who's
iec and who's
ieee and how they are connected so can
you clarify that a bit
uh
yes of course although there's a lot of
questions
yeah
okay so um so first person i guess was
um
who owns so to say the standard so it's
all three of those standardization
organizations they work together so iso
is the international standardization
organization yeah with a lot of
different standards
iec is a little more specialized yeah in
for in terms of electronic comedies so
which means they are more related
to technical
standards uh ieee as well which is the
institute for electric electrical and
electronics engineers or something like
that yeah please forgive me if i mix it
up slightly
because we're just talking with those
evasions normally and uh not exactly
knowing what the aggregations mean
however all three of them they now work
together and they send their experts in
order to come up so let's say that the
the most beneficial wordings for the for
the end users
and
it is
currently
oh it depends on how how you do the
counting so the first version was
developed in 2002
uh then it was updated in 2008
and in 2004 i guess it was adopted by
ieee
and so then the 2008 version was already
um
sorry with ieee involvement
and the
2015 version was the first one when it
was iso iec i triple e now so therefore
so let's say the counter was reset to
zero you know to one
uh which means that the 2015 version was
the second revision
even though it was already third or
fourth yeah depending on how you count
and now it's the the 2015 version is the
one that is still up to date so to say
the last one it was reapproved
and now we're working on the 20
probably 2023 version that is about the
date when we expect that it will be
approved in about march time frame
so to say
one year from now
uh yes that's right yeah
okay
yeah david
so maybe not everybody is
is
familiar with the 5288 in depth so could
you give us a rough overview what the
content of 15 288
yeah sure so 15 to 88 is on on system
lifecycle processes
which means that it contains all of
those processes that you need as a
company
in order to build successful systems
so this comprises more than just
technical expertise so of course you
need to be very proficient in in the way
you're working and where you're
developing your your systems
and this is the area uh we all know very
well with the requirements
engineering with architecture definition
integration verification validation and
it ends with the disposal so the full
life cycle
is defined in this standard
but again this is not enough to be
successful on the market yeah so you
also have to manage your systems in
terms of technical management so you
have to apply something like project
management processes you know like
technical planning
uh configuration management risk
management decision management
so all of that must
work hand in hand with the with the
engineering activities
and in addition you also need to be on
the market which means that no company
that i know of is a has a depth of 100
which means you need to acquire some
systems or services that you need to
build your your systems
and at the same time of course you have
to bring your systems to the market
so acquisition and supply are grouped
under the so-called agreement processes
and then every company even my company
even though i'm just it's only me
working on several projects in parallel
yeah which means that you have something
have to have something like an
overarching uh project management uh for
all those different projects going on at
the same time
which is a so-called portfolio
management yeah giving priorities to
different projects in your organization
you need to have something like
knowledge management and quality
management system
so in all of these processes yeah all
together they form what we call the
organizational project enabling
processes
and all of that is
is part of 15 to 88 and this gives you a
full
overview of all the processes that you
need in order to be successful on the on
the on the market so this is in in brief
what is contained in 15 to 88
oh that sounds quite large so do you
know how thick the document is the
specification document the pdf how many
pages
uh it's a little bit more than 100 pages
if i remember right so the the content
is is it is rather sharp yeah so
it is not the case that this really uh
that you want to learn something about
systems engineering this is probably not
the document you should go for yeah
because
you need to have a lot of background
information on why certain things are in
there and how exactly it's meant to be
so it's not really a guide
but there's some there's some other
standards which do a much much better
job for example ieee 12 uh 12 207
was the uh
was the document that 15 to 80 days is
based on
and this had a lot of more examples how
to really implement how we do things
until then 15 to 88 so to say brought it
on on a next higher level
um okay yeah yeah just by coincidence we
have a
very good question uh also on on the
same topic so to say so one of our
listeners asks uh
should
uh very small entities uh
adopt 15 to 88 or should they better go
to 29 110
and
um how are those standards related are
the same people behind it uh
can you say something to that oh yeah
sure um so it's uh it's not really
exactly the same people behind it but it
is from the same working group within
iso yeah so therefore uh we have to pay
a lot of attention that those standards
are perfectly aligned
and
it really depends on your organization
yeah so if you're if you're used to
adapting um standards to your own
organization yeah so then uh 29 110 is
uh is perfectly fine
yeah it's an it's a huge series of um of
standards now with several sort of
cases here so depending on the size of
your company and the area you're working
in yeah they have different profiles i
guess they uh
that's in the right name
and then you have to pick the right
processes out of that and they are fully
aligned with 15 to 88 yeah so this is uh
that works perfectly fine
if you have no experience yeah in how to
tailor and how to adapt processes to
your own organization
it probably is easier to use 15 288
instead of 29 110 because you have to
find your way through
it's not really a jungle those processes
but you have to be a little more
experienced and how to adapt and how to
tailor standards to your organization
okay thank you
well i think you mentioned that uh the
first version of 5288 was published 2004
2002 or so and was it completely
developed from scratch or is it a
successor to to another standard
of course they didn't start from from
from scratches a lot of experienced
people were involved in the time so it
was more like so the same when when i
was just starting my systems using
careers i don't have full background on
how it really was involved
but the first one that i know of was was
mil standard 499
which was the first system engine
standard that was out there it was then
developed there wasn't was an ansi
standard on systems engineering so there
was a lot of pre-work already done
before
and 15-88 was the first version so to
say putting pulling together all of
those different threads out there
and then finally um iso convinced all of
the other
uh leading organizations to participate
in this effort
uh like in cozy like ieee and iec
and they all joined forces for the for
the 2008 version uh which was then so to
say the first one that was really uh so
let's say a common work within all of
the
different standardization organizations
okay but
what i don't really get is why is 5288
so important for systems engineering so
or
ask the other way around
can i apply systems engineering without
looking into 15 to 88
uh
definitely yes yeah so this one this one
just gives you so to say the framework
for your organization yeah it doesn't
really tell you how to really say in
detail apply
model-based systems engineering or
systems engineering it describes more or
less only the activities and tasks that
should be implemented in your your
organization
of course if you have something that
that has proven to work in the past yeah
it's always all it's all about tailoring
so yeah please never ever just take
fifteen to eighty eight and say oh now
we got a new standard process or
development process and this simply just
won't work
uh so therefore depending on your um on
the history of your organization
depending on your culture
and a few other things
um just look out for those chunks and
parts that you that you see oh we're
missing something here yeah then 1528
could really be a good benefit
but of course we all know that in
systems typically everything interacts
with everything else
so which means sometimes it's very
difficult just to cut out a few pieces
because all of that is somewhat
interconnected and in many cases it just
makes more sense to really adapt very
closely to 15 to 88
but at the same time what i always tell
my customers
make sure that you're using the right
language so say your language the
language of your organization
and make it work in a way that your
people will accept it
and therefore sometimes it may take two
maybe even three steps
um before you fully implemented 15 to 88
but i can imagine because it's very very
general a lot of companies out there
already comply to 1588 maybe without
knowing it yeah so that's
that's what i discover very often
but this is possible that that i as a
project can prove that i work according
to 15 to 88 so are there any assessments
and i can achieve uh 15 to 88 level 3 or
something like that or certificates
and i think this could be important for
for tenders for example no that is
requested that the company works
according to fishing 288 things like
that
uh yes of course and and and iso is uh
is also building their own business case
so to say yeah therefore they have uh
they've put together another iso
standard on on assessment of 1528 and uh
m12 207 which is so to say the other
standard on software engineering or
software system
development
and this is uh 33004
yeah from the 2015 version
which was just a remut 2020 so it's
still valid you know without any any
changes and this gives you guidance on
how to build all of those assessments
and uh how to prove that you're working
according to 15 to 88 yeah so again the
number it's 33004
yeah that's that's the one that you look
up
and of course you pay for that one again
and then you have to find companies yeah
there are many out there
typical suspects i would say
um that can help you in order to make
this process assessment and then you get
certified as an as a company or as an
organization that you're working
according to 1528
okay
so we already talked about uh the
version 2008 2015 and
you already mentioned that the next
version will
most likely be 2
20 23.
um
so can you give us some insights what
will the biggest changes of the new
version
um
as mentioned before is as a document
exists or for quite some time it's not
really a revolution so to say yeah so
there's no new processes were added
which always makes people very nervous
yeah when new processes are added
because then they are all of a sudden
yeah you are certified according to 15
to 88
then there is a new process and then you
have to make sure that you align again
with this that new standard
the only
change let me say on this on this very
high level was that one process was
slightly renamed from architecture
definition to system architecture
definition
which may seem that's really pretty
trivial and straightforward but it was a
huge discussion behind it yeah so
and uh um can maybe if
we can do it in in in another podcast
yeah because it will build at least one
hour or so
but anyway um
um they say look at it as in so they say
as an user of 1528
of course and since the last version is
from 2015
some other standards that are that are
referenced by 15 288 have been updated
in the meantime yeah like 16 or 85
which is the
standard on on risk management yeah and
this one has been updated in the
meantime so therefore change is done to
this one but now also implemented in
same is true for configuration
management and some some other areas
and mainly was them just as let's say
maybe minor minor changes you know to
some of the some of the contents
some of the things that we experienced
very often because of course the editors
on a regular basis they get feedback
also from the from the user community
and what we what we experience it very
often the concept of enabling system
into operating system in interfacing
systems was not very well understood
yeah so therefore we also expanded this
section
we gave some more explanation
about the concept definition you know
the very early stages of an of a project
so all of that is non-normative yeah
these are just the informative clauses
for the for the normative clauses yeah
and there was uh i say all these only
these these minor changes
like adding logistics to the maintenance
process as an example yeah it's um
in detail when you want to comply to 15
to 88 there's a there's some changes in
there but not too much you know so those
pros those organizations which are
currently certified according to the 15
1588 processes from 2015 it shouldn't be
a very big deal for them you know to
switch to the 2023 version
that's good news
yeah but
only it's something that you might be
very interested in is that we have a new
nxd which is also informative which is
that is uh some information on
model-based systems engineering yeah
something that was
that is new to this version
some other stuff was then just kicked
out because it was seen no longer to be
that
that important so to say
and this standard elaborates yeah on the
benefits of uh
of uh following a model based approach
to do assistant engineering yeah it
explains in more detail all of the
benefits that you have from from using a
model-based approach
for example in the very early stages
yeah and that you have a better uh
traceability that you have higher
consistency within all of your data sets
so all of all of that is now included in
15 to 88
i'm introducing um so or encouraging all
of the companies to do all of their
development model based
yeah i'm sure that was one of the big
criticisms on the current versions
uh that you did not have a link to mbse
does it provide a definition of mbse
uh in the very in the very first
sentence yes and i i knew they were
asking that
that one but it's not something because
tim you did some some some research and
very dis defined so so
nothing new yeah so it's it's still this
uh
this one the same one sentence and so to
say we we didn't dear uh as as iso
editors or as editors of 50 28
um let me say to start a huge
conversation and and discussion on on
the definition of model-based systems
engineering
okay
i try to have a look into the new
standards and open the iso website and
where the new standard is already listed
and i saw that uh now there's another
abbreviation added to the long name so
it's now it's an iso iec ieee dis 5288
standard so what is the meaning of dis
dis stands for draft international
standard
which means that
this one is now in in draft so it has
gone through a so-called working draft
stage so this was this was the very
first one so this is the stage where you
can do
so to say a lot of changes to the
standards yeah so you don't you don't
have to explain anybody
that's not really the case but the
editors have have some some freedom in
order to introduce new material
um all of that was based in a so-called
ad hoc group yeah so
i put together an ad hoc group of
experts
and asked them so please make uh propose
some changes to 15 28 that reflect
the current state of the practice
so the at the iso standards they always
reflect state of the practice and not
state of the art yeah which means that
everything that's so to say that's
already well known in industry that is
what comes into the standards
so it's not that much future looking as
maybe some uh some some some other
publications
and it really defines what is what is
currently done by many organizations um
in in the world
and from there on so they say then we
attached the so-called working draft
version with a lot of changes on we
implemented already a lot of the changes
i just mentioned
and then
it goes through the so-called cd phase
which are the commenting drafts which
are then sent out to all of the national
bodies yeah so here in germany that's
that's dean and upno in france and and
all of the others
and there's a voting behind it yeah so
there's a bulletin and you have comments
then you have to as editors we have to
do the so-called comments disposition so
we have to answer each and every comment
you know either accept or accept in
principle uh defer or we can also reject
them yeah but all of that needs to be
justified and then there's a huge iso
meeting again where all of these
dispositions are
discussed and then it moves on to the
next stage
and bis so to say
uh it's the is last one you know so
after this and it's a final uh draft
international standard so called fdis
and there it's only allowed to do very
really very minor changes you know like
some
spelling arrows and and things like that
but no longer no more uh technical
comments yeah if you say oh i'm unhappy
with the way how you deal uh how you
treat mbse
and we of course we collect it but it
will be then for the next revision in
2031 also
and can anyone file an issue or change
requests or
is it only possible through the national
parties like dean
yeah so this is so it's mainly for the
for the national bodies like like in
um and of course the dean
representatives very often they are also
asked to involve other experts as needed
yeah but they of course need to justify
and make sure that those people do not
distribute the
document with with everybody
and um
and then there's also so-called liaison
partners for example in cosy as a
so-called liaison partner which means
that they can provide comments but they
have no voting rights you know so they
cannot vote they cannot approve or
disapprove the whole document
but they provide a lot of experts and of
course they have a certain certain
standing in the um
in stabilization and in their treatment
on on systems engineering in general
which means that these comments are
treated just like any other
um comment from
from one of the national bodies
okay so if i'm interested in filing an
issue or change requests
um i should ask my
local chapter often cosy
right and then they
can help me
uh yeah
so so we within cosy there's a so-called
standards development department
i found it or which was put in place at
the time and i was the technical
director
and they are organizing all of the
reviews on the on the various
international standards uh very
inclusive intends to participate
in the in in the commenting phase
so yeah if you're interested get in
touch with the leader of the standard
development department
which is currently richard martin from
the usa
but his
deputy is daniel
from daniel's eagle from liberty yeah so
he's from austria at least
yeah we already had daniel here on the
podcast
okay good
yeah and i remember he mentioned this
yeah
yeah so
david i guess you are not writing the
standard alone
so
who else is on on this committee
so when we when when we started um it
was it was gary roedler leading the the
whole effort yeah um probably a lot of
people know gary rhoden and very very
experienced systems engineer he's an
cozy pioneer he's a nicosie fellow and
he's a lot of uh i'd say he's an esep
yeah so he he sort of say he achieved
all of the
certificates and and recognitions that
he can achieve in your your life as an
assistant engineer
and it is really it's really a big honor
for me uh working together with him
so he was leading the ad hoc team yeah
together with gerald jones also from the
united states and bill bearden who at
the same time is also a so-called
convener in in iso which means that he
oversees all of these standards within
the working group seven uh which is the
one on on on system life cycles
and uh from france yeah so it was a team
five of us we developed this uh this
this draft version
of course based on a couple of ideas
that we came up as a team
uh but also a lot of inputs that we
received yeah from from an iso meeting
where all of the national bodies
collected some ideas yeah so this is
what we brought forward
and then we worked ourselves through the
working draft the cd1 and cd2 and there
were two commenting drafts out there
and then gary decided because he's now
he now retired from from lockheed martin
and he said okay i want to get rid of
let me say getting all of these
involvements in cozy and iso and
everything so he asked me if i'd be
willing to take over as a project editor
in order to ensure yeah that all of his
knowledge is transferred to the next
generation yeah so so again it's a it's
a big honor for me to take over from
from gary
at the moment not really sure but i can
fill his footsteps you know because this
is really extremely hard
um but it's it's really it's a lot of
fun working with that that team they are
all so experienced and for me it's uh
like every meeting is just like waking
up and say
wow here thank you for sharing all of
that knowledge with me and trying to
learn as much as possible
knowing that in the next revision it
might be me then leading others uh to
the next revision of 15 28.
so and another important publication
systems engineering is definitely the
incosi handbook and if i open the it
goes handbook well it's it's full of
processes process descriptions uh so it
looks like that iso 5288 is also
described in the in the handbook and
um
is it fully covered in the handbook or
is it an interpretation of the iso
standards or what's what's the
relationship
so the the handbook an exhibition which
will also then be published in 2023
um
of course this is fully aligned with 15
to 88 and
this is done by just ensuring that the
same people work on
that work on 15 28 are also involved in
working on the handbook so gary reuter
is also an editor of the incosi handbook
and i was also just accepted as another
editor of the incosi handbook the next
revision which will then be
released and i say probably a couple of
months later than 1528
and
and of course yeah the description in
there it fully covers 15 to 88 from all
the processes that are described in 15
to 88 but it also elaborates a little
bit more on those on those processes so
it's got more than 400 pages yeah
it adds a couple of more details and
descriptions and best practices and
common approaches and tips and and all
of that is also part of the cozy
handbook
plus some material that is that is not
covered at all by 1528
um
like let me say in more detail about the
so-called quality characteristics yeah
like system safety and
environmental considerations
and all of that was formally known as
the so-called ilities but
today it's called more the quality
characteristics
so is it sufficient to read the in cozy
handbook or
do i have any value if i also read the
the standard
uh it depends on your use case so to say
if you want to be compliant with the 15
to 88 processes there is no other way
just to
to purchase 15 to 88
because it's not really cop one to one
copy
because uh in cosi doesn't have the
right to copy so to say 15 to 88 they
only may take the purpose of each
process and then the the activities but
not the tasks which is the more details
um a description of what exactly to do
and also 15-28 has only the process
outcomes so to say yeah which is more
general first in cozy handbook has a
so-called process outputs yeah so
there's a slight difference between
outcomes and outputs
so outcomes against more general about
okay you have achieved the following
and outputs other great documents
information items and and things like
that so it's a lot more detailed and
like in specification or an interface
document or or whatsoever you know so
this is but this is not covered by by
1528 there it is more general okay
okay
so and if uh 15 to 88 and the incosi
handbook is aligned uh is there also an
alignment between 5288 and the new
incosivision 2035
body cozy version 2035 is is very much
future looking you know so therefore
like what i said before 15 to 88 is
the state of the practice yeah which
means that
the iso standard is something like
uh let me say 10 years behind the
division document which is very much
future looking and explaining i say what
approach is necessary in order to
achieve this this vision or at least to
come close to it yeah probably cannot
fully achieve it
but what's uh what needs to be done
but really where all the things come
together is so to say that the
incosivision also promotes a picture
that we have to slightly change our
approach to systems engineering and such
and in particular on the in the way how
we educate our people uh in order that
they become um say they become more
fit for their work so to say yeah when
they apply systems engineering and they
of course then there's a big overlap to
15 to 88 because they will be working in
this environment and with 15 28
processes
so
i would say that was
much information
and
even stephan haute mentioned he again
learned new abbreviations
and a lot of new numbers
yeah that's for sure so the same for me
yeah yeah so this is this is really case
yes when you i also have here's kind of
kind of a list here so after a while you
get more and more used to it yeah to all
of these abbreviations and all these new
numbers yeah
and just in preparation for this service
call which was also my first question
when i was first involved well
what is the standard how how do you call
it yeah so is it is it fifteen thousand
two hundred eighty eight or is it
fifteen to eighty eight or just you
don't wanna be an idiot yeah when you
think about that one yeah so uh but i
can i can tell you yet it's just like
and you're here uh your slogan is yeah
trust us we're systems engineers so you
can you can do whatever you want yeah so
there's no big deal people will
understand what you're talking about and
you will not be uh
seen as somebody who is got no no idea
about this whole thing i mean you just
sort of
pronounce it in a slightly different way
than other students
okay so
thank you david for being with us um
i hope this was also very interesting
for our listeners so if you enjoyed this
episode think about uh
giving us a thumbs up or um
subscribe to the youtube channel to not
miss any other episode
so what's next tim
well it's not finally set we have some
ideas and we
also have asked some potential guess but
it's not finally set but we will
do that very soon
okay yeah tim you will be on the next
omg meeting so maybe
you find our next speaker there
yeah maybe so it's in uh
three weeks or so yeah in three weeks
and in residence and you're watching
the the second physical obg meeting
after the pandemic so that will be quite
interesting a lot of this will be to
stop of course so
almost every day the whole day this is
about v2 yeah this is quite interesting
if you as a listener want to know more
about csml v2 let give us a comment
under this video so we know that also
you are interested in system lv2 and we
can organize some more talks about it
sure so
well and then finally do not forget
trust us
we are systems engineers
bye bye goodbye thank you