hello behind the fourth door of our mbse
podcast advent calendar we take a look
at base architectures
we already mentioned the base
architecture in the previous days
now let's talk about what it is
in systems engineering we distinguish
the problem space at the solution space
for example the requirements are in the
problem space and are solution free and
the system architecture is in the
solution space and satisfies the
requirements
sounds simple but it's not
what does it mean that requirements are
solution free
so
what even is a solution
so can a requirement request a vehicle
that has four wheels or is wheel already
a solution
the separation of problem and solution
space is correct what is missing is a
consideration that there are several
levels of it as solution space on one
level is the basis for the problem space
on the next level
to return to the vehicle example on one
level we have requirements in the
problem space
that the system should be able to move
on roads
in the solution space we have chosen the
concept of wheel as one alternative
in the architecture to satisfy these
requirements
this architecture is the basis for the
next level the wheel is assumed and we
now set the requirement that there
should be four wheels with the size and
so on
the system architecture from the higher
level solution space we call our base
architecture
when we describe them explicitly we more
strongly separate the problem space from
the solution space and make implicit
assumptions explicit
the decisions in the base architecture
are constraint requirements for the next
level
so now let's have a look on our model
the base architecture
is modeled here in the base architecture
package and here we find the base
architecture definition diagram
so the base architecture of our
christmas tree
already specifies a lot
since the basic structure of a christmas
tree is fixed and not part of our
solution space the diagram shows the
definition of the elements in the block
definition diagram our mbse podcast
christmas tree abbreviated tmpct
base architecture includes a
transportation net a tree with a trunk
and branches a christmas tree star fairy
lights a stand and a transportation
package
system a modeling tools allows us to use
images instead of system shapes this
makes it more illustrative
the base architecture also leads to a
base system context which we define in
the following block definition diagram
external actors are the floor in a room
of course santa claus
the owner of the tree eventual children
a power supply the planet environment
for sustainability considerations and
the tmpct base architecture itself
depicted in an internal block diagram
shows the typical figure of a system
context diagram here
it is the context of our base
architecture
we left out most of the connections
inside our christmas tree they will be
defined later in the physical
architecture of our system
when we look at those we also see how
the relationship to the base
architecture can be modeled we will
explain the concept of ports connectors
and part properties in later
sessions when we consider the system
context we will cover how the system
context is related to the base
architecture context
so what was the surprise behind this
door
it's the base architecture itself that
makes it special
it's always there but is often
carelessly documented the blurring
between the problem space and the
solution space as well as implicit
assemb assumptions
leads to many potential problems in
development projects
so much for the fourth daw of our mbse
podcast advent calendar and we wish you
a great 4th of december
goodbye bye bye