Hello, behind the 4th door of
our MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
We take a look at Base Architectures
We already mentioned the Base
Architecture in the previous days
Now let's talk about what it is
In systems engineering, we distinguish
the problem space and the solution space
For example, the requirements are in
the problem space and are solution free
And the system architecture
is in the solution space
and satisfies the requirements
Sounds simple but it's not
What does it mean that
requirements are solution free
So, what even is a solution
So, can a requirement request
a vehicle that has four wheels?
Or is wheel already a solution?
The separation of problem
and solution space is correct
what is missing is a consideration
that there are several levels of it
As solution space on
one level is the basis
for the problem space
on the next level
To return to the vehicle example
on one level we have requirements
in the problem space
that the system should be
able to move on roads
In the solution space we have
chosen the concept of wheel
as one alternative
In the architecture to
satisfy these requirements
This architecture is the basis
for the next level
The wheel is assumed and
we now set the requirement
that there should be four wheels
with the size and so on
The system architecture from the
higher level solution space
we call our Base Architecture
When we describe them explicitly
we more strongly separate the problem
space from the solution space
and make implicit assumptions explicit
The decisions in the Base Architecture are
constraint requirements for the next level
So, now let's have a look on our model
The Base Architecture is modeled here
in the "TMPCT_BaseArchitecture" package
and here we find the Base
Architecture definition diagram
So, the Base Architecture of our
Christmas tree already specifies a lot
since the basic structure of
a Christmas tree is fixed
and not part of our solution space
The diagram shows the definition of the
elements in the block definition diagram
Our "MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree"
abbreviated "TMPCT"
Base Architecture includes
a "Transportation Net"
a "Tree" with a "Trunk" and "Branches"
a "Christmas Tree", "Star"
"Fairy Lights", a "Stand", and
a "Transportation Package"
SysML, a modeling tools allows us to
use images instead of SysML shapes
This makes it more illustrative
The Base Architecture also leads
to a Base System Context
which we define in the following
block definition diagram
External actors are
the "Floor" in a "Room"
Of course "Santa Claus"
the "Owner" of the tree
eventual "Children", a "Power Supply"
the "Planet Environment"
for sustainability considerations
and the "TMPCT_BaseArchitecture" itself
Depicted in an internal block diagram
shows the typical figure of
a system context diagram here
It is the context of our Base Architecture
We left out most of the connections
inside our Christmas tree
they will be defined later in the
Physical Architecture of our system
When we look at those
we also see how the relationship to
the Base Architecture can be modeled
we will explain the concept of ports
connectors and part properties
in later sessions
When we consider the system context
we will cover how the system context is
related to the Base Architecture Context
So, what was the surprise behind this door
It's the Base Architecture itself
that makes it special
It's always there but is
often carelessly documented
the blurring between the problem
space and the solution space
as well as implicit assumptions
leads to many potential problems
in development projects
So much for the 4th door of
our MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 4th of December
Goodbye
Bye-bye