Welcome to our MBSE
Podcast Advent Calendar
Behind the 11th door, we take again
look at the Functional Architecture
Yesterday we created Functional Groups
And today we look on the derivation
of the first version of
the Functional Architecture
And here comes the special
learning gift of this advent calendar
This step and other steps
of the FAS method
could be done automatically or assisted
by the FAS plugin for Magic Draw
that is provided by the German
chapter of INCOSE (GfSE)
You can download the plugin
for free from SourceForge
at https://sourceforge.net
/projects/fas4md/
The Functional Groups are
in the sub-packages
of Functional Architecture package
And for each Functional Group
we created a functional block
and model a trace relationship
between them
The functional block is also
a stereotype specializing the block
from the FAS profile
The relationships can again be
depicted in the matrix
In the matrix, you can easily see
all the functional blocks
have exactly one relation
to one Functional Group
We created the root functional block
that represents the whole
Functional Architecture
and created the composition structure
as depicted in the
following definition diagram
The more interesting part of
the Functional Architecture
is depicted in the internal block diagram
that we will see tomorrow
So much for the 11th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 11th of December
Good bye