Hello everybody and welcome back to our MBSE
podcast.
Today we will have an episode which I guess
many of you have waited for a long time because
today we will have the talk about the first
methodology and as Tim is author of and methodology.
We will take SYSMOD and its companion Vamos.
Have waited for a long time.
And sorry I have to.
Ah OK, great I I hurt myself.
So I had to mute myself.
So OK, we are talking about SYSMOD and vamos
and fuss and what these three things are and
how.
They are related.
And therefore, yeah, Tim, maybe we can start
directly with the first question.
What is a methodology?
Yeah, well, that's a very good question, and
it's for many charms.
Isn't anything?
It seems to be simple the first few, but it
isn't.
So, so there are many terms around methodology
of methodology, method and process and tasks.
Many terms that are most useful mostly.
But they aren't.
And so.
So personally, I like the definition from
James Martin, which he provides in his book
Systems Engineering Guide Book, A process
for developing systems and products from 1996.
That's also the definition Jeff SFM used in
this paper about this methodology's. That's
quite famous paper, it's.
Fully available.
Testifying in this methodology gave an overview
about investing methodologies, but it's quite
old.
And and the introduction chapter. He also
defined methodology. In other terms, they're
using James Martin's definitions, and when
I have to read this to be correct, so James
Martin defines a methodology as a collection
of related processes, methods, and tools.
Also, processes and methods and assignments
and so methodology is different meanings.
So methodology is this collection.
And now according to James Martin, at process
there's a logical sequence of tasks.
Performed to achieve a particular objective.
So for example, a requirement engineering
process or system architecting process validation
process and and so on.
And a method method describes the techniques
to perform a task.
So in our requirement engineering process,
you could have a task to define use cases
and then you can apply a use case method.
To do it.
And finally, part of the definition of methodology
was.
The term tool.
With related processes, methods and tools,
and Atul is that's just a thing and instrument
that apply to a method can enhance the efficiency
of the task so we can do use case analysis
with a pen as a tool over the system modeling
tool and so on.
So that's that's.
The tool.
OK and yeah, and I think this is very, very
important for many people who are starting
with systems engineering to exactly.
Yeah, understand this.
This difference and familiar process is something
that you want to make repeatable and something
which.
Is connected to roles and or to people who
are performing these roles with.
Certain methods.
Great cool.
And I think it's important that a.
Methodology is is a collection, so it's more
like a toolbox.
The methodology itself is not a strict process.
The toolbox that contains processes and other
things or.
Yeah yeah yeah.
And there is also much.
Literature about PMT in general.
So if you want to know more about methodologies,
you can also Google for PMT very often, and
you will find something.
OK, so today we want to speak about 1 certain
methodology called Seesmart and Varmus and
Fuss and Tim how are they related to each
other?
So this one, this is an NBC methodology and
it's mainly used for requirement in ring system
architectures.
Also the main technical processes and systems
engineering.
In addition, it also contains some some methods
for for the adoption of mercy and also considers
consulting and training and the set up of
the technical this environment.
Things like that, but the main part is requirements
engineering and system architecture, so that's
that's this.
And namus.
Stands for variant modeling with system.
Well, that one is is it's only a method, so
it's not a full methodology that describes
how to model variability of system in independent
of any specific product line engineering tool.
That was one of the main objectives of famous
to have.
An approach here only based on the system
standard and OCL which is sort of a part of
system.
And mail is defined in the context of this,
not so completely.
There's a small profile available and part
of the profile of the famous stereotypes,
but they're.
Independent with each other so.
And without almost fast, fast stands for functional
architectures.
For systems, that's a method, so it's also
not a methodology, it's it's only a method
for deriving a functional architecture from
from use cases representing the functional
requirements.
And I found this method.
Together with yes Golem around.
More than 10 years ago.
We practiced it's in the system.
Ending journal from Wiley and the current
version is published in our book model based
System Architecture.
OK, so.
We now know about the methods and we know,
we know we have to implement it in processes
to get it running.
But what about the tools?
Is it bound to a specific tool?
No, no, no, they are not bound to a specific
tool up.
Of course it's good to use a system modeling.
Tool for them so they are.
I know at least this part is independent of
system error.
Of course it fits very well, so at least it
needs a system error modeling tool and the
model just almost conflict with this.
But it's not specific.
Them toward any of the the tools.
And even less so today there are plugins available
and containing the profiles for for some modeling
tools, but they're only for for the convenience.
So if you.
Use a system modeling tool which is confirmed
to the standard and they lost profiles and
stereotypes.
You can easily define the profiles to set
the human system modeling task.
So it's no.
Need to do some programming or so.
But defining your profiles.
It's a very good idea.
In any case, you should customize the methodology
so you cannot use smart banners.
As well, any other methodology out of the
box?
Maybe only at the beginning as a starting
point, but in the end we must customize the
task to your specific needs, and then you
need your own profile.
OK, yeah, also a very important point.
Which from my point of view is sometimes.
Uhm yeah, the blocking element too.
Two to four for the adoption of Systems engineering
for many companies because for having your
own profile, you have to have.
Much knowledge about systems engineering,
general about methods and about this symbol
and profiling.
Yeah, and and only a few persons must know
the the profile mechanism.
Not every model must know it, but interestingly,
there's very less information available how
to do this.
Also, finding some system error.
It's your stuff in blue mailbox.
Define stereotypes, but you must know.
The meter model behind it.
And I think it's only documented in the specification
and specification is not a good document to
read its specification, and so there are no
teaching books, no trainings available, how
to do profiling and then everyone needs it.
OK, Mm-hmm yeah totally totally correct and
we will go into the meta model a little bit
deeper in and follow up question.
But first of all, you said fuss is more than
10 years old.
When and how did you invent this model?
Yes, this model is about 20 years old I think,
yeah, around.
But I I don't see myself as an inventor of
sports.
I'm I'm worthy.
The editor or orchestrator, also versus not,
contains lots and lots of methods.
That are very common, so and the intent of
those case methods and so on.
So in in detail I have find you.
It's so that everything fits well together,
and I also did the mapping tool to system
error or the detailed mapping to system, but
in general.
A set of common problems.
And I did this around 20 years ago and it's
based on the methods based on the human suffering.
During that time they were quite famous and
and I have transferred them into two systems
and to society.
Oh, OK.
And since then, this is what has developed
further, of course.
But the core is very stable, so it's quite
the same then.
20 years ago.
OK, I I really didn't know that it has a Umm,
history interesting.
Yeah, so it was yes it's 2001 or 2002 surgery
at that time. In that time I was already a
consultant and trainer for modeling, and during
that time Umm so. So it was not.
Yet, and most of my customers, that's Umm
modeling for software engineering, but I also
had some customers.
They used Umm for business processes and I
had some customers that do processes independent
of of software.
They would just make sure describe their business
processes or production.
Processes and I had some customers that would
like to use the.
Common human methodologies during that time.
That was the methodology space and to describe
systems.
So I remember a customer who would like to
describe however equipment also cranes etc
with humor and it's not very bad. And then
in 2003 we started with system.
And the only tricky benefits and during the
development of system error do I.
I created the system.
Try to adapt.
Adapt the system language.
We developed an example and at the end we
we had all the team had developed system and
I had people opt in.
Ah OK, OK, interesting.
OK, so since mode is very much as if I remember
correctly, it's very much about describing
the context and and in architecture, but.
Looking on the architecture side, we also
have the functional view of a system and.
And Fuhs is exactly is a method for exactly
this aspect of view of the system, but one
of the reason to invent a known method for
that.
Yeah, so so this much does not contain functional
architectures and this is not the architecture
is a physical architecture.
Uhm, let's so to say aside my smarts.
Instead of going directly from from the function
analysis those cases to the physical architecture,
you can go to the functional architecture
and then to the physical architecture.
And when a functional architecture.
Or functions.
But they are quite important that they are
the most important things of a system.
That's why we built the system to get the
functionality that I get.
We bought a car to move people to move things.
It's not because it's nice.
For some people, it's just because it's nice.
So functions are important, so it makes.
Sense to focus on them.
But typically requirements engineers have
to focus on on functions when they elaborate
functional requirements and so, but the architects
will focus on the architecture, so the the
technical stuff and Speaking of system so
they look on the block diagrams and they do
not have a focus on activity.
Diagrams sometimes a bit on state machines
and so, but their main focus is on the pure
structural stuff so.
So the idea was to choose.
Put a focus on the functions.
For the architects and.
Well, that was one of the main motivations
that would say, and the other motivation was
in the the architecture work to strictly separate
the more stable functional part from the more
unstable technical part.
In particular, in the last years the technology
changes very fast.
Via functions are still very listing so very
illustrative simple example is I.
I very often daily use the function listen
to music and I do this.
Since 40 years.
I I guess I guess nearly 50 years you had
a birthday last week or week before.
Yeah, but.
I understand it's a baby you made.
Not actively, I guess.
But the first physical solution was probably
a completely out record player, and then I
remember in the 1980s the CD player with Dire
straits also and then MP3 player and.
Are you streaming services in the business
models?
Changed, but the function is still the same.
More functions now in the streaming service
then in the playoffs.
So it's a little bit simplified, but very
instructive and shows the point.
Yeah, yeah, I I really like the example I
once learned in a training with.
Or was it?
Was it a training or was it a?
A speech, uh presentation from you with the
the.
A Coca Cola machine where you also have basic
functionalities which didn't change over the
years.
It still cools the drink.
It's still you still have to pay the drink.
The technology for paying the drink is different
from now to the 50s.
Or 60s or 70s or 80s where you only had the
possibilities we pay with coins.
Now you can also pay with credit card or by
NFC with your watch or your mobile phone and
so on.
But the basic functionality.
Pay for the drink is still the same.
They want the beverage.
And we have more and more decoupling.
Of functions and.
At the hardware the good parts, so they were
much closer in the past.
So simply said in the past, it was a one to
one relationship with one function.
And one physical thing.
To implement it, and now it's more more decoupled
and we still focus on the pure physical things.
So we.
I have not focused on the functions anymore
and then we get problems that we optimize
the physical part without knowing the impact
on the functions.
Yeah yeah, function is a good point so.
Infus you model the function as a block and
my question would be why not modeling as an
activity as activity inherits from structural
and behavioral metaclasses.
Huh, good question.
We we have two kind of functions so to say
we have.
The function in the problem space.
And and that function is still represented
by an activity as part of the use case model
where we use activities.
And basically we also use the activities in
the solution space in the architecture world
because in insertion error the activity model
element can be depicted on our block definition
diagram.
That's possible.
And and.
Yeah, you can show relationships between activities,
so compose those relationships or so, but
you cannot show the object flow, so we cannot
show the the parameters of the activity and
about the physician diagram you cannot connect
them and that's what we would like to see
is here.
So we set the architectural mailboxes.
Interfaces and connections and so that's not
possible in activity, so we need the block
for this.
So we pick the block, the function block.
The function block represents a set of.
Related functions.
And the function block gets plots depicting
the.
Functional interfaces and the entire program.
We can connect.
All this stuff yeah correct yeah.
And another reason is the function block is.
The the semantics of the function block does
not fit to the semantics of an activity.
An activity is a.
Is a behavioral element and shows the sequencing
of actions and the functional block is more
and more set of related.
Other functions that can process audio signals
also in that block.
Yeah, and stuff.
I think that.
Not the sequence from complete sequence.
Yeah, yeah, but if you want to give it a behavior
you can still.
Put a behavioral diagram on it.
Yeah, yeah.
Can can own behaviors.
This answer came on the activity diagrams
then.
That's possible.
We'd like to have that, yeah?
Was that you who listened to your speech or
training?
So could you use us for yourselves?
Indeed I did.
It was more or less in the beginning of my
systems engineering career when I had another
training with.
I guess it was Steven.
And and I was very impressed about his knowledge
of the UML metamodel, and everything was new
for me and it was.
Really interesting.
But besides the whole system L stuff, and
we we had a big focus on the method on the
fast method in this training and it was.
Very valuable too.
Or it was my moment in my life where I first
understood what a systems engineering method.
We had this example of the forest fire detection
system.
And yeah, yeah it it was extremely interesting
because you you go through these steps.
These method steps and we created a functional
architecture where we saw something can't
be right.
So we we had many.
Uh, is Attractional flows or something as
many flows between the functional architecture
and it didn't seem to be right and so we went
back one step and we we followed the instructions
again for this one step and then we we saw.
Well, now we get an architecture.
Which yeah, is is on the one hand simple.
On the other hand, straightforward and not
so many interconnections between the different
functional blocks.
And yeah, it was very interesting to do that.
And yeah, that was my first impression of.
I had a similar experience in a real project
that was also quite interesting, so we we
did most case analysis and then the plan was
to derive the functional architecture and
the workshop there were.
Requirement engineers and system architects
together and 1st.
We started with the use cases and.
We had the system architects.
But then it was.
A little bit boring, but it's.
Not not their word.
It's not block diagram, so it's full diagrams
for activities and of course they.
They said things are nice and yeah, correct.
There was no energy there and then we used
the fastpack in that was developed by the
working group and it was the first truck end
you can.
Create the first version of the functional
architectural.
Model is automatically.
Opposes to do some steps, but they recreate
automatically.
So we did that bang and we have the function
architecture and then the architects.
No, there's something that's kind of been
true, so this this architect gut feeling.
They they see this pattern of an architecture
and see the.
That's that's something wrong.
And then they analyzed it when we there's
a lot of flexibility and and we could trace
it back and there was an error, then the use
case model, but they had not seen that before
because that's not their words and their gut
feeling.
It doesn't work in the use case for it, but
it works on the architecture work.
It was quite interesting.
OK cool good story, so I guess it was was
interesting for both sides.
So that yeah, defining use case is important,
but you can do shady stuff in in this stage
and.
If you can trace it back you, you will even
have a bad functional architecture or you
will have some some change in a later phase,
which is very expensive regularly right?
Yeah, so it's quite a nice method and it's.
Easy to apply in workshops, even for people
who.
There's no modeling knowledge.
Now you can do this with with cards and so
that's very valid.
It's also in conferences, in in for our workshops
or so we we created from the beginning of
a system idea until the function architecture
we were able to do this for hours, so it was
very simplified, but it works without modeling
knowledge, so and but if you.
Model it then, of course, it's a little bit
complicated.
If we use the the plugins then a lot of that
stuff is behind the scenes in the scripts,
but if you have to do this completely yourself,
it's it's a lot of modeling because it's not
directly supported by my system and certainly
doesn't know the concept of functional architecture,
so this also doesn't work.
Concept of system context doesn't want to
model those things and then have sometimes
do a lot of things so.
They do a lot.
So, so the the modeling could be very hard,
and if you are not the experience of modeling
then it distracts you from the real interesting
engineering stuff and you'll focus on those.
Models and so.
Yeah, yeah.
So that's probably a disadvantage.
Yeah, but everything you you said in the last
sentences is also true for variant modeling
and so.
Yeah, let's switch to famous so so.
Basically famous address is another missing
piece.
Besides functional architecture, system context
and so on and in a missing piece in the smell,
so to say and and with famous you invented
a method to make it possible to model.
Variability in UML and smell right?
Yes, right so.
So some larger one I would say.
Yeah correct, yeah, no.
Nowadays we have to say this is an.
Operation one yeah.
Version one doesn't have explicit model elements
for Marion, so it's not part of the language,
and I remember that we discussed that variant
modeling issue when we developed this Melbourne
one now 20 years ago.
So so so the.
The idea was to create a modeling language
assistant model language as simple as possible
for various reasons, and so that was the reason
why we did not explicitly included variant
modeling to the language.
And at the same time it was clear for us that
we can do modeling variants with system, that
it's possible to do that, although there's
no explicit model element.
But you can do this mainly with the generalization
relationship is a kind of.
Core variant modeling relationships with the
C.
But we explicitly excluded it from the language,
and otherwise where.
Then we also had to include safety, which
is important in other things and then then.
Yeah, it would have cost more years to develop
system and it's a very large language.
And then you need tools that implement it.
Into all these.
So it's most intended to have a simple modeling
language.
Yeah, and then well, since it was published,
the project started using system and of course
the question came up.
Model variance assessment and.
When people say very good journalism relationship.
But you know how to use.
Its learn how to model their variation point.
And how to do?
This and this and that and how to model.
Variant constraint snow, like or exclusive,
all of two backgrounds.
Right?
And yeah, there's a constraint relationship
in system.
You can use that model, but how to do this
so and that was the idea of the famous approach
to to show how to do variant modeling with
fewer system.
So including stereotypes.
But there's no need for a specific.
So you can define variation points there.
Variable constraints all this stuff.
And configurations in the end.
In configurations and I also developed the
OCS statements behind the constraints, so
these exclusive all and so we can create a
variant consideration in the model.
And if the Troy can execute the constraints,
the model can check if it's a valid configuration.
Or not, so we have this scenario configuration
inside the modeling tool based on cues.
Then it's so that's quite nice, but variant
modeling is a very complex thing.
That's a multi dimensional configuration space,
so it's invariant complex thing.
And if we now use a modeling tool that has
no convenience functions for that, that just
uses the stereotypes from Bayless.
Then we have a limit there, so if it's getting
too complex then it's really hard to manage
those models in this modeling tool.
OK, did you ever use it in another SMM tool
outside Cameo Systems Modeler?
Uhm yeah also in.
With Oedipus architect.
But without the OCL stuff.
OK.
So so the also add statements are not executed,
but the description of the the variance is
possible enterprise architects and.
Yeah, also the diversity.
OK, well, interesting.
A few weeks ago, let's officials have pushed
the veils profile for absolutely it's.
I think it's not blocked, but.
Not sure.
Oh yeah, we can.
Look it up and and put it in the episode description.
If we find it.
And and in another project we combines.
Parts of the.
Based approach with pure systems the the Q
systems tool.
I'll send it through various yeah and the
senator told us from from big level.
Gears office.
So it's the same yes, yes.
Yes, right?
So so they can manage the the feature model
and they can manage configurations.
But they do not.
We contain the capability for the toward the
configuration model, so you can do the configuration
model with the base approach.
Manage then the config.
Operations with humans, for example.
OK, yeah, it reminds me that.
Reminds me of a that we that we really should
invite our little boy in our podcast.
Because he can tell us very very much about
product line engineering.
Feature oriented domain analyzes and so on
and so further.
Yeah yeah, but.
Speaking, Speaking of variation points and
variance and everything they must brings with
it and.
This is already included in system LV 2, isn't
it?
So is there still a need for Vegas later on?
I I have not analyzed that in detail, so this
will be tool will contain variants concepts
based on the ISO standard.
And there are four variant concepts that should
be portable.
Language variation points, variant variation,
variant binding for amendment correctly.
So the core concepts of merit modeling.
So not all concepts of famous cover basis
will be true, so so I assume that I will create
an update.
On on how famous looks like a system will
be true, especially to support the migration
from system we want.
Is this maybe two orders?
Which means laimos UM.
But most parts of the current famous thing
is then obsolete in the future and in the
long term I would then focus more on the variant
modeling methods in demos.
Demos is now more more language, no language
extension and the definition of the variant
concepts.
And not so much a method.
So I think it will focus many more on the
method.
For example, there's a new interesting upcoming
discipline model based product line engineering,
and.
East UM, which was product engineer with models.
And and I think there's a lot of.
Some space to define more methods or so, so
I think that that's the future of famous.
OK, interesting.
All right, so uhm?
I think we are through with smart, famous
and fast with the basic concepts.
Who wants to know more?
We will link all the books which were published
from Tim to all these topic.
Thanks and if you want a training you can
directly go to author and.
So yeah, ask them for consultancy and training
and if you enjoyed this episode, give us our
thumbs up.
Subscribe to the channel for free here on
YouTube to not miss out any future episode.
Which episode?
What's the next episode?
That's a good question.
Can you answer it?
I can't.
Yeah, yeah, no.
I I know that we look for we we are in contact
with the company in query a very interesting
company, but we plan an episode with them
in October November so.
So we look for date.
But we will definitely do episode before October,
November and and no, we have not defined it
yet.
Yeah, so if you or if you our listeners have
an idea, let's uh.
15 minutes.
Give us, give us a hint in the comments in
the comments section what you want to hear
about.
Maybe it's a little bit on update of System
LV 2 because there we are nearly at the final
submission.
Or other topics around systems engineering?
Uhm, if not we will we have a long list of
speakers?
Should be invited by us soon and and topics
so this should not be the end of the podcast
here.
Yeah, Tim was nice to speak to you.
It was even nicer to speak to you in person
on Monday and Switzerland.
Yes, it was a great conference.
This was it.
Perfect.
And great weather directly on Zurich.
See on the Zurich Lake was was a great conference
devil.
OK, so thanks for listening and do not forget.
Trust us yeah, assist with any lists.
We assistance engineers goodbye.
Bye bye.