welcome behind the six store of our mbse
podcast advent calendar we take a look
at the system use cases
there are a lot of methods for modeling
use cases published in many books papers
and other publications
we present a very simple method and
avoid use case relationships such as
include extend or generalization between
the use cases
the use cases here are simply a list of
the functions of the system in which
actors are involved and which create
value for an actor or stakeholder
so let's have a look in the model
some of our use cases of the mbse
podcast christmas tree are depicted in
the use case diagram with the associated
actors
there are a few special features in the
modeling
the actor carrier of the use case
transport christmas tree is a
generalization of the actor's christmas
tree seller and owner
it is an xor condition so the use case
has only one actor which could be either
the seller or an owner
the association end at the child actor
has a multiplicity zero to many
which means that children are optional
but they could be
there could be many of them
who are enjoying the christmas tree
although use case diagrams are very
common
they just show more or less only a
graphical list of use cases you can
depict the same information in a table
plus more properties
the table shows also documentation of
the use case as well as additional
properties introduced by the sysmod
stereotype system use case
for the trigger and the result of the
use case
the trigger signal property stores a
signal to formalize the trigger when the
use case is executed
you will meet it again when we talk
about state machines
and that's the learning surprise behind
the store tables are valid use of system
model elements and they can be much more
convenient than a diagram
you do not have the layout effort and
depending on the tool tables are
typically queries and always up to date
use the tables for the daily engineering
work and diagrams for workshops
presentations or eventually documents
so much for the sixth door of the mbse
podcast advent calendar
we wish you a great 6th of december
goodbye