Welcome behind the 6th door of
our MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
We take a look at the System Use Cases
There are a lot of methods for
modeling use cases
published in many books papers
and other publications
We present a very simple method
and avoid use case relationships
such as include, extend
or generalization
between the use cases
The use cases here are simply a list
of the functions of the system
in which actors are involved and which
create value for an actor or stakeholder
So, let's have a look in the model
Some of our use cases of the
"MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree"
are depicted in the use case diagram
with the associated actors
There are a few special
features in the modeling
The actor "Carrier" of the use case
"Transport Christmas tree"
is a generalization of the actor's
"Christmas Tree Seller" and "Owner"
It is an XOR condition
So, the use case has only one actor which
could be either the "Seller" or an "Owner"
The association end at the "Child" actor
has a multiplicity zero to many
which means that Children are optional
But they could be
there could be many of them
who are enjoying the Christmas tree
Although use case diagrams
are very common
They just show more or less only
a graphical list of use cases
you can depict the same information
in a table plus more properties
The table shows also documentation
of the use case
as well as additional properties
introduced by the SYSMOD
stereotype "systemUseCase"
for the trigger and
the result of the use case
The trigger signal property stores a
signal to formalize the trigger
when the use case is executed
You will meet it again when
we talk about state machines
And that's the learning surprise
behind the store
Tables are valid use of
SysML model elements
And they can be much more
convenient than a diagram
You do not have the layout effort
And depending on the tool
tables are typically queries
and always up to date
Use the tables for the daily
engineering work and diagrams
for workshops presentations
or eventually documents
So much for the 6th door of the
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
We wish you a great 6th of December
Goodbye