welcome to the mbse podcast advent
calendar
we will open a new door every day until
december 24th this means that every day
there will be a short mbse podcast
episode
in 25 episodes we will each briefly
describe how to model a system using the
system methodology each episode
highlights a new aspect the system is
our super cool mbse podcast christmas
tree
of course the example is not entirely
serious
but we are modeling seriously
sometimes this will make
it look a little bit strange but
certainly very much like over modeling
with our advent calendar you get a
lightweight overview of modeling a
system and the essential steps of the
mbse methodology sysmod in addition each
episode also contains a small gift in
the form of a good practice
the advent calendar episodes are a
little bit differently to our previous
episodes they are only about five
minutes long and we don't have guests
and
since we are showing how to model the
audio only channel only works to a
limited extent
and we use the camille systems modeler
and the sysmod profile as our systems
modeling environment for the project
however any other system compliant
morning tool could also be used for the
project
in 2022 we will continue with our
regular
mbse podcast episodes with live sessions
and exciting guests from the mbse
community
okay so now let's take a first look at
our model
on the left side of the model you can
see the model structure
the package derived properties is too
specific and we will not have any
further look on this one
the international christmas tree
standard is a model library covered in
the following sessions about
requirements
and the package symbol with the tiny
triangle is the root of our product
model the mbse podcast christmas tree or
abbreviated tm pct
and on the next level you can see
packages for several engineering
artifacts like the context, requirements
or the architectures they will be
covered step by step in the following
episodes
and here comes our special learning gift
of this episode
it is a good practice to design the
package structure the following way at
the top level separation is made
according to primary engineering
artifacts the package names are each
given the namespace above as a prefix
for example t and pct underscore context
at the base architecture or physical
architecture level below the elements of
individual components of the system such
as the tree itself are stored in their
own packages
their substructure behaves like the
structure of the system model thus the
package structure scales very well
if required these packages can be cut
out and used as separate system models
now let's open the package diagram tmpct
model structure it depicts the applied
profiles
and used libraries of our system model
as you can see from left to right we
applied the sysmod profile to use sysmod
specific model elements like
system system context or system use
cases
we also applied the fast profile for
modeling the functional architecture
using the first method and we imported
engineering for planet model library for
sustainability elements
that library is provided also by sysmod
we import the passcatalog model library
to get some nice reusable elements the
library is also provided by the smart
and we import the international
christmas standard model library to get
common christmas tree requirements
all the profiles and libraries will be
used in some of the following sessions
as well as will be explicitly covered
by
other episodes about profiles and model
libraries
so much for the first tour of our mbse
podcast advanced calendar and we wish
you a great first of december
goodbye