Welcome to the MBSE Podcast
Advent Calendar
We will open a new door every day
until December 24th
This means that every day there will be
a short MBSE Podcast episode
In 25 episodes we will
each briefly describe
how to model a system
using the SYSMOD methodology
Each episode highlights a new aspect
the system is our super cool
MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree
Of course, the example is
not entirely serious
but we are modeling seriously
Sometimes this will make
it look a little bit strange
but certainly very much like over modeling
With our Advent Calendar
you get a lightweight overview
of modeling a system
and the essential steps of
the MBSE methodology SYSMOD
In addition, each episode
also contains a small gift
in the form of a good practice
The Advent Calendar episodes are a little
bit differently to our previous episodes
they are only about five minutes long
and we don't have guests
And since we are showing how to model
the audio only channel only
works to a limited extent
And we use the Cameo Systems Modeler
and the SYSMOD profile as our systems
modeling environment for the project
However any other SysML compliant morning
tool could also be used for the project
In 2022 we will continue with our regular
MBSE Podcast episodes with live sessions
and exciting guests from
the MBSE community
Okay so now
Let's take a first look at our model
On the left side of the model
you can see the model structure
The package Derived Properties
is too specific
and we will not have any further
look on this one
The International Christmas
Tree Standard is a model library
covered in the following sessions
about requirements
And the package symbol with the tiny
triangle is the root of our product model
The MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree
or abbreviated TMPCT
And on the next level, you can see
packages for several engineering artifacts
like the context, requirements
or the architectures
They will be covered step by step
in the following episodes
And here comes our special
learning gift of this episode
It is a good practice to design the
package structure the following way
At the top level separation is made
according to primary engineering artifacts
The package names are each given
the namespace above as a prefix
For example, "TMPCT_Context"
At the base architecture or
physical architecture level below
the elements of individual
components of the system
such as the Tree itself are stored
in their own packages
Their substructure behaves like
the structure of the system model
Thus the package structure
scales very well
if required these packages can be cut out
and used as separate system models
Now, let's open the package
diagram TMPCT model structure
It depicts the applied profiles
and used libraries of our system model
As you can see from left to right
we applied the SYSMOD profile to use
SYSMOD specific model elements
like System, System Context,
or System Use Cases
we also applied the FAS profile
for modeling the functional architecture
using the FAS method
And we imported Engineering4Planet
model library for sustainability elements
That library is provided also by SYSMOD
We import the PartsCatalogue model library
to get some nice reusable elements
The library is also provided
by the SYSMOD
And we import the International
Christmas Standard model library
to get common Christmas tree requirements
All the profiles and libraries will be
used in some of the following sessions
as well as will be explicitly
covered by other episodes
about profiles and model libraries
So, much for the first tour of our
MBSE Podcast Advanced Calendar
And we wish you a great first of December
Goodbye