welcome to the 15th store of our mbse
podcast event calendar today we take a
look at the modeling of interfaces
typically you use ports type by
interface blocks with a connector you
model the connection between two ports
let's have a look at our physical
architecture in the model
the connection between the trunk and the
stand is a typical interface
specification two ports type by
interface block named standport
connected with a connector
today we show you a way to specify an
interface in more detail a connector can
be typed by an association or
association block
an association block can define details
of the connection
the following block definition diagram
shows the definition of the association
block
plug socket interface between two
interface blocks plug port and socket
port each with nested ports
in addition the association block has a
part property specifying the power cable
with length of 200 centimeters
like any other block an association
block can have an internal structure
which is depicted in the internal block
diagram
the dashed rectangles on the left and
the right are the references to the
association and typed by the interface
blocks
with the nested ports
here we have modeled a simple structure
by connecting the nested ports directly
this interface definition is applied
between the external power supply and
our christmas tree as depicted in the
following diagram
so much for the 15th door of our mbse
podcast advent calendar and we wish you
a great 15th of december