Welcome to the 15th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
Today we take a look at
the modeling of interfaces
Typically you use ports
typed by interface blocks
With a connector you model
the connection between two ports
Let's have a look at our
Physical Architecture in the model
The connection between
the "trunk" and the "stand"
is a typical interface specification
Two ports type by interface block
named "StandPort"
connected with a connector
Today we show you a way to
specify an interface in more detail
A connector can be typed by
an association or association block
An association block can define
details of the connection
The following block definition diagram
shows the definition of the association
block "PlugSockectInterface"
between two interface blocks
"PlugPort" and "SocketPort"
each with nested ports
In addition the association
block has a part property
specifying the "powerCable"
with length of 200 centimeters
Like any other block, an association
block can have an internal structure
which is depicted in
the internal block diagram
The dashed rectangles on the left
and the right are the references
to the association and typed
by the interface blocks
with the nested ports
Here we have modeled a simple structure
by connecting the nested ports directly
This interface definition is applied
between the external power supply
and our Christmas tree
as depicted in the following diagram
So much for the 15th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 15th of December