welcome to the 22nd door of our mbse
podcast advent calendar
today we travel to the future and model
our great mbse podcast christmas tree
with the next generation modeling
language sysmlv2
system rb2 is currently under
development it will be officially
available probably in 2023 or 2024 so
there's still some time however it is
already interesting to take a look at it
now in order to set the cost in good
time two to three years is a very short
time in relation to major changes in the
process and tool landscape in mbsd
the csml submission team sst for short
is currently working on the
specification of system lv2 what is
great is that they also provide a pilot
implementation so that you can
experiment with system lv2
we use the pilot implementation based on
jupiter lab to show you some more or
less equivalent system lv2 models of our
christmas tree
to avoid having to set up a jupiter lab
environment yourself my company also
provides a ready-to-use implementation
at
systemlv2lab.com
here you will find a general
introduction to system level 2 the
current state of the specification and
many examples you can also create your
own models and play around with them but
be aware from time to time the server
will be restarted and all files will be
lost if you want to save your models you
have to download them manually
we have already uploaded our jupyter
notebook for the mbse podcast christmas
tree
system lv2 offers a textual notation in
addition to the graphical notation known
from system lv1
to create the models in the pilot
implementation
one has to use the textual notation and
then can generate the graphical notation
automatically
later there will probably be graphical
editors for system lv2 as well
so let's have a look into the jupyter
lab
our tmpct model is a simplified version
of our system lv1 physical architecture
of the christmas tree
we have directly modeled the parts
they have no explicit type here
simplified in system will be one it
would mean to define part properties
without blocks
what works in system v2 but not in
system v1
is that the parts can also define
structures themselves as you can see
here for example with the part 3 which
defines the trunk the branches
and an attribute for the head of the
tree
if no type is defined however a type
from the system library of system lv2 is
implicitly set in the background
also a part
always needs a context
if this is not given
as for example with our top level part
the mbse podcast christmas tree
then the element anything from the
kermal base library is set as the
context as the context for the element
by the way kernel is the meta model of
system lv2
for one part we set the type the part
ball is of type christmas tree ball
which is defined at the end it contains
the definition of an enumeration which
is then used to specify the attribute
color
so far all we have is a list of things
the diagram is therefore also just a
simple tree structure which of course
fits perfectly with our christmas tree
project
the graphical notation of system lb2 is
very similar to systemarry one one
difference in the diagram is the
relationship between the part ball and
the part definition christmas tree ball
the relationship with the two points is
defined by relationship
now we add some connections to our model
for example we use
simple connection relationships
and if we visualize the model we can see
the structure of our christmas tree
however since the visualization is
generated automatically we cannot adjust
the layout
so much for the 20-second door of imbc
podcast event calendar and we wish you a
great 22nd of december
bye