Welcome to the 22nd door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
Today we travel to the future and model
our great MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree
with the next generation
modeling language SysML v2
The SysML v2 is currently
under development
It will be officially available
probably in 2023 or 2024
So, there's still some time
however it is already interesting
to take a look at it now
in order to set the cost in good time
Two to three years is a very short
time in relation to major changes
in the process and tool
landscape in MBSE
The SysML Submission Team
SST for short is currently working
on the specification of SysML v2
What is great is that they also
provide a pilot implementation
So that you can experiment with SysML v2
We use the pilot implementation
based on Jupyter Lab
to show you some
more or less equivalent
SysML v2 models of our Christmas tree
To avoid having to set up a Jupyter Lab
environment yourself
my company provides a ready-to-use
implementation at systemlv2lab.com
Here you will find a general
introduction to SysML v2
The current state of the
specification and many examples
You can also create your own
models and play around with them
But be aware from time to time
the server will be restarted
and all files will be lost
if you want to save your models
you have to download them manually
We have already uploaded
our Jupyter Notebook
for the MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree
SysML v2 offers a textual notation
in addition to the graphical notation
known from SysML v1
To create the models in
the pilot implementation
one has to use the textual notation
an then can generate the
graphical notation automatically
Later there will probably be graphical
editors for SysML v2 as well
So, let's have a look into
the Jupyter Lab
Our TMPCT model is a simplified version
of our SysML v1 Physical Architecture
of the Christmas tree
We have directly modeled the parts
They have no explicit type here
Simplified in SysML v1
it would mean to define part
properties without blocks
What works in SysML v2
but not in SysML v1
is that the parts can also
define structures themselves
as you can see here
for example with the tree
which defines the "trunk", the "branches"
and an attribute for
the "height" of the tree
If no type is defined however a type
from the system library of SysML v2
is implicitly set in the background
Also a part always needs a context
If this is not given as for example
with our top level part
"theMBSEPodcastChristmasTree"
then the element anything
from the kernel base library
is set as the context for the element
By the way, kernel is
the meta model of SysML v2
For one part, we set the type
The part "ball" is of type
"ChristmasTreeBall"
which is defined at the end
it contains the definition
of an enumeration
which is then used to
specify the attribute "color"
So far, all we have is a list of things
The diagram is therefore
also just a simple tree structure
which of course fits perfectly
with our Christmas tree project
The graphical notation of SysML v2 is
very similar to SysML v1
One difference in the diagram
is the relationship
between the part "ball" and
the part definition "ChristmasTreeBall"
the relationship with the two
points is defined by relationship
Now we add some connections to our model
For example, we use simple
connection relationships
And if we visualize the model, we can see
the structure of our Christmas tree
However since the visualization
is generated automatically
we cannot adjust the layout
So much for the 22nd door of
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 22nd of December
Bye-bye