Hello, behind the 2nd door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
We describe the System Idea
and the System Goals
The System Idea is the elevator pitch
of the system of interest
It briefly and crisply describes
what a system is
with special focus on
what makes it special
It is a text and provided
the graphics if needed
Let's look at it in the model
The SysML language does not know
the concept of System Idea
Interesting, SysML does not know
the concept of System either
although it's a systems modeling language
You can teach the language new concepts
We have the profiles
and stereotypes about this
Behind what are the following doors
there will be the exposit
explanation about this as well
Here in a nutshell, SYSMOD introduces
the concept of a system by a stereotype
specialized from the block
And you can define the System
Idea as a property of it
In the model, it can then
be represented like this
It is a too specific property
that the texts can be formatted
If graphics are a part of
the System Idea, they are all friends
The System Idea of
the Christmas tree is as follows
"The Christmas tree is the symbolic
centre of the Christmas celebration"
and delights people
especially children
"The Christmas tree branches prevent
evil spirits from entering the house
and give hope for the next spring"
The System Objectives are also a concept
that SysML does not recognize
SYSMOD again uses the stereotype
to include it to the language
The System Objective is a special
form of a SysML Requirement
The following requirements diagram shows
the objectives of our Christmas tree
We have an upper-level
summarizing objective "OBJ0"
which summarizes all the
"MBSE Christmas Tree Objectives"
And we have different objectives like
having the "Best Christmas Tree"
the "Number of Gifts"
"Zero Footprint" on the environment
and we all trace it back
to the "MBSE Podcast"
The diagram topology of the
elements doesn't include much yet
So, it is a good practice instead to
manage the model information in tables
In this stage a lot of modeling efforts
In addition, today's modeling tools'
tables are usually more furious
that means they show all
elements in the model
In the diagram
there are only the elements that
a modeler has placed manually on it
If needed, the diagram can be created
quickly easily for a workshop
You may have noticed the stakeholder
System Objectives just have a
relationship to the stakeholders
who are responsible for the goal
Here, it is the Podcast hosts
Christian and me
And as we are responsible for
the overall of the system
SysML knows the concept of a stakeholder
And SYSMOD never the less defines
the stereotype "extendedStakeholder"
to extend special properties like
a contract or a priority
Since the stakeholders are also
related to the requirements
they are also belong there
They are stored in the
requirement package in the model
You could represent them in the diagram
as much more practical tabular form
The table does not show all properties
of the stakeholders in this case
but only the name, documentation
the contact information, and a priority
So much for the 2nd door of
our MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 2nd of December
Goodbye
Bye-bye