hello welcome to a new episode of our
mbse podcast
like many others we had a little summer
break but now we are back
the swiss conference will take place
next month september the 6th in zurich
in switzerland of course
and we take this as an opportunity to
talk a little bit about the conference
of the local swiss in cozy chapter and
our guest is professor marco di mao who
is one of the organizers of the
conference and welcome marco and please
introduce yourself hello
um
thanks tim and christian for inviting me
to this podcast first time on this show
so to say
and
think about myself so i'm currently
professor of systems engineering at
ingles start university
and
i live in switzerland which is why i'm
part of this
amazing event this we said 21
and i also work for the swiss chapter so
you know that that's the connection to
today's podcast before i became
professor i ran my own consultancy for
systems engineering for huge projects
mainly fusion research nuclear fusion
research so
the biggest experiments in the world
currently uh run and the
the nicest one is but it's it's probably
not the nicest project but it's
definitely the nicest location it's in
the south of france where i worked for
six years and after that in oxford for
the successor of eta which you probably
have heard
and yes i've i've been involved in in
cozy for about 10 years now so i know
tim and christian because i was member
of the german chapter for quite a while
and as i said i now live in switzerland
so i'm now a member of the swiss chapter
and also member of the organizing
committee for all sorts of things
all right thank you for your
introduction
yeah it's a pleasure to have you with us
um
and i guess many of our
podcast listeners will see that we have
again quite a new
series like uh mbse events
and so we are talking about swiss today
and swiss is
swiss ad
like i learned before
swiss ad is a systems engineering
conference but what does it stand for
so as we said um yeah it's it's a
mangled word like a portmanteau so
basically there's swiss in there you
know obviously it's the swiss
and then we have the systems engineering
day is said so it's you know kind of a
mix but basically it's a swiss
systems engineering day so it's one day
every year where the whole of
switzerland plus
friends and
family sort of say long-standing friends
come together to um lake zurich where we
hold it and have an i have a really nice
day where we talk about systems
engineering and have lots of very
interesting keynotes and presentations
and uh who's the organization behind
swiss
so uh the organization behind the swiss
ed is the system the oh sorry yeah we
didn't call it swiss because you've been
switched um
so
we call the swiss chapter of in cozy
it's called ssse which stands for um
the swiss society of systems engineering
and
um yes
we run it
as a bit like the tdse in germany you
know it's our flagship event
every year
so this edge should also be written with
3s right because this is systems
engineering and maybe it's free
it should be that's that's why i say
it's like uh
and an acronym
i don't know what the actual grammatics
you know the term for it is but yes it
should be swiss sed
um but maybe it's like in german where
you can't do the three s in in one word
unless there's a t after the third one
or something remember your weird
grammar rules in germany
how do you spell the abbreviation for
the chapter this is
s-s-s-e-r yes
c-c
see
i think we say ssse yeah this is z
okay that was one s too much
it's three s n e so triple s e we should
call it right like i triple e yeah
triple s plus e
that's actually that you know and then
we could make up ideas of what the three
s e's you know it could be three s e
then
uh i'll put it i'll put it in the you
know for the
um to discuss it when we actually
committing
all right the agenda
yeah so
how do you organize this conference the
swiss ad
do you have a professional agency or
just by volunteers
um
actually no we do it it's all voluntary
work so it's it's as i said we have this
committee
and we're between six and ten people who
run the ssse and we also organize this
with it as i say it's our flagship so
it's it's
um
yeah
it is actually the event that draws in
people so it's a bit like a marketing
thing as well as our
focus event where we you know talk about
new ideas and systems engineering and
all that so
all the volunteers who do it really like
to work for it because yes it's it's
quite a bit of work but it's also you
have you get to know a lot of people a
lot of players internationally so some
of our sponsors for example come from
australia
why ever but um
so it's a lot of fun to do it plus we
meet regularly and
okay now with covet we meet remote but
not all of us because um some people
work in the same company so they use one
of the offices and then we have a video
conferencing with them um you know where
we are remote and then they're there
drinking beer bastards and now it's a
lot of fun so we do it as the swiss
chapter but it's it's like a circle of
friends organizing a party basically
a bit more professional sorry i don't
want to give you the wrong impressions
but
yeah it's very professional
yeah but to be at the party it cost
money so
as a participant i have to of course pay
a registration fee uh do you know how
much is it and is there a discount for
the cosy members
yeah so hey
it's you don't really pay money it's
it's like it's a small fee compared to
other conferences definitely i think
it's about 100 francs or 120 or
something it's not not that much and
then there is a discount definitely for
uh in cozy members i'm i'm
i'm not the secretary of the
i don't know the actual price but you
can find them on the registration site
but it's it's definitely um
i wouldn't even call it a fee because
you get a lot for it it's it's basically
the entrance to a really nice venue i
don't know i think we might talk about
the venue later but um the venue is on
lake zurich it's the casino of zurich
and so it's an amazing venue with a
really nice view
and we have i think you might want to
correct me but i've been to lots of
systems engineering conferences all over
the world
and i think we have the best catering
so you get a really nice lunch buffet
and
we haven't we always have an upper row
and you can then have it on the terrace
right basically sitting on a balcony
overlooking lake zurich
and good wine and and even even good
beer and always good weather so
almost everything's crossed this year
right
we haven't had a summer in switzerland
and with lots of hail so yeah fingers
crossed but yes it's normally a really
nice thing
okay
so
the swiss chapter is quite young but you
already have quite a history in swiss ad
so when was it held the first time
so the first swiss ad was the same year
when the swiss chapter was founded 2014.
so this is the eighth edition of it
coming up and
yes we've we've held it every year even
last year with the
say the more
although in september it was it eased a
lot so we we held it as a hybrid
conference as we will
this year so
we haven't lapsed yet eight years in a
row
and we've yeah it's it's been a very
varied conference with lots of nice
contributions from
you know
a nice
say a cross-section of the people that
you would expect at a systems
engineering conference
yeah i remember last year that was
great was my only in-person event last
year so in the second half last year
it was very surprising it was very
strange to travel again to to meet
people
yes and we had we had two in two or
three weeks within two or three weeks we
had the
uh requirements engineering conference
the ieee one that was in zurich and that
was also an in-person event
at the university and then um suicide
yes so hybrid event but we i mean you
were there tim and christine you were
there as well right so
no last year no i skipped last year you
skipped this i always see your face when
i come in like that
it's like the first person you see as we
said sorry
um yes but
so so we had it in a
nice personal event
and um
it's it's as i say the the content is is
really varied and it's
probably less than 60 percent of swiss
contributors yeah it's probably less
than 50 even service contributions so we
get them from all over the world
speakers
who were the speakers so in the past can
you name a few of them
yes we had
a lot of the high caliber ones
so the the keynotes alone is like the um
who's who of systems engineering so we
had olivier divek who runs the systems
engineering class at mit
we had larry liefer who's
kind of the he's not the inventor of
design thinking but he's definitely one
of the icons of design thinking in
stanford university we have dave snowden
who invented the kinevic um or kinevin
framework
um for you know
what is it uh
complexity yes so it's
i couldn't remember i think it's he's
got different names but it's roughly
it's simple
it's com um complicated complex and
chaotic and then you have this really
nice fault in the middle so where you
can basically go
jump into chaos from from any of the
four so um that was one of the like the
keynotes that stand out in my head
because it was the first time i saw dave
and then i immediately booked his class
he came to i think he stayed in zurich i
think it was two weeks later so
and we had yourself tim
you're not only a regular contributor
but also we had yet
as a keynote
and david long you know everybody who
knows in cozy knows probably david long
from tech
and john holt you know i don't know was
it last time you had him on the on the
podcast but you definitely had him on
your plate yes
after that germany lost against uk
in the
soccer championship as they should
the man with the
or was it his
for everyone who doesn't know john so
he's the magician systems engineer
and
so he's got this black hat and he's
always dressed in black and then he
always claims to give a presentation in
one slide but it's heavily animated
yeah it's a lot of good fun um last year
we also had michael lyric
he's also one of the design thinkers
yeah so it's a really nice
selection
how do we get all these people so how do
you get in contact with larry life oh
well they they direct us they contact us
no no
no
i think i think
and this i think it's also the same when
i was in gfc it kind of is all about
networking and then these contexts just
emerge in a way so it's like an emergent
behavior like in systems engineering
anyway so um i know that mike johnson
who's a household name in the swiss um
chapter not only but you know everybody
who knows
about or is interested in systems
engineering switzerland would know um
michael mike johnson and he contributed
to the design thinking playbook
which is the the famous one by larry and
michael
and so i'm guessing that that was you
know where this connection came from
olivier
also he is not only at mit but he's also
the class runs at mit and epfl at the
same time so epfl is in lausanne right
so that is also swiss connection and i
think he's actually from eth zurich so
you know that's all like um dave
and mike work together so that's where
dave snowden probably came from
well tim we all know you so
um
yes and and david long is is also one uh
one of the people who who likes to come
to europe europe and help us
presenting stuff and john obviously he's
you know he's everywhere
right
yeah so you already told us about the
venue which i can confirm which is
really nice and
uh
so if if somebody
chooses to be part of of swissette
what can you expect how how does the
work the conference
that works conference day
well i think i already hinted at it so
it is and and it has been before i moved
to switzerland it is my favorite systems
engineering conference because a it's
not
it's not as stiff as any of the ieee
ones so it's not about publication it's
not about
being seen and you know showing off and
ooh look at what i my research so it's
less presenting research it's more
presenting experience and talk about it
so it's it's a really relaxed atmosphere
i think that's my main point and then
because it's so relaxed and because the
catering is so nice and most people
drink wine at lunch
um everybody's really approachable so as
i said you know i met dave well i saw
dave in that
keynote he gave dave snowden and then i
just talked to him and he told me oh i'm
giving this class if you want to come
you know
join us so
it's it's really nice you meet all these
people that you've heard of or seen
youtube videos off or you know read
papers by and and they're there and you
can just talk to them and everybody is
approachable and really enjoys being
approached and then the lunch break is
considerable i think is it an hour and a
half or an hour it's definitely an hour
and then you sit on the balcony and and
you know that the people walk around and
change tables and so you can talk to to
a lot of people and a nice cross-section
of industries
um obviously this being switzerland we
have a lot of med tech and you know
emerging industries for systems
engineering
and they they all of them have
interesting stories to tell so it's
that's really nice and afterwards we
have this upper row which i
i know we have it at conferences that
run over two days or something you know
we have this icebreaker maybe uh but but
there it's just the the people who don't
want to leave don't leave they stay
there and we we you know we have some
drinks and we talk more and i
i think i normally stay until the last
train home
yeah because you know
you ask some people you want to join us
for dinner and then we have a dinner
downstairs there's a restaurant and
who wants to stay
stays and then yeah we we eat something
and talk
even more about systems engineering but
this is mostly about anecdotes from you
know
from system other system engineering
events so that's it yeah absolutely it's
really nice maybe i should change my
travel plan so i always have to leave in
the evening that at six or seven to
catch the last plane back
so
i have a nice sofas tim yeah i need to
stay and jose is not paying for it
i just wanted to say it's just because
in zurich the hotels are the prices are
enormous
and that's the other thing right
everything is extortionately expensive
in switzerland but as we said isn't
yeah so for the price of the suicide you
get three yogurts in the supermarket
it's not a commercial conference right
it's uh you must cover the costs and
yeah
yes so so we we have sponsors
and obviously we're very grateful to all
the sponsors that we have because
without them we couldn't run it
and they also come as i said they come
from all over the place
and also from from different their
different industries we have kind of
everything
there and the sponsors obviously they
get they get nice visibility so if
anybody out there wants to become our
sponsor this year you know silver
sponsorship only costs a thousand francs
um which is hardly anything in euros
probably a thousand euros now but um
yes so you got really nice visibility
there and and obviously entrance for
some of your people
covered okay
yeah you already mentioned that
uh it's in
zurich at the lake and it's possible to
um join
it virtually again yes how does it work
so how can i join a an in-person
conference virtually
we stream all the presentations so you
you have we have three streams and you
can basically just
log on to the stream and and follow it
but they
everybody remote can also ask questions
um so they will be either unmuted or um
the questions i can't remember how we
did it actually i think some of the
questions were then relayed by a person
at the conference and asked
well that worked really well last time
so
i thought the virtual participants were
even more awake than they didn't have
the wine at lunch right
right
yeah so
maybe some of our listeners are
wondering their selves that
why are you talking about a
swiss engineering conference um and i
think the the answer is that your
conference language is english but why
is a swiss as with
engineering day in english
um
many reasons a as you know switzerland
has four official languages right
so
there isn't the one although it's always
in zurich or always has been in zurich
at least
which is the german-speaking part of
switzerland
you could say it could be also a
german-speaking conference but
the
um
the atmosphere zurich is very
international place as you all know then
as i say we have french italian and i
don't know how we say it in english
so there's another language in
switzerland
um
they're the official languages so
picking one would be wrong you know it's
it's
so picking two french and german also
the italians wouldn't find that funny so
um english is like the uh
yeah the compromise but it's it's more
than that because also all our chapter
work although most of us are german
speakers we we speak english and i think
systems engineering you know lends
itself to speaking in or to discussing
it in english so
a lot of the terms are are
only known in english only exist only
makes sense in english and then in the
other languages you might have some
false friends you know so people don't
understand and you know one of the main
things you have to get right in systems
engineering is your glossary everybody
has to use the same terms with the same
meaning
and that's easier in english so
yes we we speak english at all our
committee meetings so the one we had on
tuesday i think we were only german
speakers native germans and we still
discussed it in english because then you
write them well you write the minutes
you know if you want to write the
minutes of that and then other people we
also have italians we have english
people on the
on the committee um you know then then
you know we then have to translate
everything so it's easier to talk
english
yeah um
well it's in three weeks or so now right
yeah yeah and
they cannot speak us this year now so
who are the keynote speakers yeah oh um
we have lars from daisy last
yeah if you don't know him
so i've i've heard him talk
i don't know how many years ago but he's
already he's been invited back then to
the fusion community and he's yeah he's
he's a wizard on on very in in various
fields and on various topics and he's
going to talk about plm-driven systems
engineering as a service
which you know i'm really much looking
forward to because um as
tim and chris you know i'm half of my
brain is also talking about
organizing information in systems
engineering so i'm really looking
forward to that one and the other one is
also really well known
definitely in the swiss chapter so
alessandro goldka
he's currently working at scaltech in
moscow
and he's going to talk about
accelerating product development um
he's already asking the question it's
the v model still
the answer i think it's called or still
up you know is it still
um up to date or
yeah topical
so
that's going to be more you know the
theoretical i'm guessing but then
knowing him and knowing skull tech um
you know it's probably still very
interesting for all us practitioners as
well so yeah i'm really looking forward
to those too
yeah um
i already had a look in
the agenda and
i saw a very interesting thing you have
a
track called climate and
you tim and marco you have to get also
one session in it so that sounds very
interesting to me to apply systems
engineering to
the climate change and uh
what what can you expect from that
so
the the basic idea is that both tim and
i independently from one another we both
got engaged in you know
not tackling climate change because
obviously that takes a lot but um just
getting getting to start um being part
of a movement or trying to help with our
or bringing our expertise to the various
problems and when you think about
climate change it's it's a very complex
problem
you have obviously the complexity of
weather
or climate right so obviously they're
not the same but it is a complex system
on many levels you have the
system that is the earth and its
atmosphere which is another system or
def you know definitely closely linked
with all these pockets of for example
carbon on earth somewhere hidden some
are melting now so it's it's very
complex um the time aspecting this so
the behavior changes all the time and
all of the problem definitions that you
read as a systems engineer you would
always go oh that's that's a problem
that we would love as systems engineers
that's really our um you know our
realm where we we discuss things
so that's one thing but you also have
the all the social aspects
you know why are there some still some
climate deniers and and how can you
convince them so that's also complex to
understand how you can tackle it on on
this level because you need
like the whole world to come together
and then last not least you have all
these models that try to predict what is
going to happen and then modeling is is
a big part of tim tim's and my work
we love modeling mbse and um
bringing all these things together and
and just discuss it and try to
ignite the systems engineering community
and say look
we can be
if not key but we can definitely
be
an important contribution or make an
important contribution towards tackling
climate change i think that's that's
how the idea was born and
that will be three presentations and a
workshop on climate or related
topics um and yeah it's the first time
we do this in any systems engineering
conference as far as i know
and we hope it catches on and then
that's the systems engineer
engineering community as a whole um gets
engaged and helps the world to tackle
this this amazing problem
yeah that sounds
really interesting
i think it was 10 years ago or so when
the encloses symposium was in the
netherlands um they called
it's a systems engineering for the
planet and so the mission of this
conference and
um
that was very inspiring so it was
it was great and it was one of the first
conferences or in cozy conferences i i
was and uh yeah so
we could definitely do something to
tackle systems uh the climate change so
the assistant engineering discipline is
perfect for that
as well as systems thinking and speaking
of
playbooks there's a playbook the
system's thinking playbook i think
that's the name playbook's
famous name for books but there's also a
book
the systems thinking playbook for
uh climate change or so
yeah there you learn
yeah systems thinking patterns methods
how to apply them to climate change
to better understand the climate change
all right you have to send me the link
it sounds really interesting but we will
do an exercise from this playbook on the
conference oh yeah
sure
great yeah we can we can look it up and
maybe we can link it in the show notes
yeah i have it here somewhere
i don't know
somewhere
too many books on my desktop
i i know that
too many books to read um yeah and i i
recently saw that we have a comment a
live comment here from stephan holt who
makes a great suggestion um he says why
not extending the conference
by something like a bar camp or with
open spaces on the next day
very good idea so what we do have not
this year but we used to have like a
world cafe
which is a bit like that we know we can
discuss ideas
um but extending the conference i think
we like to keep it to the one day but
obviously we wouldn't mind any
satellites so if anybody wanted to
organize a satellite conference
and and just you know it happens to be
the day after
that that would be great so stefan come
forward do it
you can sleep on my couch
how many cultures do you have still the
one tim and stefan i'm sure you don't
mind sharing yes
and then we do an mbs emac camera also
the next day
sure
next year
um
okay so
well
what else do you do
besides
swiss organizations
um
what else do i do so so um i'm a father
of four year olds so i'm trying to teach
them
all
all the technology things um so that
they can take over at some point because
um you know i'm not as young as i sound
um
as a professor i'm i'm teaching systems
engineering and i also run some projects
with the students
and i always use systems engineering for
the project and
i try to link them to some some real
problems in the world that are better
approached with systems engineering so
it's either climate change so this
semester we worked on offshore wind with
a uk startup who put the
um the blades of the turbine basically
on
on the c so they're not standing up
they're like
the the axis is vertical rather than
horizontal so that was really
interesting and
i always try to learn when i teach so
this is kind of my approach and the
other thing we do a lot or i do i'm
involved in a lot is working with
charities in africa
who um
do mobility devices they they make
mobility devices for disadvantaged
children so in sub-saharan africa really
rural
low-income
low-resource
areas
so that's kind of my
it's not a hobby clearly but it is it
feels like a hobby because you know
you're talking a lot to people who try
to do good things and that that's a lot
of fun and then you can bring in some
systems engineering ideas
um my hobby is um as i mentioned before
is trying to bring proper information
management into the systems engineering
world so i think
um systems energy i'm convinced systems
engineering needs really well-structured
information and you know as we have our
experts on system earlier in the room
um and they're working on system l2
who's promising to bring this um into
into the world of our of nbc
you know um i i know that i'm talking to
the right people there so i i really
like to understand what or to build
models that
normal engineers can also understand and
that's like my my hobby
within systems engineering
so you should have joined the system lv2
project that would be great but now we
are
you know finally
almost done almost done um no but what
i've heard about it um it really sounds
like
the ideas i mean to our listeners so
christian tim and i we know each other
from the german chapter and we've come
to the workshop of the german chapter
where we've been discussing this for at
least what seven eight years now
and i think we all had the same
goal at least you know this is where we
need to take mbse
and i'm grateful that you've you've done
it i didn't have the time sorry
no problem
so
yes and part of from that my my favorite
my real favorite hobby is um fisher
technique so i don't know if any
non-germans
don't exist it still exists and my my
kids love it and um we're building
models so i i don't know i have probably
one of the largest collections of visual
technique in
uh in germany and um yes we can build
some really nice models to explain basic
things and that's brilliant and i wanted
to bring it into teaching but it's so
difficult to beat lego um you know
so the the robot called the lego robot i
can't
mind
like
minecraft
yeah
so they they've they're basically you
know they've basically taken over the
university world and although the fisher
dating obviously is a much better system
and the systems engineer should
understand that it is a system whereas
lego is just components who can do
things
but okay
stefan asks if you have the 5000 euros
industry 4.0 factory from visual
technique
no i haven't my dean didn't want to give
it to me
no no no i know in fairness no i didn't
ask for it but i've seen it i've seen
i and i worked with uh
on um digital twins to to connect it to
mbse
and they have all the fish technic kits
for teaching so
i was quite impressed yeah we were
thinking about buying it but then we
stayed also at lego
yeah now 5000 euros is a lot of money
you can buy
five silver sponsorships
yeah that would be
would also be a good thing to do
maybe we should ask fisher dating to do
it and sponsor us in
you know material contributions that's a
good idea
yeah
i'll contact them
all right
so
i would say
we are more or less through um yeah we
now know what is going on in september
in
zurich yeah do do all do come just do
come it's it is the best conference
you know what so i i have vacation in
this time and we still do not book
anything so if we would not book until
then maybe
i will catch the car and
come over
yes plus there's no restrictions in
switzerland or not you know it's it's
not as many as in germany at least
and we've we've all been vaccinated more
or less in switzerland so
um it's a safe place to travel to and
you can see the mountains the glaciers
with the snow
from
um the
lakeside
venue so
it's yeah
it's it's brilliant
um and you have a couch for christian
and i have a couch
not for his dog maybe i'm
no the dog stays at home no we like dogs
actually about it
yes so do come over
[Music]
and let me know and then we can find you
some amazing things to do with a family
uh around lake zurich it's a really nice
destination
all right
yeah so well what's our next topic
christian
yeah um
according to my mind we will talk about
our first uh method and we will talk
about sysmod invented by tim and others
and
yes
so as we have the expert here
we take sysmod as the first method
and
yeah we
like so often don't have a date yet
ah yes but it will print it but it will
come in within the next weeks
yeah
yeah we need time for the date
that's the issue
is there going to be a system 2.0 when
sml changes
uh
yeah probably it's it should be
interesting to see what's what's the
impact of system lb2 on sysmod so
so this is more or less independent of
the language but not 100 percent
independent i would say there's always
an interdependency and a new language
enables new features and
m1 library for sysmod or something like
that
yeah okay let me know i'll join the
podcast yes yeah we will talk about that
and if you need other methodologies i
can you know find your people
and there's a good framework to evaluate
methodologies but that's also a good
okay
all right
we would like to close right christian
okay
can we go on talking but i think after
40 minutes uh some of our
listeners
are also
tired because yeah it was a long day we
have after eight o'clock in the evening
yeah we're already in a row mode
at least here in central europe
then yeah let me say thank you for
inviting me it's been a great pleasure
yeah thank you for joining us
and
hello
the famous last word is christian do not
forget trust us
yes
goodbye
bye
bye thanks