[Music]
so
hello everybody
hello welcome to our third mbse podcast
i'm tim and i'm one of your hosts today
we do an unboxing episode
um it will not be the new iphone but
much better
the brand new system l version two and
well this time we do an english episode
so
let's ask my co-hosts christian why two
german guys
do an english or germish podcast
yeah you know up to now here there are
only a few
uh it's only a few information on sml on
the internet
and besides on some presentations of at
cydowitz and
sandy friedenthal we thought that there
might be a worldwide interest in system
lv2
and we decided to hold the session in
english
okay so we also have some pure nbse
podcast listeners who do not see what we
do
so it should also be understandable
without the video
so do not switch off if you are only
listening to us
however it will be easier to follow us
with the video
um yeah christian can you briefly
explain what we want to talk
about today sure so
first of all we i think we need to
clarify
that all what we are doing today is uh
having a look under the hood
and within these 30 40 minutes which we
have we can't go too much into detail
but we will show you what what's there
what's existing
and you will see much textual language
and it might seem to
some people that susan l2
is getting a programming language with a
textual notation
but the contrary is the truth so um
of course there will be a graphical
notation in near future
but textual notation will be added as a
second view or another view on the model
which
is very precise and
if you know modelica there you can
switch between
graphical and textual notation and it's
very clear to the user
what the system is doing with your
graphical notation that you have modeled
yeah so um
moreover um with a textual notation
we might have the chance to have
something like a let's call it
stateless exchange format um of course
in such a notation there are no user
uuids
and that means a small modeler can't
really decide is this a new modeling
element or was it there before
you pasted something in in an existing
model
but it's better and it should work much
better than the existing xmi schema
so tim what is in this box
yeah so since the latest release that's
uh
20 2010 um the
release is available on on github well
the previous releases were available on
google drive so we
we published a link to a google drive
where you
found a zip file and now everything is
on
on github so let's open the github page
there's a team for the sst who develops
the system lb2 so i share my screen and
you
will shortly seed the github
let's see
well covered here
ah here it is here we have the github
so so 6ml is so big tim has to look
around
yeah so now you should see the the
github
team page of the system submission team
the url is github.com systems
modeling we will also put
this url in our show notes after this
episode
and there are um five
public and one private repositories here
to see so i can see the private
repository because uh i have access
rights to it because i work on that
that's
this isn't a v12v2 transformation
and we make it public as soon as this is
more
major currently it's very draft
so we see different repositories here
and today we would like to un
box the release and we find the release
of course here in the release repository
so let's go
into this one
so you can clone this repository or you
can
download still the zip file that
contains everything you need
and the zip file is here if you scroll
down you find the readme
of this one and there somewhere is the
link
um to the
releases and if you click on the link uh
you come to another page
where you find the zip file of the
latest
release actually there are two zip files
one is the pilot implementation
and the other one is api and services
and today we look on the pilot
implementation
so christian unzip the zip what's in it
yeah let's have a look so let me
share my screen yes i want to
overwrite tim oh
so well prepared
when we unzip this the zip file
we find several
folders and files and all in all it has
around 175 megabytes so a lot of stuff
in it
but let's have a look so first of all we
have a readme file
a readme markdown file so there are
all the instructions how to install and
and what it is
of course there's some licensing
licensing stuff so uh currently
nearly everything is licensed under the
sst member organizations
listed in the documents and the pilot
implementation is especially uh licensed
by model driven solutions so
ed took a lot of work in it he's working
for
and yeah but it is licensed under
creative commons i think
and yeah so you can use it
you can modify it i think
but you can sell it or something like
that
yeah so actually the the pdf is uh
creative common license the other one is
the gru
license oh thank you tim
the legal stuff is sophisticated yes
yeah so what do we have we have a
documentations folder where
you find some documents we will show you
in the next minutes we take a closer
look to them
um but as you can see over a megabyte of
text
uh it's a lot of stuff and we have
all the install files for eclipse and
jupyter jupiter
both parts are pilot implementations uh
in which we will have a look in the next
minutes
um then we have uh yeah some metamodel
stuff here in carmel
as well as in sysml so uh all the
sources
um to the
um to the language and inside the
language
and the source folder you also find many
examples
so there are several examples for
example for example another example
of the vehicle example
which might be
might have get some fame because it's
the example from ads and sandy's
presentations
so far but as you can see there are
several more examples the camera example
which contains some stuff
especially for behavioral modeling
which is coming from cornet block i
think
and many more
so the last folder we did not login
is the ssml library and
this is not filled up very much
up to now but as you can see there is a
folder in it
called geometry and it contains
some basic geometry geometrical geometry
some basic stuff of geometry means
how to um to cover some domain knowledge
regarding cat and how to connect that
so um did i miss something
tim no i think that's it that we
will revisit some of these elements
when we look at the implementation sure
so then tim tell us what's in part one
of these documents
yeah so there are three documents for
the system lv2 specification
and let's have a look at part one
i try to share my screen
so you can see it at least the people
who have video
i must look around my box
yeah part one is the specification of
carmel
and carmel is um so to say the beta
model elect
for system lv2 system everyone is based
on uml and susan lv2 gets a new
complete new brand new beta model
uh so here's you see the the cover page
of this document it's already
more than 200 pages long so and i assume
it will be
much longer uh when it's finalized
and yeah we can jump
to the scope chapter if you open an omg
specification document
the scope chapter at the beginning it's
mostly it's
chapter one it's interesting because
there you
can read what is the scope of this one
and it says uh the karma provides an
application
independent syntax and semantics for
creating more specific
modeling language well so that's the
meter model
the the basis for the system uh v2
and yeah we kind of look uh
into the beta model that's meter models
are sophisticated
stuff so let's look for example
here into the into
section seven three um that's about
types types is a common concept in the
modeling languages
and currently we look on the on the beta
model diagram
for those who cannot see it and we see
the the type for example and
on the right side the feature so simply
set
the the block and the property for
example these are special types or
or features and we can also see a
special thing here that the feature is a
special type
that's that's new in system lv2 uh
we have in system v1 we have types and
we have the features
and in system lb2 a feature can also be
a type itself
that's a little bit weird and
i think it's worth another episode of
this podcast to discuss
that one and maybe one more you also see
here
an element called feature membership
that's
the relationship that a feature is owned
by by a type and we will see these
elements
later again when we look into the the
pilot implementation
um yeah i think that's it so far for
part one
of course there's lots and lots of more
stuff but uh that's out of scope for
this unboxing
so christian what's what is this in part
two and three
yeah let's have a look on my screen
again
and i also prepared um
some why done yeah some
pdfs here and um yeah
part two is about um
the language so it's the omg
systems modeling language version 2.0
specification which is
submitted in response to the rfp
from 2017 and
yeah so let's have a look uh into a
similar section like
tim has shown that so you see this is
also
nearly 400 pages long and
there you can imagine how much work
is in this in this language and in this
specification
and uh yeah so what i wanted to do is
switching with you
to section 7.7
um and maybe i will
find it in a minute so
because um 7.7 is
regarding and
parts is um yeah the concept of parts
was there also
in sesame one but
we have some change we don't have a
block anymore
so the block is called part definition
now in system lv2
which brings us the concept of
definition and usage all across the
language
and you find it also in terms of
attributes in terms of of some behavior
stuff and it's
very similar for all the concepts
and yeah you can see the abstract syntax
now
here in this diagram
which gives you the context between
definition and usage as well how item
definition and part definition is
connected
to definition and how item usage and
part usage is
connected to usage and how those
two sides are acting together it
doesn't look very familiar and
it's fancy stuff behind it but trust me
there were people thinking a lot and uh
there were brilliant minds on
at work um
who decided to get rid of uh
of the uml meta model just because of
those things would not be possible but
they are the foundation for a much
clearer and
more specific and precise language like
system lv2
will be so we could
scroll through the other 384 pages
but then we will have a 24 hour
podcast session so we won't don't want
to bother you with this so that's why we
are
switching to the third document in this
release and the third document
is about the api
and as you can see again the front page
of the api which is in response to
another rfp like we mentioned it in the
last episode of our podcast which came
some months later than the language but
the api
is is
developed together with the language and
the benefits of it we will see in
some minutes so let's switch back to the
chapter
752 of this specification
it is a little bit shorter much shorter
than the language specification
and chapter 7.5 is about
element versioning the api is
offers some services and one of the
services
is element versioning and what i wanted
to show you
now is the abstract syntax
here in chapter 7.5.2
which shows um
a diagram connecting
the project itself so that means
the model um the head or the root
of a model is called project now and the
project contains
several element identities
and an identity can have multiple
versions
as well element version as
also element identity is
called a record and
the last element on this diagram is
commit
which is very yeah let's say git like
that a commit has a change set and a
change set contains
several element versions we will show
you a
pilot pilot implementation where we have
shown
in on the tdse on the german
national symposium in cozy national
symposium
last week where we yeah did a proof of
concept
how well and how easy that is working
so um
so we are through with all the documents
so i would say let's open the install
folder
yeah now the real stuff
so um yeah i take the screen
um and it's
here
so um if you have unzipped
the the release um you find the install
folder and
inside the install folder um are
two subfolders one is for the eclipse
pilot implementation and the other one
is for
jupyter and i open the eclipse one
and inside the eclipse folder you find a
readme file
and the rigby file explains very well
how to install
the system iv2 pilot
and i tried it a few days ago and it
works very well exactly
like it is described in the pdf
before you can start this installation
you need eclipse
it's not described how to install
eclipse but
that is quite easy you can download
eclipse from the eclipse.org website
uh actually you download an installer
then you start the installer and maybe
then it's a tricky part
the installer asks you which edition you
would like to install
i always install the so called eclipse
modeling tools
because we would like to do modeling but
it should also work with one of the
other ones
at least it must include the java
development kit
so once you have installed eclipse you
start with the guideline in
in the readme so i already
did that because that cost a lot of time
downloading installing etc etc
so it's already prepared and i
changed to my eclipse so let's do a new
share
and to the eclipse folder
should be somewhere on my pc
yes
and now you see the eclipse ide
by the way if you are not familiar with
eclipse um
you may be desperate to find the
preference
menu item that is mentioned in the
readme
it's located in the window menu
so maybe you would not expect a
preference
when you item below the windows so there
you find that one
so here you find when you install it you
find three
folders um karma system and the system
library
and as christian already showed you
below the system ad package you find the
examples and training stuff
which is also a huge list of examples
um and you can create your own modeling
projects that is also described in the
pdf how to do that
uh how to create a new project and then
you must
convert it to x text and things like
that that everything is described
very well in the pdf and in the end you
have
an empty projects and i already created
one
called simple system and inside the
project you can create a new file
with the with the
and dot system l and inside the file you
can start
yeah should i say programming system
[Laughter]
so there you find this isn't a code
maybe it's code and how to
do the textual system lv2 syntax is
displayed in one of the pdf
we mentioned before this is my v2
introduction pdf and the doc folder
contains actually a description of the
texture this might be two syntax
so i created here a very simple
model um it's
a part definition so a block and this
might be one
uh called simple system which contains
an attribute
mass of type real and then i create
a part of that type containing
three parts of that type so a very
simple structure so
pata is named my system and it has three
parts p1 2p3 very simple
when i click inside
the yes this is my v2 code
you see in the in the outline view of
eclipse
the the models structure
and there again you find then um
the types of the beta model you saw
before in the
in the pdf for example you find a lot of
feature memberships
so the relationship that relates a
feature
to to the owner in this case here it's
a part definition or a part usage
depending on which level we look into
our file
yeah and for those who would like to see
it graphically
[Music]
it's also possible to do that and the
readme pdf
is described how to install planned uml
so it's a
not a modeling tool i would say it's a
graphical visualizer
for for uml and it's adapted for
system lv2 and if it's installed you can
open
the plant uml view and for that you must
select the the window menu there you
find show views and then you can select
the the planned uml window and
then it shows that it should show
the system lb2 code in a graphical
notation by the way this is not the the
final system lb2 notation
uh it's just a graphical visualization
of this is my v2 code
but it's not not the final one it's the
notation that is
possible to do with planned uml
yeah that's uh quite nice
[Music]
and well i think that's it
so far but there's another this is my v2
pilot implementation
in the install folder and it's uh
based on jupiter and jupiter lab and
christian you know
jupiter much better than me so that's
your part
is it the case that i know it better
than you okay
might be so okay let's switch to the
other
pilot implementation as uh
to mention there is a second one it's
called jupiter lab before it was
a jupiter notebook which is basically
the same thing for
uh for the user and it has
two prerequisites you need java and you
need
some python stuff for example anaconda
and then you will find a batch file or
a shell script for for other platforms
with which is it it is extremely easy to
install
jupyter notebook one trick under windows
is that
you should start it
the command line and the batch file
under administrative privileges
and then it is no problem
so let me share my screen again
okay so what i prepared now is um
i have a cons a command line
window where you just type in jupiter
lab
and it starts it starts a web service
and in a few seconds in my browser there
will be a window
and i will bring that window up
on the screen our
live and video watchers will see
so
whoop it is loading
so that's jupiter lab and we just say we
want to do a new notebook
in the sml language
and now it is preparing a new notebook
in this time i can
copy some of the oh come on
it worked before ah okay it needs some
some time
so there's a there's a lot a lot of
things
loading in the background i guess
and the video encoding for this podcast
needs also some of my cpu
i think it's important to say that it is
only a pilot implementation so it's not
correct
optimized regarding performance and you
user interfaces etc etc only a pilot
implementation
yeah and you can see that on on several
edges
and scratches and so on so
um yeah let's let's continue so i have
my new notebook
and if you know jupyter lab or jupyter
notebook
you can enter some code in
this example we will do
sysml textual notation
and i think it will be ah okay
you might have seen or might have
noticed that everything was black and
white before and now where
the meter model in the background the
syntax was loaded
and we get get some highlighting uh
syntax highlighting here in the code
and what we can do now
is we can use
the show method
maybe okay there it's coming
and if i execute the show command
something in the background is
not working of obviously you need an
argument
so of course you are so right
tim the name of the package for example
exactly
mbse podcast
so it was an oc layer 8 problem
so now there should be
something in the background and i think
it needs some time again
did i misspell something packaged
[Music]
could not resolve reference why not
okay that worked before
what you should have seen now and that's
okay that's live
[Laughter]
what you should have seen now is that
there
will be or should be the same
model structure as you have seen in the
eclipse
environment so what jupiter lab is doing
in the background
is resolving the code resolving the
textual notation and
yeah building up the model and all the
objects
containing also these membership
feature memberships and so on and so
further for you in the background
so um the next command which is
available in
this pilot implementation is the
publish um
command port last
and it works let's have a look if it
works or not
um okay cannot resolve
so do we have
a parenthesis to know
oh you must run the code first
that that is possible yeah
well you are the jupiter expert you
called me the truth
but not me so and then it
is working let's see yeah i wonder
what a wonder yeah so now we have the
model
structure here and you see besides the
code we have typed or
pasted in the import statement is clear
that is the one we we pasted there we
have memberships
and superclassing and what do we have
here feature membership
feature typing subsetting so everything
what was happening
before in in these statements in the
code
is now here in the model structure and
you might notice that there are already
uuids
behind each of these modeling elements
um so that means we
have an instantiation of the objects
in the object model of jupiter lab
and what we can do now is publish
this model to a repository
using the system lv2 api
and this takes some time so this is not
optimized
up to now and even this example or
a very similar example from us um
was around a million lines of json
so it's a lot of stuff what is happening
in the background and this will
truly be optimized and you'll see it's
still processing
to transfer this model
from my computer to
the system lv2 repository which is
hosted by intercax
who do a lot of stuff in this pilot
implementation
of the sysmlv2 api
so but tim what what else can we do with
this repository
yeah so we we can access the repository
um using a browser
that's pretty cool um so i will share my
screen
again and
so
and the url is systemlb2.intercax.com
and then port 9000 slash docs
and then you find the the rest http
binding of the system lv2 api
there will also be an osrc binding be
available
they're currently working on the the
pilot implementation of that one i think
in the next or in the
release after that it will also be
available to the public
but here we have a rest http binding and
we use swagger to to access
uh the methods there so this is already
published
uh yes it was yeah okay okay okay great
so we can uh for example then here uh
uh get the list of all projects um
let's try it out and see if it works
so it's a public server so everyone who
plays around with it published to it you
see a lot of stuff
um so here you see the response
uh picture taken uh here's a one c parts
tree red definition from october 30
again
and so on and at the bottom we should
see
the mbse podcast project published a few
minutes ago
before nbs podcast we see the tdse
that's the project
chris and i published last week for the
conference
and we see an identifier so here's the
unique identifier of the project
and i can copy it because i need that
one
for for another call let's go further
down now can
get the commits of this project
and i need the id
of the project paste and execute
and then i get here the response
the commits there's only one commit
and what i need for to dive
into the model through this api i need
the commit
id so here we see the project id
and the commit id of this commit
and then we can call let's go further
down here
um for example here get the elements by
the project and the commit
or get the root element by project and
commit and so on
so i will call get root elements by
project and commit
because get all elements takes very long
and i tried
it this morning i just crashed the
server
so um i try this one
and again we need the project id
it's still my clipboard and i need the
id of the commit
and it's here
i'll copy paste
and let's see if it works
because it costs some time it's still
loading
well and the response is uh the json
stuff oh he just uh it's very long
and you see a lot of empty fields so
that's what
could be optimized
and somewhere here in all this stuff you
will find the mbse podcast package which
is the root element of our model
um and if i
would have called get all elements then
you will also find
uh the paths and the part definition
element and so on
yeah so but it's nice to play around
with that one
and to see that it works and yeah
christians you already mentioned last
week
we did a very cool demonstration of that
of the api
can you briefly explain it so we have a
few minutes left
sure so um yeah as
we've told you two times already in this
uh session we did a demonstration at the
national symposium in cosi national
symposium in germany
and um yeah we've shown a similar thing
like
we've shown you here we started with um
the eclipse implementation just for our
for viewing
then i've gotten to jupiter notebook
and published a model and
the the thing is that we
thought about yeah just publishing
something to a repository and
viewing it in the repository is not a
big deal
so we decided to write some lines of
code
and we thought how can we interact
with another tool from maybe another
engineering domain
and one of the most common tools
on the world is microsoft excel so
yeah we took a look in
microsoft excel and we found out oh
where microsoft excel
can make rest calls for get calls
and you can also make http post calls in
excel
and so we we made up the um
the story or the um
the use case that someone let's say a
systems engineer
is pushing
is pushing a model into the repository
and another domain engineer
will call this information in his
tooling and
in this in this case the tooling is
excel
so he makes an http get on the
repository
and he changes the information and
writes it back into the repository so we
could do that also live but as tim has
said
this takes a lot of
a lot of time so we took it into a video
and this we will show you now
so i'm jumping a little bit ahead
because this is as i said
um jupiter notebook and uh
eclipse uh yeah and the real interesting
part is
here in the back of the video where we
call the information from the model so
it was a an integer with value 42.
the domain engineer decides oh 42 is not
my number my
number is my favorite number is one two
three four five like all my passwords
and i will have i have here a button
to send this back to the api
and like it was here in
uh in the example we've shown you some
seconds ago
uh before there was just one commit
and now there are
uh after the
publishing of out of excel we call all
the commits again
and we see there are two commits now in
the project
and um yeah we now do look up
one special element which was this
integer value property and
now we find the number one two three
four five
also in the repository yeah and
maybe you might say now oh that's not a
big deal
bringing up some stuff from excel to
to to a repository
but the thing is um i'm not a programmer
so i i know how to use uh some some
programming languages i did it in my
my thesis and and so on so i know how to
program but i'm not a programmer i know
a little bit
how the internet works and
it was possible for me within a few
hours without
programming visual basic before
bringing up this um proof of concept
and that means that it the
maybe the bigger deal than the language
might be
the api because with the api we have
with this proof of concept we have shown
you that
[Music]
how easy it is to integrate different
toolings in a model based
tooling environment and this was not
possible before so you always had these
yeah proprietary integrations and the
truth was that you had
the mbse silo or even a sysml
silo and besides that a
matlab simulink silo and
yeah model exchange and also model
um
what's the word model transformation
was not available or not easy to achieve
and
what we've shown you now is that with
this implementation
even with this early implementation of
the
api it is possible to exchange
models and elements of models so another
use case could be
and i think tim and i will do something
like that in future
um that we run a simulation in let's say
modelica and we get the actual
weight of a composite structure out of
the system model so these use cases are
extremely easy to achieve as you have
seen yeah
so i think we
that was it that was it yeah we unboxed
system lv2
we took three quarters of an hour
um but i hope it was worth it i hope you
are not too
too disappointed uh if you wanted to go
more in detail
but i think as tim already mentioned we
will have
several other podcasts on the language
especially when it gets more mature
and yeah
what did i miss ah yeah if you have
questions
on the pilot implementation there is a
google group
we will put the link also in the
description of
this video and on our website
there you can post questions and uh
ed is very keen on answering them and
all the all the team on the pilot
implementation
yes and yeah
two months what's our next episode
oh yes our next episode it's in uh
less than three weeks it's on december
15th um this time again in german
and we have a guest for the first time
we have christian neurita uh he who is
director of the new research center
josef wrestle center for dependable
system of systems engineering in austria
and yeah i'm very looking forward to
have him here and i'm
also very curious what you say when we
have
a guest here yeah that was it for today
but do not forget trust us
we are systems engineers