Hello, everybody
Hello, welcome to our 3rd MBSE Podcast
I'm Tim, and I'm one of your hosts
Today we do an unboxing episode
It will not be the new iPhone
but much better
The brand new SysML v2
And this time
we do an English episode
Let's ask my co-hosts Christian
"Why two German guys do
an English or Germish podcast?"
You know up to now here
there are only a few
It's only a few information
on SysML on the internet
And besides on some presentations of
Ed Seidewitz and Sandy Friedenthal
we thought that there might be
a worldwide interest in SysML v2
And we decided to hold
the session in English
We also have some pure MBSE Podcast
listeners who do not see what we do
It should also be understandable
without the video
So, do not switch off
if you are only listening to us
However it will be easier
to follow us with the video
Christian, can you briefly explain
what we want to talk about today?
Sure
First of all, I think we need to clarify
that all what we are doing today
It is having a look under the hood
And within these 30, 40
minutes which we have
we can't go too much into detail
But we will show you
what's there, what's existing
You will see much textual language
and it might seem to some people that
SysML 2 is getting a programming
language with a textual notation
But the contrary is the truth
there will be a graphical
notation in near future
But textual notation will be added as a
second view or another view on the model
which is very precise
If you know Modelica
there you can switch between
graphical and textual notation
And it's very clear to the user
what the system is doing
with your graphical notation
that you have modeled
Moreover with a textual notation
we might have the chance to
have something like a let's call it
stateless exchange format
in such a notation
there are no user UUID
And that means a SysML
modeler can't really decide
is this a new modeling element
or was it there before
you pasted something
in an existing model
But it's better and it should work much
better than the existing XMI schema
Tim, what is in this box?
Since the latest release that's 2020
the release is available on GitHub
The previous releases were
available on Google drive
We published a link to a Google drive
here you found a zip file
And now everything is on GitHub
Let's open the GitHub page
There's a team for the SST
who develops the SysML v2
I share my screen and
you will shortly see the GitHub
Let's see
Here it is
We have the GitHub
SysML is so big
Tim has to look around
You should see the Github team page
of the SysML submission team
The URL is
https://github.com/Systems-Modeling
We will also put this URL in
our show notes after this episode
And there are five public and
one private repositories here
I can see the private repository
because I have access rights to it
because I work on that that's
the SysML v1 to v2 transformation
And we make it public as soon as
this is more mature
Currently it's very draft
We see different repositories here
And today we would like
to unbox the release
and we find the release, of course
here in the release repository
Let's go into this one
You can clone this repository or
you can download still the zip file
that contains everything you need
and the zip file is here
if you scroll down
you find the README of this one
and there somewhere is
the link to the releases
And if you click on the link
you come to another page
where you find the zip
file of the latest release
Actually there are two zip files
One is the pilot implementation
And the other one is API & Services
And today we look on
the pilot implementation
Christian, unzip the zip
what's in it?
Let's have a look
Let me share my screen
I want to overwrite Tim
So, well prepared
When we unzip this the zip file
we find several folders and files
And all in all
it has around 175 mega bytes
A lot of stuff in it
But let's have a look
First of all we have a README file
a README markdown file
there are all the instructions
how to install and what it is
Of course, there's some licensing
Licensing stuff so currently nearly
everything is licensed under the
SST member organizations
listed in the documents
And the pilot implementation is especially
licensed by Model Driven Solutions
Ed took a lot of work in it
he's working for Model Driven Solutions
And but it is licensed
under Creative Commons
You can use it
You can modify it I think
But you can't sell it
or something like that
Actually the the PDF is
the Creative Common license
the other one is the GNU license
The legal stuff is sophisticated
What do we have
We have a documentations folder
where you find some documents
We will show you in the next minutes
We take a closer look to them
But as you can see over
a mega byte of text
It's a lot of stuff and
we have all the install files
for Eclipse and Jupyter
Both parts are pilot implementations
in which we will have a look
in the next minutes
Then we have some meta model
stuff here in KerML
as well as in SysML all the sources
to the language and inside the language
and the source folder
you also find many examples
There are several examples
for example of the vehicle example
which might have get some fame
because it's the example from Ed's
and Sandy's presentations
So far but as you can see there are
several more examples the camera example
which contains some stuff
especially for behavioral modeling
which is coming from cornet block
and many more
The last folder we did not
login is the SysML library
And this is not filled up
very much up to now
But as you can see there is
a folder in it called Geometry
and it contains some basic geometry
some basic stuff of geometry means
how to cover some domain knowledge
Regarding CAD and how to connect that
Did I miss something, Tim?
No, I think, that's it that we
will revisit some of these elements
when we look at the implementation
Then Tim, tell us what's in part 1
of these documents
Yeah, there are three documents
for the SysML v2 specification
Let's have a look at part 1
I try to share my screen
You can see it at least the people
who have video
I must look around my box
Part 1 is the specification of KerML
And KerML is, so to say
the meta model elect for SysML v2
SysML v1 is based on UML
and SysML v2 gets a new complete
new brand meta model
Here's you see the the cover page
of this document
It's already more than 200 pages long
I assume it will be much
longer when it's finalized
And we can jump to the scope chapter
if you open an OMG specification document
the scope chapter at the beginning
It's chapter 1
It's interesting because there you
can read what is the scope of this one
And it says
the KerML provides an application
independent syntax and semantics
for creating more specific
modeling language well
That's the meta model
The the basis for the SysML v2
And we look into the meta model
The meta models are
sophisticated stuff
Let's look for an example
Here into the into section 7.3
That's about types
Type is a common
concept in the modeling languages
and currently we look
on the meta model diagram
for those who cannot see it
and we see the type for example
and on the right side the feature
so simply said
the block and the property
for example
these are special types or features
and we can also see a special thing here
that the feature is a special type
That's new in SysML v2
We have in SysML v1
we have types and
we have the features
And in SysML v2 a feature can
also be a type itself
That's a little bit weird
And I think it's worth another episode of
this podcast to discuss that one
And maybe one more
you also see here
an element called feature membership
that's the relationship that
a feature is owned by a type
and we will see these elements later again
when we look into the pilot implementation
I think that's it so far for part 1
Of course
there's lots of more stuff
but that's out of scope for this unboxing
Christian, what is this in part 2 & 3?
Let's have a look on my screen again
And I also prepared some PDFs here
And part 2 is about the language
It's the OMG Systems Modeling
Language version 2.0 specification
which is submitted in
response to the RFP from 2017
Let's have a look into a similar
section like Tim has shown that
You see this is also nearly 400 pages long
and there you can imagine
how much work is in this language
and in this specification
What I wanted to do is
switching with you to section 7.7
And maybe I will find it in a minute
because 7.7 is regarding parts
the concept of parts was
there also in SysML v1
But we have some change
we don't have a block anymore
The block is called
part definition now in SysML v2
which brings us the concept of definition
and usage all across the language
You find it also in terms of attributes
in terms of of some behavior stuff
And it's very similar for all the concepts
and you can see the abstract
syntax here in this diagram
which gives you the context between
definition and usage as well
how item definition and part definition
is connected to definition
and how item usage and part
usage is connected to usage
and how those two sides
are acting together
It doesn't look very familiar
It's fancy stuff behind it
but trust me
There were people thinking a lot
There were brilliant minds on at work
who decided to get rid of SysML
from the UML meta model
just because of those things
would not be possible
but they are the foundation
for a much clearer
And more specific and precise
language like SysML v2 will be
We could scroll through
the other 384 pages
But then we will have
a 24 hour podcast session
We won't don't want to
bother you with this
so that's why we are switching to
the 3rd document in this release
And the 3rd document is about the API
As you can see again
the front page of the API
which is in response to another RFP
like we mentioned it in the
last episode of our podcast
which came some months later
than the language
But the API is developed
together with the language
and the benefits of it
we will see in some minutes
Let's switch back to the chapter
7.5.2 of this specification
It is a little bit shorter much shorter
than the language specification
and chapter 7.5 is
about element versioning
The API is offers some services
And one of the services is
element versioning
and what I wanted to show you now is
the abstract syntax here in chapter 7.5.2
which shows a diagram connecting
the project itself
That means the head or the root of
a model is called project now
and the project contains
several element identities
and an identity can
have multiple versions
as well element version as
also element identity is
called a record
and the last element
on this diagram is commit
which is very git like
that a commit has a change set
and a change set contains
several element versions
we will show you
a pilot-pilot implementation
where we have shown
in the TdSE on the Germany
an national symposium in INCOSE
national symposium last week
where we did a proof of concept
how well and how easy that is working
We are through with all the documents
I would say let's open the install folder
Now the real stuff
I take the screen
And it's here
If you have unzipped the release
you find the install folder
and inside the install
folder are two subfolders
One is for the Eclipse
pilot implementation
and the other one is for Jupyter
And I open the Eclipse one
And inside the Eclipse folder
you find a README file
and the README file explains very well
how to install the SysML v2 pilot
and I tried it a few days ago
and it works very well exactly
like it is described in the PDF
before you can start this installation
you need Eclipse
It's not described how to install Eclipse
But that is quite easy
You can download Eclipse
from the eclipse.org website
Actually you download an installer
Then you start the installer and
maybe then it's a tricky part
The installer asks you which
edition you would like to install
I always install the
Eclipse Modeling Tools
because we would like to do modeling
but it should also work with
one of the other ones
at least it must include
the Java Development Kit
Once you have installed Eclipse
you start with the guideline in the README
I already did that because that cost a
lot of time downloading installing etc.
It's already prepared and
I changed to my Eclipse
Let's do a new share
and to the Eclipse folder
should be somewhere on my PC
Yes, it is
And now you see the Eclipse IDE
By the way, if you are
not familiar with Eclipse
you may be desperate to
find the preference menu item
that is mentioned in the README
It's located in the window menu
Maybe you would not expect a preference
when you item below the windows
so there you find that one
Here you find when you install it
you find three folders
kerml, sysml, and the sysml library
and as Christian already showed you
below the sysml package
you find the examples and training stuff
which is also a huge list of examples
And you can create your own modeling
that is also described in
the PDF how to do that
how to create a new project
and then you must convert it to Xtext
and things like that
that everything is described
very well in the PDF
and in the end you have an empty projects
and I already created one
called simple system
and inside the project
you can create a new file
and *.sysml and inside the file
you can start
And should I say "programming SysML"?
There you find the SysML code?
Maybe it's code
And how to do the textual SysML v2
syntax is displayed in one of the PDF
we mentioned before this is
SysML v2 introduction PDF
And the doc folder
contains actually a description
of the texture of SysML v2 sysntax
I created here a very simple model
It's a part definition
a block of SysML v1
and called simple system
which contains an attribute
mass of type Real
and then I create a part of that type
containing three parts of that type
A very simple structure
A part is named my system and it has
three parts p1, p2, p3 very simple
when I click inside
The SysMLv2 code
You see in the in the
outline view of Eclipse
the the models structure
And there again you find then
the types of the meta model
you saw before in the PDF
for example you find a lot
of feature memberships
The relationship that relates a feature
to the owner in this case here
it's a part definition or a part usage
depending on which level
we look into our file
and for those who would like to
see it graphically
It's also possible to do that
and the README PDF is described
how to install PlantUML
It's not a modeling tool
I would say it's a graphical
visualizer for UML
and it's adapted for SysML v2
and if it's installed
you can open the PlantUML view
And for that you must
select the window menu
there you find show views and then
you can select the the PlantUML window
And then it should show the SysML v2
code in a graphical notation
By the way, this is not the
final SysML v2 notation
It's just a graphical visualization
of this SysML v2 code
But it's not the final one
It's the notation that is possible
to do with PlantUML
That's quite nice
And well I think that's it
So far but there's another SysML pilot
implementation in the install folder
And it's based on Jupyter
and JupyterLab
Christian, you know Jupyter
much better than me
So, that's your part
Is it the case that I know
it better than you?
Might be so, okay
Let's switch to the other
pilot implementation
as Tim mentioned
there is a second one
It's called JupyterLab
before it was a Jupyter Notebook
which is basically the same thing for user
It has two prerequisites
You need Java and
you need some python stuff
for example Anaconda
And then you will find a batch file
or a shell script for other platforms
with which is it it is extremely
easy to install Jupyter Notebook
One trick under windows is that
you should start it
the command line and the batch file
under administrative privileges
And then it is no problem
Let me share my screen again
What I prepared now is
I have a console, a command line window
where you just type in "jupiter lab"
And it starts a web service
And in a few seconds in my browser
there will be a window
And I will bring that window up
on the screen our live
And video watchers will see
It is loading
That's JupyterLab
And we just say we want to do
a new notebook in the SysML language
It is preparing a new notebook
In this time I can copy some of the...
Oh, come on
It worked before
Okay, it needs some time
There's a lot of things loading
in the background, I guess
and the video encoding for this
podcast needs also some of my CPU
I think it's important to say that
it is only a pilot implementation
It is not optimized regarding
performance and user interfaces etc.
only a pilot implementation
You can see that on several edges
and scratches and so on so
Let's continue
I have my new notebook
And if you know JupyterLab
or Jupyter Notebook
You can enter some
code in this example
We will do SysML textual notation
And I think it will be okay
You might have seen
or might have noticed
that everything was
black and white before
and now where the meta model
in the background the syntax was loaded
And we get some highlighting
syntax highlighting here in the code
And what we can do now is
we can use the show method
Maybe okay, there it's coming
And if I execute the show command
something in the background
is not working obviously
You need an argument
to show "MBSEPodcast"
Of course, you are so right, Tim
The name of the package for example
Exactly, "MBSEPodcast"
There should be something
in the background
And I think it needs some time again
Did I misspell something packaged?
Could not resolve reference, why not?
Okay, that worked before
what you should have seen now
and that's okay, that's live
What you should have
seen now is that there
will be or should be
the same model structure
as you have seen in
the Eclipse environment
What JupyterLab is doing in the
background is resolving the code
resolving the textual notation
and building up the model
and all the objects
containing also these membership
feature memberships and so on
and further for you in the background
so the next command which is available
in this pilot implementation is the
publish command MBSE Podcast
Let's have a look if it works or not
Okay, cannot resolve
Do we have a parenthesis to know?
You must run the code first
That is possible
You are the Jupyter expert
You told me the truth but not me
so and then it is working
Let's see I wonder what a wonder
We have the model structure here
and you see besides the code
we have typed or pasted in
The import statement is clear
that is the one we pasted there
we have memberships and superclassing
and what we have here feature
membership, feature typing, subsetting
so everything what was happening before in
these statements in the code
is now here in the model structure
And you might notice that
there are already UUIDs
behind each of these modeling elements
That means we have an
instantiation of the objects
in the object model of JupyterLab
and what we can do now is publish
this model to a repository
using the SysML v2 API
And this takes some time
This is not optimized
up to now and even this example or
a very similar example from us
was around a million lines of JSON
It's a lot of stuff what is
happening in the background
and this will truly be optimized
and you'll see it's still processing
to transfer this model from my
computer to the SysML v2 repository
which is hosted by Intercax
who do a lot of stuff in this pilot
implementation of the SysML v2 API
But Tim, what else can we
do with this repository?
Yeah, we can access the
repository using a browser
That's pretty cool
I will share my screen again
And the URL is
http://sysml2.intercax.com:9000/docs
And then you find the the REST/HTTP
binding of the SysML v2 API
There will also be an OSLC
binding be available
They're currently working on the the
pilot implementation of that one
In the next or in the release after that
it will also be available to the public
But here we have
a REST/HTTP binding
and we use Swagger
to to access the methods
This is already published?
Yes, it was
It's there?
Okay, great
We can, for example then here
get the list of all projects
Let's try it out and see if it works
It's a public server
Everyone who plays around
with it published to it
You see a lot of stuff
Here you see the response
Picture taken
here is "1c-Parts"
"Tree Redefinition" from
October 30th, and so on
At the bottom we should see
the "MBSEPodcast" project
published a few minutes ago
Before MBSE Podcast
we see the TdSE
that's the project Christian and I
published last week for the conference
And we see an identifier
Here's the unique
identifier of the project
And I can copy it because I need that one
For another call
let's go further down
Now I can get the commits of this project
And I need the ID of the project
paste and execute
And then I get here the response
the commits there's only one commit
And what I need for to dive
into the model through this API
I need the commit ID
Here we see the project ID
and the commit ID of this commit
And then we can call
Let's go further down here
For example, here get the elements
by the project and the commit
or get the root element by project
and commit and so on
I will call get root elements by
project and commit
because get all elements takes
very long and I tried
It this morning, I just crashed the server
I try this one and again
we need the project ID
It's still my clipboard
and I need the ID of the commit
And it's here
I'll copy paste
And let's see if it works
because it costs some time
It's still loading
The response is the JSON stuff
It's very long
And you see a lot of empty fields
that's what could be optimized
And somewhere here in all this stuff
you will find the "MBSEPodcast" package
which is the root element of our model
And if I would have called
get all elements
then you will also find the parts
and the part definition element and so on
But it's nice to play around with that one
And to see that it works
Christians, do you already
mentioned last week?
We did a very cool
demonstration of that of the API
Can you briefly explain it?
We have a few minutes left
Sure
We've told you two times
already in this session
We did a demonstration
at the national symposium
INCOSE national
symposium in Germany
And we've shown a similar thing
like we've shown you here
We started with um the Eclipse
implementation just for our for viewing
Then I've gotten to Jupyter Notebook
and published a model
and the the thing is
that we thought about just publishing
something to a repository
and viewing it in the repository
It's not a big deal
We decided to write some lines of code
And we thought how can
we interact with another tool
from maybe another
engineering domain
And one of the most common tools
on the world is Microsoft Excel
We took a look in Microsoft Excel
and we found out where Microsoft Excel
can make REST calls for get calls
and you can also make
HTTP post calls in Excel
And we made up
the story or the use case
that a systems engineer is pushing
a model into the repository
And another domain engineer will call
this information in his tooling
an in this in this case
the tooling is Excel
He makes an HTTP get on the repository
And he changes the information
and writes it back into the repository
We could do that also live
But as Tim has said
This takes a lot of time
So, we took it into a video
and this we will show you now
I'm jumping a little bit ahead
because this is as I said
Jupyter Notebook and Eclipse
And the real interesting part is
here in the back of the video
where we call the
information from the model
It was a an integer with value 42
The domain engineer decides
"Oh, 42 is not my number"
"My favorite number is 12345
like all my passwords"
And I have here a button
to send this back to the API
and like it was here in the example
we've shown you some seconds ago
Before there was just one commit
and now there are after
the publishing of out of Excel
We call all the commits again
and we see there are
two commits now in the project
and we now do look up
one special element
which was this integer value property
and now we find the number 12345
also in the repository
And maybe you might say now
That's not a big deal bringing up
some stuff from Excel to a repository
But the thing is
I'm not a programmer
I know how to use some
programming languages
I did it in my thesis and and so on
I know how to program
but I'm not a programmer
I know a little bit how the internet works
and it was possible for me
within a few hours
without programming
Visual Basic before
bringing up this proof of concept
and that means that
it the maybe the bigger deal
than the language might be the API
because with the API
we have with this proof of concept
we have shown you that
how easy it is to integrate
different tooling
in a model based
tooling environment
and this was not
possible before
You always had these
proprietary integrations
And the truth was that you had
the "MBSE silo" or even a "SysML silo"
and besides a
"MATLAB Simulink silo"
and model exchange and also model
What's the word?
"Model Transformation"
was not available
or not easy to achieve
And what we've shown
you now is that
with this implementation
even with this early
implementation of the API
It is possible to exchange models
and elements of models
another use case could be
And I think Tim and I will do
something like that in future
that we run a simulation
in let's say Modelica
and we get the actual weight
of a composite structure
out of the system model
these use cases are extremely easy
to achieve as you have seen
I think that was it
We unboxed SysML v2
We took three quarters of an hour
But I hope it was worth
I hope you are not too disappointed
if you wanted to go more in detail
But I think as Tim
already mentioned
we will have several other
podcasts on the language
especially when it gets more mature
What did i miss?
Ah, yeah
If you have questions on
the pilot implementation
there is a Google Group
We will put the link
also in the description
of this video
and on our website
There you can post questions
And Ed is very keen on answering them
and all the team on
the pilot implementation
What's our next episode?
Our next episode
It's in less than three weeks
It's on December 15th
This time again in German
And we have a guest for the first time
We have Christian Neureiter, who is
director of the new research center
Josef Ressel Center for "Dependable
System-of-Systems Engineering" in Austria
And I'm very looking
forward to have him here
And I'm also very curious what
you say when we have a guest
That was it for today
But do not forget
Trust us
We are systems engineers