okay so hello welcome
to a new episode of our mbse podcast
uh today we start our new series mbse in
the field and take a look
at how mbse is used in practice
our guest is from the company vender
lender
and well although you may have never
heard of the company
you have mostly likely worked with the
system either directly
or indirectly among other things
wonderland develops baggage handling
systems
for airports so and we are pleased to
have fatih akan
as our guest today and fatih please
introduce yourself
hi tim christian thanks for having me in
this uh
amazing nbsc podcast first of all
um my name is fatih arkhan
i work in architecture and strategy team
in bundo london
we are as a team defining the reference
architectures
and the design methods and the
guidelines for all of our business
segments
you can generalize our domain as
material handling systems in waldoland
recording in progress but also the the
warehousing
domain and the past domain
we delivered solutions to to our
customers which
are like hong kong airports heathrow
airports orlando amsterdam
istanbul airport amazon lidl
fedex ups dhl are also our customers
from warehousing and parcel business
so we are global leader in airports but
also a key player
in these other businesses
um i started to work for one london in
as a solution architect in
airports business segment
and then we i also moved to this
new role last year
my bachelor and master degree is in
embedded software
and hardware engineering that was the
first five years of
my 15 years of engineering story and
later on i became a systems engineer in
the air defense and weapon systems
and in 2017 after
doing this weapon systems engineering
for
six years i moved to netherlands to work
for vandal under and
for the last four years basically i'm
i'm i'm doing this systems architecting
both for the projects
and also for the technology rnd side of
development
okay very cool cool experience
a good good kickstart for mbse
so could you give us a brief
motivation what was the
yeah the beginning of the journey the
nbc journey at vanderland and
when did it start how did it start
well i need to take it all the way from
the beginning
the foundation of the company is going
and you might imagine the evolution of
the design was bottom-up like in other
words it was from mechanical to
electro-mechanical the
electro-mechanical to
embedded software first and then to
application software
and somewhere around 2000 2005 the
complexity became higher
and basically becomes a complex system
and then at that time the company
already started to invest on
having a stable requirements management
environment configuration management
change management
it was not just the military standards
like ocd sss ssd
but we also started to see some visual
drawings
which which was explaining the material
flow of diagrams which is really
critical in the logistic domain so all
of these things
try to be taken out of control in a in
a stable configuration management but
you can imagine
when when the systems are getting more
complex
and you can lose the traceability easily
and at the same time we were
forcing our um internal design to be
more platform-based like
creating reusable assets that that each
project can
can reuse what we are building and this
brings extra complexity
and somewhere in 2005 2010 we already
started to see that
it's it's getting more difficult to to
make
a reliable change impact analysis on the
things which are changing in your
technology domain on the customer's side
and that's why even actually before me
starting to work for this mbsc all the
way back in 2010
we started to see some uml models
appearing especially in the software
environment but
you can imagine the uml models are also
used to explain system level things
and at that time bond london was working
with ibm in certain projects so
that's why ibm rational draws what was
they appearing at that time
so when i look at the history i can
still see these type of models
in 2010 by the way 2010 they used
russian roles for indian projects
yeah there was again 2010 was still
a little bit influencing relationship
between ibm and wonderland
at that moment later on monday are
influenced by this and i started to
when i started to investigate backwards
i think 2013 is the year when i have
seen some
reference models appearing so some
people
already the people who are ready to
embrace the complexity and try to solve
it
started to create some uml models which
are really
depicting what we have
i even seen in 2015-16 when you look at
again the repositories create created
before you can even see some
automated interface creations like xst
files coming from these uml models
it was getting more and more
professional i should say
really more executable model instead of
just
knowledge gathering and sharing
but in all of these stories
there is there was a missing piece which
is a framework so
there was not a single way of creating
models
the modeling languages were not that
much
structured so there are several ways to
model with uml and csml
as you know so i tried to put this
missing piece into puzzle by trying to
create a framework and also a way of
working and the other missing piece
was basically uh
the models were never at the base so
they were always the supporting artifact
of the
of the main channel which is
documentation and that's why
we not just uh people before me but
it's always a common pattern that you
give up maintain the models if it's not
at the base of your thing
so that was also the missing piece in
the puzzle so
we were not i think one london was not
putting models at the base of the
of of the of the development of the
configuration management and etc so
these are basically the things i i put
on the frame
did you join wonderland to to create
this missing piece
was this that your first task the mbse
journey
well that was that that
uh that would be a different way but i
think
it was part of the story i was having
from
defense which you might imagine putting
a good foundation on your
systems engineering and model based
approach that's what
i have learned in my ex-employment in
turkey
and there was a certain reason i think i
started to work
here also they they need a structure
on the systems engineering not from the
documentation perspective also on the
model
based so i have been asked to
investigate this as a site task
i was doing the airports projects
like hong kong but at the same time
i was i was trying to understand how we
can move
the complete apos design from document
based model based
and i i was basically taking this as a
kind of side track but
later on it became an official task for
me
and in the beginning i was trying to
apply this only for airports platform
airport platform business and then
airport platform and the business models
and then i was asked to apply this to
the whole business segments
try to create a framework applicable to
everything we do
as one london
okay and when you are talking about
foundation
and platforms what do you mean by that
well you can accept the
mbsc foundation as a light definition
for
the framework actually because when you
say that
hey i'm defining a framework for you it
can
create a heavy feeling on the other side
we call it mbsc foundation
so that's basically what we are trying
to create and
this framework is just having a meta
model
to explain people not just the content
but
the main structure of the models so a
kind of conformance guideline
also the way of working this is
basically what the mbsc foundation is
about
and the platform so
these are different things right the
mbse foundation is more the
the methodology and the platform is
your product itself right yeah the
platform is is
you can accept platform as a system with
its
own architecture and product line so it
is
similar to product design not completely
but
because it is a system architecture and
we
platforms are basically not necessarily
they don't need to be model based of
course our platforms are just reusable
asset repositories
in each business segment so that each
project can be instantiated from this
reusable asset repository you don't need
to
start from scratch all of your
functional decomposition structural
decomposition
you just need to pick what you need we
are nowadays calling
configure to order business instead of
engineer to order
so that's what the platforms are about
so that means you have this platform
approach really from
the requirements or at least from a
functional
layer uh throughout your bombs in the
end
yes that's true that's foreign
technology environment like you are
trying to generalize
requirements or features which can cover
the market
and then your reusable asset repository
should be covering as much as possible
so that
you don't need to reinvent things for
each customer specific things
well how does it work well
that's that's a dream for many
organizations to have something like
that a
working product line in the mbse
environment so
how does it work indeed it's
very challenging and i would be really
happy when it really works
we are really working hard to make it
work
and having a platform in its own
environment is a challenging task but
applying an mbac to this which is
actually our topic today is an extra
challenge because from what i
what i've learned before and what i'm
studying and also applying
doing mbs for a project can be a little
bit better like focusing on a certain
customer requirement and applying
this decomposition according to the
needs is fine but when you try to apply
it for
platforms you need to create a reusable
asset repository for your models
so that so that each project can reuse
your your platform models
what what we are working on nowadays
is to to define
the core parts which is not changing per
project
and the variable part explicitly so that
you can at least work on work on the
variety model in a different way than
the core modeling so core modeling can
still work
with main artifacts which is a little
bit a little bit more straightforward i
should say when it comes to the right
model
you need to do different stuff but also
we are trying to simplify things for
projects
such as if you have a model for your
uh core part and even for the variant
part which is
not specified for customers so you have
it already
you don't need to ask your projects to
to be dealt with models
they just need to configure what you
have but at least they can focus on the
customer specific part so
they can spend their time to create
models for customer specific parts
but to be ready applying this we we try
to
introduce a data connection from the
models to a web-based application like
you can
use the data of the model instead of
trying to
understand the models which you already
have in your product line
because the models for the platform is
only for the product line
and that's a communication pattern as a
communication channel you need to do in
your development
environment but when it comes to deploy
some customer solution
you don't need to expose your models to
the customer environment that's
basically
one of the most important stuff we are
trying to implement
um for for the for the other
for for the other aspect of it um
so we want solution teams to spend more
time on the customer specific part but
that means we have a big task in the rnd
environment to really make
the change impact analysis consistent
and also the models which are being
created by different teams are not
looking very different from each other
that's where that's where this
meta model comes into place in other
words metamodels should also show
your core and their right parts
separated from each other
that's that's basically um that's
basically what we are
spending time on to to really apply
product line engineering on an mbsc
environment
um maybe for this one tim
maybe make it more tangible i can i can
show the platform and the project
connection a little bit better to you
by some by some slides if you like
yeah that's a good idea but please
explain the slice so that
our pure audio listeners also understand
it
that would be great
i hope it's visible it is
yeah so
the platform is basically
as you can see at the bottom of our
picture it's a kind of
reusable asset repository again which
can be
instantiated for different customer
projects
and as you can see in the middle of
picture we have
a reality which is a kind of airports
this is the heathrow project at the back
end and on top of it you see the
customer solution model
that's really what you are deploying
but this this model of course does not
mean too much
for the stakeholders if not if you are
not creating views
and you need to be able to create
different views and these different
views
as you can imagine in the in for
instance csm like csml pillars like you
have a
behavior view you have a structure
you might have also customer specific
views like the layout like our 3d
environment involved which is very
important how the
how the mechanical equipment is really
fitting into building that you need to
show
so if you speak about models you do not
only mean system
models mbs e-modules in general so
including
cat models and whatever models okay
well you see you see in the in this
diagonal
you see the the software structure and
the function capabilities we've already
you can cover them easily with the very
well known aspects of csml and uml
when it comes to this logistic view for
instance like the material flow diagram
you might need to switch to domain
specific languages which we are for
instance looking at
and as you mentioned when it comes to
mechanical it's the cad model
but this this weave is also interesting
if you look at the right hand side
you see a configuration view point
that's basically how we want to set so
if you can emit the data
of your configurability in a certain way
in a customer meeting
what we are saying this is a configure
to order business that's that's how you
can execute
this platform model for a certain
customer starting from sales
till the end of deployment that's what
we are also trying to put in the context
and the other wheel you see on the left
is the documentation
so it's always the topic in mbse are you
able to create documents out of
models that's what we want to do if it's
if it's hundred percent
uh coming from what you have done before
you should be writing the text again and
again
that's what basically we are saying so
this is all in this
image in a nutshell same system
mean different things for different
stakeholders and you need to really
understand all these views by
communicating with your stakeholders
that's what we are doing
furthermore you haven't seen the meta
model in this discussion yet because
your meta model should be aiming
different businesses so in this slide
you see a platform model warehousing
platform model and the parcel platform
model
to we are aiming these things to work in
the same way
at least on the model-based environment
that's why
you need to be able to create a common
guideline
at the bottom that's showing the
relationship between each classes
each blocks so what type of
things you can have in this model i
think the theoretical definition for
this is taxonomy of your model
and a part of its ontology so we are
trying to
merge this theoretical discussions like
metamodel ontology and taxonomy in a
single thing called metamodel
and we even call it mbsc foundation to
make it even simpler for
the company so that's what you see on
these slides
okay uh yeah if i look at this that's
for example for for the airport it looks
like
in the center you show a solution model
and around i can see the different views
like the layout view of the airport
or the software view or the functional
views and so on
but in the middle the solution model is
physically these are several models
right
it's it's a cat model and it's a system
model and so on
uh so logical it's a single solution
model but physically you have
several models exactly how do you
connect these
models well that's one of the big
challenges today
yeah for many companies how to connect
different models so this model
interoperability how does it work
well in our case
a little bit i think we can
we will talk about more details on the
tool suite challenges i guess here but
yet at least the interoperability now
we're not that much
in good shape yet so we are still
using our existing tools like sparks
enterprise architect
we are using csml and the magic grid
framework which explains
how you should make this metamodel but
when it comes to really realize it
with this interoperability we are
hitting the boundaries of our existing
ict architecture in this story of course
we are working on some gateways like
showing the proof of concepts
like trying to connect at least requires
management to
to to the modeling environment to really
be able to create documents
automatically
maybe some some synchronization between
these environments
when it comes to cad models and etc we
need to think
within the platform world and good bits
because as i said we have some domain
specific languages already in place
it's really difficult to call them
officially the dsls but
as an organization you already have them
so there are rules
in these mechanical models we are we are
now
for instance running a project with tno
esi here in netherlands just to focus on
the relationship between these models
and the plm environment product line
management like in innovia
and in our layout environment for
instance
the transformations i think we
we will be creating some gateways but at
the same time while
showing the necessities of this stuff
with with the ict people in our company
we are looking for different two suites
which are really showing these
dependencies immediately like
synchronized way
but for now our transformations are
really
um we are still too much
optimizing the well-known
model artifacts like the functions and
structural view
the challenge is a little bit the
configurations view but we are still
modeling this in the sparks enterprise
architect so in a nutshell
still the models are in a kind of
single tool island but we are trying to
connect them to the others as much as
possible that's what we are working on
okay and then imagine that you are also
doing
model based product line engineering
um which is a challenging thing for
itself
so what kind of technologies do you use
in this direction
yeah let me stop sharing and then
this this product line engineering
we we can call our platforms as a
product line engineering plus more
so it's not completely a product line
because we are not just selling
single products they are really working
together there is an architecture and
etc
and meaning that we have a bigger
challenge but at least just for this
product line part
for the variety management we
we started to investigate some
extensions to the existing csml
as i said we are using xml mostly 1.55
waiting for 2.0 to be also
more solidified because i know very well
the right
management is more explicit there what
we are trying
what we are trying to do is looking at
some
existing extensions like vamos for
instance from them
try to apply it in our project
but at the same time we have been
realizing
the variety trees are not that much
difficult to model even with the
existing xml blocks
but when it comes to model
the constraints the rules
and to really execute them for
verification validation and for
sending purposes or your product line
we have a challenge there that's where
we are looking at
for some transformation like maybe
modeling the rules
in a little bit more domain specific
language environment
where we can make some xml connection
between the sparks environment and
the other rule based
modeling environment so that's that's
basically
uh one of the things
we are doing the pure variance
we are looking we are also looking at
this orthogonal variety
modeling is another
method from vm
so all of all of these things are in our
concentration that's a very
good good moment to speak about this
because we are really running this
project with tn or esi right now
and i think at the end of this project
somewhere in june
we are finishing it in july or august
you might see an article coming from our
side on our learnings on this variety
modeling
moving the how it will it can be applied
in an automated logistics domain
so that will be writing the title of the
article
oh cool it reminds me that we have to
have two more episodes one on vamos and
one we have to invite danilo boyce from
pure systems
will be interesting also and i i've
currently a project where we combine
both
which are perfectly fits together
with farmers you can model variability
and you can model the the features and
the feature constraints now if you
select this feature you must also
select that one etc but you can also
extract the feature modeling to appear
variants
which makes sense if it's not only about
system l
the feature model should also impact
other models not only the system model
oh yeah
but the modeling of the variability in
the system um
can still be done with uh with the
vehemence approach
the dsl discussions a little bit we have
some complexities like
very very complicated rules just
sometimes need some dsl extension that's
also
a very interesting learning for us on
the way
yeah okay so
well yeah you do a lot of sophisticated
mbse stuff i would say
so and what do you think are
the main organizational challenges in
adapting mbsc so one part is the
technical challenges but what are about
the organizational challenges yeah
that's the
that's the bitter sweet part
of the meal now so acceptance and
ownership
that might sound cliche i think i see
this answer as a copy paste
in many contexts especially if you're
trying to embed this
on a wider scope and if you have someone
it's possible to do that
i think that's that's still the biggest
challenge um i need to maybe
i need to go back to what i did before
like as i explained in airports i tried
to do that
as a side track and i was trying to use
it in the project and showing the value
immediately
at the same time having meetings with
with many stakeholders and
i i was not the domain senior
meaning that i was i need i needed to
find senior architects
knowing the domain also can understand
what ccmet and uml means i should say
and and not running away when i call
something called metamodel
if it's too theoretical let's say and
also some executive leaders of course
you need to find
some some budget owners some sponsors i
was mostly aiming
that part saying that if i if i had
these green lights
then we can go but i think that was not
the
whole story so acceptance and ownership
is really running in the teams
so you cannot really understand your
acceptance and ownership by just looking
at the organizational chart so you need
to look at
who is struggling about this document
creation who is struggling about
doing some certain stuff and maybe they
don't need model they need something
else and
you really need to hear these stories
first to understand
the level of details in your models
but also they need to be involved from
day one
i mean if you go there with the complete
story
there's not much room for improvement
and you're just staying with your great
models i mean
it's really like the ivory tower
behavior happening also on the nbsc
that's not only for nbc you can imagine
in all kinds of transformation and what
i did now for instance in this new task
i tried to get all stakeholders involved
as much as possible from day one so that
they can define the metamodel
so it's a kind of language you need to
create all together so everyone needs to
understand the same thing
from a function and the function can be
written in
100 different ways in all systems
engineering books
even in csml you can say i have a
function but there is a property which
makes it non-functional you
you really need to align on this stuff
from day one so that they can feel that
that's also their
own thing so that they can all so that's
basically
would be my message to everyone when it
comes to
they face the same challenge on
acceptance and ownership
all right so one
question so that uh do you translate
your your meta model or your
your language your mbse language into
the models meaning that you
do not use for the system l term for
example activity
but instead use your term for that and
uh by using
stereotypes and name it and function or
whatever yeah
that's where this story went a little
bit theoretical for our team but thanks
for asking
because actually that's what we are
doing
so we are somehow tuning some names like
you know we don't call it uh
a function but we call the capability so
that's
so that that's that's maybe more
resonating with the company but when it
comes to
certain diagram artifacts we are not
hiding the fact that we are using use
case modeling
they are use cases
but people are just understanding hey we
have a capability model here
so they don't need to understand what
the use case is
but it's not a very formal method model
meaning that
there is another toolbox that you can
drag and drop different
artifacts like a profile it's not there
yet
although i'm thinking about it how
we are deploying this method model now
is just a little bit knowledge model
i should say and then we are creating
the platform models for each business
segment
that they look exactly the same how the
metamodel looks like
they have the same relationship between
all of their packages and classes and
even views
and then they can always look back how
the metamodel looks like
but the relationship between these
elements are not
automatically transferred to each other
but in time after a while after a solid
metamodel team we are planning to
create a verification template like you
can
compile your platform model saying that
okay you are still in the meta model
or you have some relationship which
doesn't make sense for the metamodel
that's also what i plan to do in future
okay
cool yeah but i'm still interested in
those
acceptance and ownership things i i
guess this is much
more the problem than finding the right
tool chain or something like that
yeah that's true i mean there is
one trap for instance we have found
ourselves recently
it was a little bit similar question and
answer that just happened between team
and me so when you
when you when you are really enjoying
modeling when you are enjoying when you
know the mbscs similar
uml that can also stay very theoretical
for
the organization you can say hey we have
a nice language here
we created this meta model together
but you should be able to create very
quick proof of concepts
like really maybe documented as part of
the baseline
or creating some software for them they
can drag and drop
a block and the interface is
automatically appearing
so if you are not able to show this very
quickly
you can also find a trap find yourself
in the trap that i have found so
i i've heard a lot of criticism for
instance like it's too theoretical so
we need a phd to understand this abs
influence these type of things are also
something that's right now happening for
instance that's
why we started to deploy some proof of
concepts very quickly so
i already started to see some teams are
taking it
as as part of their daily job
so we have some acceptance but the
ownership is also like
the validation of the systems you need
to wait one year to see that they are
really maintained
so i think maybe
in another episode after a year we can
close the loop saying that hey
the ownership is there but i'm still
hopeful that that
that we will really uh overcome this
acceptance of ownership
challenge
uh i think the well another part side of
the coin
of acceptance is the right tool
um you could have a very good
methodology and concepts etc etc but if
you don't have
the tool then it does not work in
practice or it's not
not very effective to do that so um and
you mentioned that this
is another organizational challenge so
what what exactly do you mean
by that challenge in your context
actually it's the kind of cliche from
time to time when you say hey the right
tool suites are
very important because i've been hearing
more and more
hey the tools are coming later first
define your
methodology define what you need but
especially looking at
my previous answer like you need to be
able to show the proof of concept as
quick as possible to be able to do that
you need to write connection with your
existing structure
the reason why i'm saying the existing
structure
if you are not creating systems
engineering as a green field
in your company if you have something
already in place
probably you have systems engineers who
know
how things work they know how doors
can be used for requirements management
in the traceability
things are in place it might work it
might not work as well you might have
some
personal view on this topic it should be
improved
but this is a stable environment if you
somehow show
just the side track without being able
to synchronize
the current channel and your side
channel
you will never be able to show the proof
of concept values
as as big as you think because that's
not an added value
so you are bringing something but at the
same time you are taking
something out of the box it's a kind of
chicken and egg scenario so
you don't have the right tool suite in
place
because you have a vision first and
before having the right tool suite
you believe that you're not able to show
the real value as you are imagining and
that's why i think the solution to that
at least what we are doing is
without explaining the details to people
what you are doing just try to connect
with gateways
like it can be bi-directional it can be
just export imports like what we are
doing in the variety management
maybe and then you can say that if i
have a full synchronization here
like in this tool suite it will be 100
better so just give me this tool suite
so that i can go that way so that's what
basically we are doing in wanda london
which is really profit based and you
should always show the value
to be invested in so that would be my
answer to this
two suite challenge question
yeah was definitely very interesting to
see what's what's going on in the field
and um yeah so our
our time is more or less already over
okay so thank you very much fadi for
your insights
and your openness talking about your
approaches i hope people can learn from
it
we will link your linkedin
profile so people can get in touch with
you if they have additional questions
uh of course uh people you can write
your comments below
the video or below the
uh streams and we will give
the questions to fatty
yeah to everybody who is not subscribed
yet please don't forget to subscribe the
channel
so you're getting informed about new
videos
and the next episode will
be with daniel siegel about a tool
and we are talking about lementry
unfortunately we can't give you a date
we are
still in consideration with daniel but
we
you will find
on the known channels
the information on the website
mbse.rocks
or on the youtube channel you will find
the date
yeah that's it for today but
do not forget trust us trust us
we are systems engineers correct good
bye
bye bye