[Music]
so
welcome to our new episode of our mbse
podcast
today
from our series mbse methodologies
and we have an exciting topic that moves
many many projects variant modeling or
more generally model based product line
engineering
and we have a guest who knows the topic
very well marco valengiri from airbus so
marco welcome and great to have you with
us please introduce yourself and then we
will dive into the topic
hello team hi christian so it's a very
big pleasure to be part of this podcast
and uh yes i'm a marco for lingerie
working currently in airbus and leading
the model-based product line
engineering topic so it's quite long
but
we had the word on the existing
concept and yes i joined airbus
2020 in the middle of the pandemic but
i've been working with this topic
already since 2012
so actually almost 10 years
and yes working different companies
before i started at bombardier
transportation when was stillborn body
transportation
now is alstom
then moved to ibm and consulting to
apply mbsc and product line engineering
enterprise architecture especially in
different companies
and industries then to accenture
and finally
airbus so and i always worked with the
product line engineering
model-based system engineering so these
are the main two areas of
experience
no it's a long journey
yeah speaking of model based product
line engineering or product line
engineering and mbse maybe we should
explain to our listeners
what is product line engineering and how
is it related to mbse
so this is the first the first question
everybody asked me
at airbus so i have to repeat this
100 times yeah so it's really simple
okay so
we have mbsc
one of the main scope of mbsc is a
model we use okay so we would like to
reuse as much as possible models
and we would like to reuse the model
that we developed for one single project
in multiple projects when a manager said
okay let me
have a look at mbsc which is the return
of investment
then most of the managers
since they invest a lot of money in the
initial mbs investment then they would
like
to reuse these models in multiple
projects for example in multiple
programs now
the reuse part
can be improved by product line
engineering so if we apply product line
engineering to mbsc then we can boost
the reuse of models but this doesn't
apply only to models it applies also
other type of artifacts like
requirements test cases source codes
design artifacts like 3d electrical
design and so on
and at the core
of this methodology
there is the management definition and
management of variability
so we need to be sure that we have a
single source
of variability
and this single source of variability
enable the reuse
of the different assets overall on top
of all the assets the mbsc the system
so
but in mbs ple there many different
terms around and
they are very often mixed up
and one of those terms is i think the
term feature
well it's a very important term in mba
ple
but it's also an important term in uml
or system modeling but there's something
different and then but of course it's
also a natural english term so what is
the feature in mbple
so a feature is like
the quidd
if we use the latin word of
for that because it's something that
everybody talk about
but nobody is able really to define okay
right so when i start a project where we
support the definition of availability
one of the first questions what is a
feature then some people start to say a
feature is a really abstract
characteristic of a system say okay good
but then okay can be something more
physical can be
something describing more physical
characteristic implementation
characteristic yes can be i am quite
flexible in the use of
features for me
uh it's like whenever you have
availability
uh and you in this variability is not
just in one specific aspect but it's
let's say it spread also multiple assets
and you want to control this variability
use a feature
for that okay
and but let's say the official
definition of feature if you look at the
standard iso two six five and zero and
the first standard
is there is a characteristic of a system
of a product that the stakeholders can
understand
that's why
it's a
and there are a lot of more um
terms in in this iso standard like asset
and product line of product family
we also
talked about or you talked about
variability
uh then there is a term like variation
and variant and variation point so can
you can you give us a rough overview how
to to bring these terms in order
yes okay so i try to refer to the
standard as much as possible but also to
deviate a bit because so in airbus we
have a different understanding of the
world
so assets after feature you have the
assets let's say that the feature define
the variability define the source of
variability
and then you need the why do you define
this source okay so because you want to
control and reuse the variability that
is implemented in several us so the
asset is actually what you want to reuse
and some some standards are so the
standard
26550 consider feature also on assets
but for me a feature is uh
something a bit more than us you know
because it it it's needed to control the
asset and in the reality doesn't exist a
feature okay
uh other types of assets can be as i
said system models are assets or source
code other assets so it's everything
that is needed to engineer a product or
a system
that you want to reuse okay
uh then after this that's we have the
concept of product line and product
family so for me the two concepts are
really synonymous okay
in airbus i would say
two
but um
we distinguish more that the product
product line can be at any level so it
can be a system can be a product can be
a component level while the product
family is really the airbus not the fly
the airplane products like the a320 a321
a330 and so so this is just an internal
distribution but for me we can see that
there are synonyms then we have
variability and variation what's
variability and variation are somehow
synonymous but i like to say that i
define the variability in the future
models and the variation in the assets
why i distinguish like that because i
there is a second term called
variant and variation points
since
there is the word variation that is it
in both a variant and variation points
i prefer to distinguish that the
variation in what you implement in the
assets what the variability is what you
define let's say more as a need as a
source
of variability in the future model okay
so um
the variant is actually the the part in
your asset that varies okay so that's at
least
my understanding here how i use the work
well the variation point is the point in
the asset where the variability where
the variation starts to propagates okay
so this is basically um
a bit and
of course rough and
fast definition of these terminologies
thank you
yeah very good so the terms are often
used very differently and so and i think
there's no single source of proof but
it's good to
that uh you have your own
uh valid definition of it um and yeah
you definitely have one and and a
reference is
iso26550 you already mentioned that
standard uh there's another standard the
new one published last year yeah last
year uh iso 26580
uh does that standard replace the other
one or what what is that
standard about oh let's say that the new
standard is an extension or clarify
what come what was before no there uh
what so the previous standard that's the
clarify in brackets
for me there are some words that in the
new standard or some terminology a new
standard are not so clear okay
so i really like the preview standard
honestly because
it was generic it could have been
applied to different
if you are using for example ovm
uh that's uh talking about ability
language or if you are using a feature
modeling language you had a broader
application
now the new one of the biggest
advantages of the new standard that was
released as we said in june 2021
is uh probably the console feature based
because it says that uh if you want to
develop product
systems with the product engineering you
have to do with a feature-based approach
and it's something i like a lot
however i think the standard is still
too much tool driven the terminology are
too much uh
put vendor to events and this is
something that i would like to avoid
especially for the definition of a
standard because it should be as much as
possible through agnostic also from the
terminologies and in general the
terminology that are in the 2650
i find that more generic and also clear
for certain aspects
that's uh
let's say a bit uh but of course i
mentioned already
ovn okay and uh
i probably i can mention folder that's
the father or feature modeling language
and these are different approaches to
formalize the variability
so if we can
the standards don't specify
any of these approaches and this also i
find it good
however
both approaches are somehow based on
features
uh folder that's
the so
it's basically the the father of uh
feature modeling
is uh uh
the
it's explicitly mentioning the features
uh and defining the features while
orthogonal variability model
is an alternative language where
feature are not i would say explicitly
defined
and
in the end it depends for me it depends
on the usage that you want to do i am
not a fan of ovm for example uh for the
following reason
because their their development is
defined orthogonally this would be a
good thing because you have let's say
your mbsc
models your dc project you have
operational functional logical you may
have the variability that is impacting
all the layers okay then you can link
the
the ovm models the variability model
and with the different assets on the
different levels photography however
there's no hierarchy
so there's no hierarchy in the ovm and
if you build a complex system like we do
in our bus that we have different levels
so system of system aircraft a big
system like fuselage cabin smaller
systems and components equipment and so
on then you get lost okay and it's
difficult to keep the consistencies of
the variability that you have defined so
that's why i'm more in favor of a
fodder let's say and of feature modeling
languages especially cardinality-based
teacher modeling languages from
charnecki that's one of the
also father of feature modeling and its
application
but in general both approaches the ovm
and future modeling that the main one
can be used for product line engineering
and product engineering is really the
the
is at the core of uh variability
management availability modeling because
it's really the mechanism that allows
you to reuse
assets
in a systematic way
for the variability scope that you need
to cover
so marco
where do you know all the stuff from uh
so when did you start uh experiencing uh
mple uh even before
bombardier or
yes so actually i started by by accident
because
i was doing my master thesis at
bombardier
and bombardier transportation was at
that time it was 2012
moving from a project oriented
organization to product line oriented
organization i was ended up
in the city of chief technology office
of the company
and we were defined the strategy the
approaches the methodology that could be
put in place
and at that time
when i was so my manager asked me to
do research about that and
i i found basically these two main
methodology mbsc
and product line engineering
and then uh
so fortunately another mark will join
the company so that's that i was marco
ferogalini that has a similar surname
and
a similar name and we are both italian
and at that time he joined one by the
transportation as a manager trying was
driving mbsc topic
and uh
and then we we got in touch and then he
we had
a lot of uh common grounds especially
because you work at aston and he already
applied
uh
product engineering with mbsc and he
showed me an article and this article
was how to boost uh
mbsc with product engineering an article
from 2014-2015
one of the first publication and then
since that time i started to investigate
research more and proposing the company
the approach and i from the beginning i
saw this strong link with mbsc so that's
why i i continue then in the other
companies to promote it within
bombardier or even with the company i
work with as a consultant
in different industry automotive defense
chemical industry railway so
and it became let's say my baby i would
say i see it really like
a small uh a small baby to
uh to grow you know and to
those i wanted other people
use it and contribute to that
that's basically the short story of it
so well you're definitely an expert of
mbl pe so one of the
best choices for airbus
to manage the the adaption of
mbpe can you give us some some insights
um how it is standard at airbus
yes so at airbus we take the topic
really serious okay so i i quote update
your
your motto no but um let's say
um
when i joined airbus 2020
there were uh some small proof of
concept about how to use a pure variance
that's one of the tools okay
how to use pure variants and doors how
to use
other tools uh
ptc
token availability modeling ptc how to
use the gears you know was really tool
oriented
and uh and actually there were some
colleagues really really smart and
really
advanced i would say they try to
experiment the topic mainly on
requirements okay so when i arrived what
i saw it was mainly the application of
product engineering requirements and
there was at the time a big debate
because uh my manager told marco we have
to give a name to this
group so i want that you are focused on
developing methodology for product
engineering but we need to give a name
to the
to the subject okay and then immediately
say model based product and engineering
and then the the the question well yeah
but we also cover also support the
requirement management and because it's
what we did before no really there were
some projects managing variability
requirements and doors and events but i
said yes okay it could be that we have
to cover this aspect and we will cover
this aspect but the goal the vision is
to go to uh mbple approach so to reach
an mbp so the combination of model basis
imaging and product engineering so it
means if we have to reach that of course
we have to pass through requirement
engineering viability textual
requirements but the idea is really to
move
uh
so the vision really to move to a
model-based approach and that's
basically how we started and uh
what we decided with the team is to
organize the project give us a framework
and otherwise the topic was really tool
driven at that time so we start to
define
uh different framework with different
categories so we have processes
method and handbooks tools information
models data model
tools and environments okay so these are
the main categories and we cover we try
to develop the topic in each category
for example we have the
system engineering processes
and airbus business processes so we look
at how uh product engineering is
impacting and mbble is impacting the
system engineering process the system
injury referential mainly based on the
in cozy handbook
uh the
airbus business process so it means
really the company landscape of process
then at metal
handbook level first we work on method
level so for us method is something that
is tool independent
and the handbook is basically the
implementation of the method within a
specific tool okay so this is the
difference we have in our bus
at um the method we start to explore so
for me one of the key things and team
was involved and helped us also in
figuring that out
because was really a new topic and due
to his experience with vamos
we
try to have a look okay how we can model
the variability in xml so it was one of
the first things that we take of
doing the mental definition and we have
several uh discussions several we define
the two main ways of doing it
and we call clean and direct but
basically way to model the variability i
will not enter into the details but
so really explore methodologically okay
so what how can we model the variability
and
then the next steps was okay now that we
have a
concept
how we can implement this concept in the
existing airbus
mdsc framework that is called moflt so
mission uh operational functional
logical and technique
and this was a very big challenge and
then comes a new challenge how we can
support now multi-level so it means if
we have variability at multiple level
multiple system level how we can support
it
and you know and this was all the
methodological part that we had to
produce handbooks because we had to
support user key users in applying this
and testing is if it was working or not
and uh we need to be sure that what we
define
can interoperables with other concepts
for example requirements validation
verification so we have an
interoperability model an information
model data model in airbus where we also
have to define uh
variability concept we come back now to
the the concept that we mentioned in the
beginning what is a variation point and
how do you link a variation for with an
asset what is a feature what is the
relation between a feature and us and so
on
and then the tools so the tools come
really after all of these so it's not
the first uh the first
piece of the puzzle
and the
edit
also i mean is really important topic
and we have several solutions we have a
tactical solution and a strategic
solution the tactical solution mainly
based on pure variance and cameo the
strategic solution will be probably
based on the 3d experience and the
sources
and then finally that's for me the most
important part is the environment okay
the environment is where we really test
and we collect feedbacks from our users
on the methodology on the tools on
everything we do so we have a page that
is public to everybody in airbus
everybody can access but we publish all
the information all the content is
really knowledge based
and the transparent available to
everybody and we
undertaking activities with different
teams in airbus from space helicopters
doors team wings
program aircraft
new flight management system and so on
zero me show a new program we provide
them the methodology to the coaches and
they apply and they provide us feedback
and we refine the methodology according
to their feedback sometimes the feedback
makes sense sometimes
we we tell them well maybe we you can do
it in a different way we don't have to
change the methodology so this is really
is really uh how we we work no it's
really a lot a lot to do and it's really
difficult to explain this in a few words
but that's really the the big score uh
at airbus
so when you talk about airbus you really
mean
the whole airbuster you mentioned space
defense commercial aircraft and so on so
it's the whole company and not only a
single project
no no because maybe i didn't mention
that i should have mentioned otherwise
my manager
[Music]
i'm part of a program called ddms for
digital design manufacturing services
their program is to transform the way
airbus engineer
its products
and of course in a digital way because
digital is the first uh word in ddms now
in the the program
and in the ideas you want to transform
the way we engineering the products from
the beginning
from the
the requirements and the market needs up
to the manufacturing and we want to
establish a digital continuity between
all the data we produced
of course in a model-based way but one
of the two main three main pillars of
the ddms in fact uh product line
modeling and simulation and digital
continuity so in this three topic match
really well with mbps
because you have
let's say you develop all three within
ambiguity
so let's let's spread ple a little bit
so if i'm a listener and i would like to
learn about it what are the main sources
for me
so first of all the standards so i would
say start with the iso 26550
is the first
standard
i would say of course you can also have
a look at the second standard the two
six five eight zero at the main
references probably i don't know if you
will understand a lot if you are a
beginner the topic because uh sometimes
they are not always clear
i would propose them two main sources
one form from matthew
uh house those i think uh
that's one of those main systematic
contributors i think
and uh
he was one of the first to talk about
mbtly especially applying with the ptc
i would say there is a ptc case with
your token availability model uh there
is a fourth tower availability model we
have klaus paul
that's also one of the main
professor and that developed the oem
topic
for
let's say for what concern mbple we have
also uh ferrogallini charlie
the the paper i mentioned before that
from 2015 how to boost mbsc with product
line engineering uh in the rolling stock
so with the allstone case
and it's really interesting there
because they propose different type of
reuse strategies
then of course uh
there is a
for product line engineering itself
there are a lot of sources okay i'm just
referring more on the mvp sources
because then product engineering is like
can be almost like mbsc so you have a
lot of sources and i'm really referring
and even the standard the standard don't
talk about mbps so the standard talk
really about ple so if we want to be
really precise the two standards refer
just ple
and there's really the two sources that
talk about mbps are
matthew hauser
and
ferogalini
from 2014 2016.
there's not so much actually
i'm actually active and maybe so we'll
come with some publications this year
let's see
no spoiler but there's not so much
actually
and so there's there's no
official definition of mbpe in a
standard right so not yet
no that's not and also we have mainly uh
some two vendors that uh let's say
called their own plugin mbtl
they kind of uh you know use the
the terminology and some people when you
talk about mvp they think immediately
about a specific tool
but in theory it should not be like that
no because it's more than that and if
you if you today you did it online mbp
you find a lot of demonstrations purely
based on boots
different tools so rapsody camillo and
with a big lever variance ptc
or the main one
but there's not really a theoretical
foundation or something too agnostic
yeah speaking of of tool agnostic um
would it make sense from your point of
view to have some kind of ple modeling
language in addition so to say to system
l or something something standardized
which is uh supported by multiple tools
yes definitely definitely it's not easy
because as i said
there is not a single understanding
there are different way of defining it
so one aspect feature model let's start
with teacher model first of all it's not
just feature modeling there's feature
modeling and obian okay the main
languages
so we which one do we pick okay so we're
already there we'll have a big
problem to make people agree on that
some people they know vm is better some
others the feature modeling no is better
because of that so we are very therefore
okay
then when we go into the
it's not just about defining features
it's also about how do we implement
these features how do we implement the
variability
and
we take now uh
the two values will will end there also
in the game
also
for example we have some tools that
apply oem some others apply feature
modeling
some of them would apply a mix of the
two then how do we realize this
variation point in the different
assets it's not easy to find i think
there were several attempts with the cbl
common variability language there have
been some attempts uh
with the
yes but a bd exchange language more on
the exchange
yes exactly but
it's really difficult to find a common
language i would so my dream would be
12. so that's my dream man so don't take
it as
2m
um
ple language or feature modeling
language based on csma so this would be
let's say
maybe for the omg group
i'll just leave it like that okay
yeah maybe as uh
m1 library in sml2 for example
yeah which is to be interesting system
lb2 will cover uh variability um but not
feature modeling it's not part of the
language
but i guess you can use this in lv2 to
do feature modeling but it's not a first
class model element so yeah actually if
i want to really why i said that because
in airbus we really find useful
uh to have our own feature modelling
it's a way to define feature models
based on csma
we have we call it c7 system feature
modeling
and actually i took it uh from uh
so the experience and some work that we
did at bombardier transportation and of
course is the idea at least and then we
refine it and it's really useful because
we
we define the features and directly in a
model-based way we can already trace
them to the assets of course the
transformation is really limited because
we
it's a plug-in that mainly focuses on
definition of features on the relation
of the constraints it would be good uh
if this could also
it could enable the transformation today
for the transformation we need to go to
those lighter variants we're doing for
then the
the feature model that we define in
coming in pure variance and so on but
the idea there is because the users find
really user friendly especially if you
already use a
system system l is really good not to
work with the same similar language and
with the same model based
functionalities and
and then be able to link your feature
directly with your models so there is
definitely an added value for that
yeah yeah and system uh
yeah it has all the the basic concepts
is already there so decomposition and
and all this stuff so it's uh
yeah
um
yeah so
well if our listeners are now interested
to learn mbple
uh or to to use in their projects uh
what's what's your recommendation for
those people um
where should they start and and so
oh first recommendation okay
it's a complex topic but the most
difficult part is dealing with people
okay so uh
because you especially in a big
organization if you're in a big
organization i expect that if you apply
a new daily problem you are in a big
organization and then you have to
explain what it's and probably these
people already uh
had difficulty to understand what the
mbsc is
and then okay now i got what the nbc now
you go there it's not but there's
something on top it's mbps
what what is that now
this is already one of the one
difficulty so really really good i would
say one recommendation is
clarify exactly what uh if you need mbp
could be that you don't need could be
that first you need to apply good mbsc
and maybe enable the reuse just
on csml with the reusing library or
modeling in a generic way
or maybe you have a requirement base a
text-based approach and you have to
reuse the requirements so you just can
apply the
the the feature modeling and the
variability of the variability
definition on the requirements
but if you really need if you have a
mbac approach and you want to boost
you want to get to the next level then i
would say you should go with mbps and
the first things clarify basically what
you cover what what it's covering in
bple and for me it's really the the and
try to explain it with simple terms to
people so to really show everything vsc
then why we put ple on top what is the
added value i use disney video to show
that you know i because you think in
airbus you deal with people that
all are analytical engineers no it's not
the case they have to go with sales
people with marketing so sometimes i use
a disney video to explain what mbp is we
use coffee machine to explain what uh
how to define the variability it's
really important to tailor the knowledge
depending which is the stakeholder
second recommendation
detach the discussion from the tools
sometimes they go into a meeting and
then the first question they're talking
about uh
are you doing with with this tool or
with these other things
please try to detach the discussion from
the tools try to have some uh
conceptual uh really thinking on the
concept and of course no don't reinvent
the weird there is there are some
sources
ask experts also to support you there
are not so many experts also but you
know there are experts even people with
a good understanding of mbsc uh can help
you okay it's better than
not having anybody and try to
reinvent the concept from scratch and
then a third recommendation i would like
to give
create a framework okay so really know
exactly
what are you doing and which category
your topic is
part of it are you working on process
are you working on methods are you
working on full
tool chain customization are you doing a
proof concept to get a feedback
about the methodology or to test
something about it to clarify the
framework
and this is more marketing so i like to
mention that but it's important
uh today we leave a social network area
right so and we have concept of hashtags
so i want that mbple in airbus becomes a
nation so one that really people use it
as uh
i sometimes i hear people talking about
mvp now
and so good but even they don't know
what it is okay so it's important
sometimes that people talk about it
within the organization
and you create somehow this height you
know that people talk about it because
you start to see everywhere and be fair
then the understanding will come okay
but sometimes it's also good to create
this momentum especially in big
organization
same for mplc
yeah exactly
not inventing anything yeah
yeah
okay wow that was
a very
compressed and
much information in around 30 minutes
so it's up to us to say mille grazie
marco
that's your voice
if you like this context uh
this context uh this content consider
subscribing to the youtube channel
and give us a thumbs up
um
yeah
tim
what's next on our agenda yeah the plan
is to talk about uh the next version of
iso 15-88
and
we will have david andler with us um the
former technical director of incosi and
he is heavily involved
in the new version and well we will have
a look um what what will be new and if
there's something in there about mbse
maybe and things like that um the date
is well it's
still in progress uh but we plan it in
some weeks
great yeah so well finally i can say
do not forget
trust us we are systems engineers
okay bye
bye bye
bye marco