Ho ho ho!
Behind the 12th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
We take a final look at
the Functional Architecture
Yesterday we created the breakdown
structure of the Functional Architecture
Now we look at the interesting
part of the Functional Architecture
It is the internal structure with ports
and connections between
the functional parts
It is also of interest to consider
the functional system context
therefore we inherit the function
called text from the system context
The inherited actors are
not purely functional
but our normal system actors
An internal block diagram of
the functional context elements
shows the context and the structure
of the Functional Architecture
A functional path represents
a group of activities
and the connectors and parts are
derived from the activity models
If an activity of one part has
an output parameter
which is an input parameter of
an activity in another function part
They are connected and the port
specifies that these parameter
objects flow through it
Some parts have no arrow
inside the rectangle symbol
Here the detailed specification
of the flow property is missing
because either it's not important or
it has not been modeled yet
The flow properties are
specified by interface blocks
The interface blocks are
the types of the ports
the block definition diagram shows
some of our functional interface books
So much for the 12th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 12th of December
Bye-bye
Goodbye