ho ho ho
behind the 12th door of our mbse podcast
advent calendar we take a final look at
the functional architecture
yesterday we created the breakdown
structure of the functional architecture
now we look at the interesting part of
the functional architecture it is the
internal structure with ports and
connections between the functional parts
it is also of interest to consider the
functional system context therefore we
inherit the function called text from
the system context
the inherited actors are not purely
functional but our normal system actors
an internal block diagram of the
functional context elements
shows the context and the structure of
the functional
architecture functional path represents
a group of activities
and the connectors and parts are derived
from the activity models
if an activity of one part
has an output parameter which is an
input parameter of an activity in
another function part
they are connected and the port
specifies that these parameter objects
flow through it
some parts have no arrow inside the
rectangle symbol
here the detailed specification of the
flow property is missing because either
it's not important or it has not been
modeled yet
the flow properties are specified by
interface blocks
the interface blocks are the types of
the ports
the block definition diagram shows some
of our functional interface books
so much for the 12th door of our mbse
podcast advent calendar and we wish you
a great 12th of december
bye-bye
goodbye