welcome to the 18th store of our mbse
podcast advent calendar today we take a
look at the modeling of profiles and
stereotypes
typically you cannot use sml out of the
box very well the language is too
general to provide enough words to talk
about a corporate system for example
systematic finds a block but not a
system subsystem component module domain
block software block and so forth
or sociality finds a requirement with
only three properties name id and text
but neither functional requirements nor
performance requirements nor properties
like a priority motivation or risks
it is intended that you extend susml
with a more specific vocabulary that
fits your need
so let's have a look at how we did it in
our model
besides others our model applies to
sysmod profile a profile defines an
extension of sysml
the profile application relationships
make the extension available for the
model
the profile is similar to a package and
contains stereotypes a stereotype
extends an existing system element it
provides a name and semantic and can
provide additional properties and
quotations
the following diagram shows some
stereotypes of the system profile which
extends the sysml block
the system stereotype specializes with
the smart block
and adds two properties to store the
problem statement and the system idea of
the system
the cismod stereotypes are defining also
different actor categories
like external systems environmental
effects and so on
as well as it introduces a new notation
therefore the actor can be depicted by
cubes in the system context
typically the first step before modeling
stereotypes is creating a concept model
of the new concepts
as one example this block definition
diagram shows the concept of variant
modeling terms from the vamos profile
vamos stands for variant modeling with
susaml
the wellness stereotypes which are part
of the system profile are derived from
this concept model
we will have a more detailed look at
variant modeling tomorrow
so much for the 18th store of our nbc
podcast advent calendar and we wish you
a great 18th of december bye bye
goodbye