Welcome to the 18th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
Today we take a look at the modeling
of profiles and stereotypes
Typically you cannot use SysML
out of the box very well
The language is too general
to provide enough words
to talk about a complex system
For example, SysML defines a block
but not "system", "subsystem"
"component", "module", "domainBlock"
"softwareBlock, and so forth
Or SysML defines a requirement
with only three properties
"name", "id", and "text"
But neither "functional requirements"
nor "performance requirements"
nor "properties" like a "priority"
"motivation", or "risks"
It is intended that you extend SysML
with a more specific vocabulary
that fits your need
so, let's have a look at
how we did it in our model
Besides others, our model
applies to SYSMOD profile
a profile defines an
extension of SysML
The profile application relationships
make the extension
available for the model
The profile is similar to a package
and contains stereotypes
A stereotype extends an
existing SysML element
It provides a name and semantic
and can provide additional
properties and quotations
The following diagram shows some
stereotypes of the SYSMOD profile
which extends the SysML block
The system stereotype
specializes the SysML block
and adds two properties
to store the "Problem Statement"
and the "System Idea" of the system
The SYSMOD stereotypes are
defining also different actor categories
like "External Systems"
"Environmental Effects", and so on
as well as it introduces a new notation
Therefore, the actor can be depicted
by cubes in the system context
Typically the first step
before modeling stereotypes
is creating a concept model
of the new concepts
As one example
this block definition diagram shows
the concept of variant modeling terms
from the VAMOS profile
VAMOS stands for Variant
Modeling with SysML
The VAMOS stereotypes which are
part of the SYSMOD profile
are derived from this concept model
We will have a more detailed look
at variant modeling tomorrow
So much for the 18th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 18th of December
Bye-bye
Goodbye