Welcome
Behind the 10th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
We take a look at
Functional Architectures
A Functional Architecture is a system
architecture based on functions
and independent of the physical entities
that implement the functions
However the functions can
depend on physical concepts
defined in the Base Architecture
The FAS method describes how to
derive the Functional Architecture
from the Use Case Activities
The first main important step
in the FAS method is
the grouping of the Use Case Activities
All the activities are grouped as
a decision of the system architect
The Functional Group itself is modeled
by a stereotype specializing in the block
The grouping then is modeled
by a trace relationship
from the Functional Group
to the activities
It is best to show and manage
the grouping in a matrix
Let's have a look at it in the model
The Functional Groups and the matrix are
located in the Functional Architecture
package in our system model
The columns are the activities
from the use case analyses
The rows are the Functional Groups
The single cells represent the
presence of a trace relationship
A special learning gift of today
sometimes it is easier
to manage relationships
between model elements in a matrix
instead of showing
them in a diagram
the following diagram shows
the same information as the matrix
So, you can easily see
that it is more confusing
The next step is to derive the
Functional Architecture from the groups
We will have a look to this tomorrow
So much for the 10th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 10th of December
Bye-bye
Goodbye