welcome
behind the tenth store of our mbse
podcast advent calendar we take a look
at functional architectures
a functional architecture is a system
architecture based on functions and
independent of the physical entities
that implement the functions however the
functions can depend on physical
concepts defined in the base
architecture
the first method describes how to derive
the functional architecture from the use
case activities
the first main important step in the
first method is the grouping of the use
case activities
all the activities are grouped as a
decision of the system architect
the functional group itself is modeled
by a stereotype specializing in the
block
the grouping then is modeled by a trace
relationship from the functional group
to the activities
it is best to show and manage the
grouping in a matrix let's have a look
at it in the model
the functional groups and the matrix are
located in the functional architecture
package in our system model
the columns are the activities from the
use case analyzers
the rows are the functional groups
the single cells represent the presence
of a trace relationship
a special learning gift of today
sometimes it is easier to manage
relationships between model elements in
a matrix instead of showing them in a
diagram the following diagram shows the
same information as the matrix
so you can easily see that it is more
confusing
the next step is to derive the
functional architecture from the groups
we will have a look to this tomorrow
so much for the 10th store of our mbse
podcast advent calendar and we wish you
a great 10th of december bye bye
goodbye