hello
behind the third door of our mbse
podcast advent calendar we take a quick
look at requirements modeling
there is and has been a lot to say about
requirements modelling we will limit
ourselves to one special feature which
is also the learning gift of today the
reuse of requirements
this is a bit unusual but is supported
by system l with a special relationship
and the relationship is not yet used
that often
in the christmas tree business there is
the important international christmas
tree standard abbreviated ics
the specific ics
2425-26-12 standard contains a list of
requirements for christmas trees we
import the standard to our model as a
model library
so let's have a look at our model
as an example the following table
contains
three of the christmas tree standards in
our library
so it's here in the library package and
here is the table
and they are for example
the tree shape now the shape of the tree
shall be complied with the ics standard
the three kinds the tree shall be a
third tree and the tree height the tree
shall be at least 150 centimeters and
maximum 200 centimeter high
our mbse podcast christmas tree project
would like to use exactly these
requirements from the library
however we would like to have a
different numbering schema and also add
additional properties like obligation
priority or the stakeholder
therefore we use the system a copy
relationship to create copies of the
requirements in our model
we have here an example for the tree
which is located in the base
architecture
there's the tree and the requirement of
the tree and here is our
diagram
the requirement height of the tree is a
copy of the standard requirement tree
height
the relationship assures that the text
of the copied requirement is always
identical to the master
all other properties can be different
the following table shows some of our
mbse podcast christmas tree requirements
with the properties
id name text obligation priority
stakeholder and the master of the
requirement if it is a copy
so let's open the table it's here in the
requirements package
system requirements and here's the table
the requirements are in different
packages of the model some of them are
located in the package structure of the
related component for example here those
for the tree
so much for the third door of our mbse
podcast advent calendar and we wish you
a great third of december
goodbye
bye