welcome
behind the 14th store for mbse podcast
advent calendar we take a look again on
the physical architecture
yesterday we worked on the definition of
the physical architecture and the
allocation of the elements from the
functional architecture
let's have a look at it again in the
model
today we will cover the internal
structure of the physical architecture
the internal block diagram shows all
parts and connections of our physical
architecture
it's somewhat simplified here and we
have not explicitly modeled all of the
ports
as a reminder you can identify the
inherited elements by the circumflex
symbol before the name
if the system is more complex
you will have more internal block
diagrams
on the one hand different diagrams on
the different hierarchical levels of the
system and on the other hand diagrams
for different aspects for example
internal block diagrams that only show
logical or internal block diagrams that
show only electrical connections
or entire block diagrams that only show
the connections necessary for a specific
use case
so much for the 14th store of our mbse
podcast advent calendar and we wish you
a great 14th of
december bye-bye goodbye