Welcome
Behind the 14th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
We take a look again on
the Physical Architecture
Yesterday we worked on the definition
of the Physical Architecture
and the allocation of the elements
from the functional architecture
Let's have a look at it again in the model
Today we will cover the internal
structure of the Physical Architecture
The internal block diagram shows
all parts and connections
of our Physical Architecture
It's somewhat simplified here
and we have not explicitly
modeled all of the ports
as a reminder, you can identify
the inherited elements
by the circumflex symbol before the name
If the system is more complex
you will have more internal block diagrams
On the one hand
different diagrams on the different
hierarchical levels of the system
And on the other hand
diagrams for different aspects
for example internal block diagrams
that only show logical
or internal block diagrams
that show only electrical connections
Or entire block diagrams that only show
the connections necessary
for a specific use case
So much for the 14th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 14th of December
Bye-bye
Goodbye