welcome to a new episode of our mbse
podcast today's episode
comes again from our series on
mbs
and we are not looking at a standard
system modeling tool but at the ink very
sweet from inquiry labs
we will talk about the tool in the first
part of the episode and look at it in a
demo in the second part so for all your
only listeners it means that the second
part might be difficult to follow the
podcast without the video
today we have two great guests with us
eastbound from inquiry and enrique from
zuken so
let's start with the introduction so
please introduce yourself let's start
with eastbound welcome
welcome thank you very much for having
me and having us today i really
appreciate that
my name is ishnarat i'm the ceo of
inquiry labs
the digital thread analytics company has
been uh call it nowadays but many of our
listeners maybe know us from the mbsc
world as a provider for customized tool
solutions around various mbsc tools and
tool chains
and csml in general
and obviously i'm here today to talk
about our flagship product the inquiry
suite
all right i am enrique kursmalnik i
think that might be the first time many
of you have actually heard me pronounce
my last name
i usually just go by enrique
um i'm currently the ceo of vitek vitec
is a company that was acquired by
zuken in august of 2019
and i think many of the listeners might
be familiar with vitek as being the
originators and developers of core
which has now been succeeded by genesis
which is the new modeling platform from
vitek
and uh of course i know tim and
christian and ishvan from my
previous role as cto of no magic so i'm
very excited to be here um excited to be
talking about mbsc and excited to be
showing some of the work
that uh ishvan and i have been working
together uh working on together for the
last six months or so
yeah great very nice to have too so yeah
so to say long-term experts on mvc here
on the podcast
um yeah
as we already discovered you're from two
different companies and um maybe you can
tell our listeners um
what's the relationship between inquiry
and zukin or why tech
well i think that's a great place to
start
um so as i mentioned zuken acquired
vitek
in 2019 and zuken for those of you who
don't know
is an international company
headquartered in yokohama japan
known for its ecad tools specifically
around pc board design wire harness etc
and zuken realized a while back
that it was important to start moving
upstream couldn't continue to just be a
detailed design company focus on
electrical and electronic design
um the
correlation and the connection between
ecad electrical design and
mbse specifically because so many
complex systems today are dependent on
electrical electronic
execution of behaviors and software
that's
deployed through ecu's
they're inextricably connected right
so
being able to move upstream to the
architecture and that top-down design
was very important to zuken
hence the acquisition so there are
really two dimensions to to the work
that's that's been done
um
zuken
sees the the streamlining of that
transition from architecture to detail
design as a critical
enabler
for successful development of products
right now as we know uh mbsc and systems
engineering unfortunately
function
as a silo in many cases
and and that's problematic it's
problematic for organizations because
they can't really realize the the
potential roi
that mba and not just mbsc but the whole
digitalization
this whole transformation can deliver
so one aspect is this streamlining of
that transition from architecture to
detail design
but the second aspect of this
is and this is really driven by by vitec
is a belief that it is open and
connected
ecosystems that need to drive
these digital engineering strategies in
these digital engineering platforms
smaller companies like inquiry labs
are companies that often drive a lot of
the innovation
in industries
and
we as zooken we as vitec want to help
enable that
we see these collaborative partnerships
as really bringing new ideas and new
technologies to the market
and you know these
providing these open connected vendor
neutral and i
you know it's hard to say vendor neutral
because as you know it's hard to support
everything out there but as vendor
neutral as one can be
you know the idea being that we want
companies to be able to select their
tool chain
find the tools that they believe are
best of breed and that best fit their
needs
and build that digital solution on those
tools um so the partnership was was
really a natural and uh the
conversations have been
very natural and
they were driven really by this
lightweight bridge that zuken developed
to connect genesis to
the the wire harness tool
and having had you know a previous
relationship with with ishvan and his
company
i saw them as being a
a partner that could really help tie
this together for us
so i know it was a long answer but i
think there was a lot to share in that
absolutely
the lightweight bridge between
e3 and the genesis the lightweight
bridge is a part of the inquiry suite
then
no it is not part of the it's not part
of the inquiry suite it is actually a
product that is
that has been developed and is marketed
by zukin us
okay so and welcome the inquiry speed
then into the game
so the inquiry suite is a layer that
sits on top of that so the bridge itself
what it does is it exposes a design
envelope
you can think of this as
you know the the information needed by
the electrical engineer to do their job
so we provide in this design envelope
you know diagrams requirements um
verification requirements test
configurations
all done through a viewpoint so the
systems engineer
doesn't have to do anything that special
other than
you know i'll i'll make this analogous
to to the sysml world it's basically
adding some stereotypes right so
you you um
you make sure
as a systems engineer that you indicate
what
signals are electrical signals
what components
are electrical components are
participating in an electrical system
so
basically just like stereotyping
and
through this process we're able to
extract this viewpoint that is then
consumed by the electrical engineer
and is used to prime that initial
electrical design
in the process of priming that design
and bringing information over from
genesis into e3 we begin to create that
traceability that that connection
right
but that wasn't enough
right that's only part of the process
we have to ensure that what's brought
over
is then worked on in a way that that
delivers a complete design because we
can't bring
a detailed design over when
in its entirety when we're doing
something that's at a high abstract
level right we're only providing
guidance and knowledge and
specifications for what needs to be done
but there's still a lot of work that the
electrical engineer has to do
so the idea behind this is to make sure
that as the electrical engineer
does it does his or her job as they are
iterating on this that we have a way to
automatically check
the the quality of the model and make
sure that
that what is defined in that
specification is reflected
in the detailed design right if a
component exists in the architecture it
should exist in the detailed design
if there's a connection
it should exist
if there's a signal it should be
allocated to some sort of wire somewhere
right so we run all of these checks to
ensure that what we've
specified
is complete and consistent and correct
on the
design side iterating that means this
bridge works in both directions so it's
not only that you push information from
genesis to e3 but also in the other
direction
there is information that goes in the
other direction
so the electrical engineer is able to
provide feedback
uh for example on on requirements and
verification testing
that would go back to the model exactly
exactly and it's a good point tim
because one of the one of the problems
we have today is not just that this
process of transitioning from
architecture to detailed design is is
disconnected
as a result of that the model becomes
irrelevant right the model
doesn't matter anymore and the detailed
design continues to evolve
without any reference back to the
original architecture
so this gives a way to bring that back
that feedback back into the model so yes
it is actually
it is actually a two-way connection and
i guess
electronics and software are also
tightly connected very often and i saw
that
inquiry suit also offers alm
connectors and so on
so
i think we will
see some more information now in in the
demo so you
prepared something for us
yes actually that's the plan so so
actually the
the this integration with with zukan uh
e3 and wi-tech genesis is something that
we covered the uh in some talks earlier
this year uh first i think at the
western states regional conference and
then later at the models industry tracks
and obviously i'm going to show you the
the
relevant part of the demos today but for
today we prepared an
extended significantly extended
demonstration that showcases some other
capabilities of the inquiry suite and
puts you know some of the things that
you may have seen earlier into a bigger
and broader context
actually we are going to to be using
a different set of tools
for that part focusing on sysaml and and
requirements management in in jira so
yes the demo is going to be
much more than what you have seen
previously
dean if you were wondering how committed
zukin and vitek are to open ecosystems
there you go right we're we're gonna be
the the core of the demonstration today
will actually be with with other tools
and i think that's great because
you know environments aren't completely
homogeneous today yeah
right so
we we need to provide
rich connectivity and foundations for
organizations to build these
digital ecosystems
and uh is you mentioned in the beginning
that uh inkberry is is the digital
thread company i think you named it like
that yes and the term digital effect is
used very often and very
differently
so
what's the digital thread for for you
and uh i am i think i use the term the
digital thread analytics which is
something a little bit more specific
than just a digital thread obviously
the digital thread i think is it's uh
probably a term that is more used in the
u.s uh rather than over here in europe
but it's basically to me
expresses the idea that
all the engineering data that we all
work with in various processes
is not you know a collection of isolated
uh artifacts uh you know that that are
somehow uh just connected loosely in our
heads uh some way right but they should
be part
of the digital thread something that is
tangible
in technological terms
that that actually provides this
end-to-end traceability across all the
different artifacts that need to be
connected in an engineering process
for the purpose of
you know providing navigability going
from tool to tool in a seamless way
integrating the tools to each other
being able to generate at least part of
the documentation which is very
important especially in safety critical
design processes
and also helping on board
new engineers to an organization which
is a very important added value i think
of modern tools especially
that you know these very complex
engineering disciplines become more
accessible so this is the digital thread
part of the answer and what
our technology can provide as an added
value to all of this is the analytics
part right
and of course nowadays data analytics
and data science in general are
extremely popular and have an extremely
high impact of industrial and
academically
and we want to
what we want to achieve with our tool is
to bring the results of all of the
these uh these innovations to the
digital engineering domain
to
engineers
the team leads and then
architects to take advantage of uh
powerful capabilities for the purpose of
quality assurance maintaining the
quality of the model of
in the digital thread and also for
facilitating automated tool integration
and many other interesting features so
this is what we
envision has to be the future of of
engineering tools
so that's a little bit like like the
compiler of the
the engineering data
i think that's that's often missing in
mbse
great models
but nobody really checks if
it really works but it's like
programming without running the compiler
yes yes you could you could you could
use this analogy i think that's a good
one
okay
and um
this is your tool then i think we will
see that later in the demo but is your
tool
uh visible for the engineer
this is something that works in the
background
of course i have actually i think and so
but but if i work with an mbse tool with
genesis and with e3 have also worked
with uh inquiry suite
then
yes the answer to this question as with
all good questions is a yes and a no at
the same time depending on your context
so originally originally where we
started this you know developing this
product
it was originally intended to be
something which is in the background so
something that is not necessarily
visible directly to the end user for the
systems engineer but as a service to a
tool vendor or a tool integrator inside
an organization
to to to provide additional value-added
services on top right
maybe for the purpose of integrating
certain tools together or adding
very desirable features to
popular modeling platforms such as
the ability of being able to search
inside the teamwork cloud repository for
instance right so this was the original
idea
but once we once we started building
this and talking to vendors and
potential customers we realized that
there is actually quite tangible and
high demand on the customer side
for directly integrating and interacting
with such features
uh mostly because
you know as
there is a large degree of heterogeneity
among the tools that are using organ is
it
there's a design i mean every organ
to try to own actually own
uh their data rather than having it just
inside uh various engineering tools and
able to do
uh we did things that the original
vendors have never even imagined that
would be meaningful and useful to the
end user right
and that's why what we once we started
doing about two years ago is to develop
the inquiry suite into
not just an enabler technology or a kind
of a middleware
but also an end user product that can
cater to
various audiences originally
expert audiences so people who not just
understand the modeling and mbsc but
also can write a database query for
example but as you will see in the demo
gradually as we progress with the
development of this product we are more
and more
approaching the level that we can
provide value-added and easy-to-use
features
out of the box essentially for systems
engineers or people who are in charge of
reviewing the work and integrating the
work of systems
yeah
i was wondering uh why there was no plm
tool on the list of your connectors
right now maybe you already have
connectors for in in the case of some
customers
um but you are really focusing at the
moment so that's my point of view on
systems engineering
as a single domain and then
now the
step in in direction to
eda ecat
and alm
yeah yeah so so inquiry suite is a very
new product in fact i would say that
that uh that it's uh
it's it's at its current stage it's it's
still in a kind of a pile of uh face
majority of our customers but it's
developed at a quite rapid pace and
one of the one of the consequences of
this is that the connectors that we
offer are expanding also
basically from quarter to quarter at the
moment i think we have connectors in
five
categories systems engineering tools
such as cameo
and we are working on one for enterprise
architect
uh the second one is uh um
actually i would say al and pln2 so the
likes of uh jama for example
can
be as a such a tool in in the way and we
are working on connector tools like
polarion for example
the third one is a documentation
platform like confluence or
mbe in a certain way i think it can be
regarded as well you know with the view
editor and stuff like that
and jupiter of course the fourth one is
simulation tools like modelling which is
a very nice modern web-based tool for
working with modelica simulations
and the fifth one at the moment on our
focus is ecad and and this also ties
back into your first question which i
wanted to uh reflect on why the
partnership with vitek and zulkin is of
particular interest to us and the reason
for this is that we have found that ecad
is actually
one of the most frequently used
tools together with mbsc at least
looking at our customer base and there
is actually a quite a
tangible demand for for integrating ecat
tools better with mbsc tools because mbs
suppose to my surprise
actually i'm coming you know originally
from the model driven software
engineering world as many of my
colleagues they know
is that mbsc tools are actually used for
hardware design quite quite
substantially so so that's the reason
why we are particularly interested in
ecad as well
interesting
i think you mentioned or
i saw on your website that
the ink very sweet
creates a knowledge graph so so the
digital thread is stored in the
knowledge graph so what actually is is
stored
then in inquiry street now if we have e3
there's the the e-card stuff and genesis
has three mvse stuff and what is stored
in
inquiry then
yeah so the fundamental idea of of
analytics in our case our approach to
managing the digital thread in this
knowledge graph is
that that uh that we don't intend to
replace any of the engineering tools
rather we want to augment them right so
the users
work as they did before with whatever
tools they want to work with or whatever
tools they have already available
but using our connectors
the data
can be um let's say
um
extracted from these engineering tools
in a scalable
important
thing is
to this unified and the common uh
representation which we call the
knowledge graph and conceptually
this is really a graph like
maybe in technical terms i would even
call it a property graph you know so
nodes and edges and attributes and
whatever and this is then stored
in our own
database actually collection of
databases at the same time because the
unique uh let's say design principle of
the inquiry suit is what i call
redundancy by design which means that we
not only store this data in one
particular format but actually three or
four or even more depending on the use
cases because what we have found is that
in
in reality the
what you actually want to do with this
data whether you want to use it for
numerical analysis purposes or tool
integration purposes is just validation
purposes
is a different kind of representation
which can provide the optimal
performance and scalability for that
scenario so that's why the inquiry suit
is really
technically speaking an epl engine of
some of some sort so an extra
transformer load
which is able to to use this engineering
data that is coming from the stores and
put it into various scalable cloud ready
back-end storages and then do
interesting things on on top of this
these representations um and and at its
core the inquiries would also provides a
set of apis open apis in fact
you know accessible through rest uh full
interfaces with open uh web tools
to access uh the contents of the
knowledge graph travels or process the
contents of the knowledge graph and also
you know do interesting things with that
so run queries on it or an analysis on
it
or or
basically other things as well so this
is the core core engine of the
technology
but those interesting things are
important
yes
it's the interesting things which the
users will then find useful not just you
know being able to access the data even
though i think from a from an
organization's point of view or someone
who is working inside an organization on
managing and integrating a tool chain
even just the fact
to be able to to access the data which
was previously only
possible in a in a proprietary
i think it's
people very well
in many cases
enrique maybe another question for you
so
many people are connecting the company
of vitec to the name of david long so
what did they say to to this corporation
and then to the
all the software stuff you are doing now
well you know david is is very committed
to this concept of an open ecosystem
and really believes that
you know we need to break out of this
scenario where
systems engineering has been so siloed
for so many years
um so you know
we talk about this regularly obviously
over the last two months
since i joined vitek
but
he's he he very much
likes what he has seen with this
um because it does add that
that layer of of semantic richness
and to to the
full
digital thread right it's not just about
creating these links anymore it's not
just about knowing what the relation
that the relationship exists
it's about understanding what's inside
of that relationship that's important
and we know as a company
we can't solve everyone's problem by
ourselves
right we're really good
at that
that behavioral description we're really
good
at the upper left side of the v we're
really good at that stuff
we don't claim to be nor do we want to
be a plm company or a digital threat
analytics company but we want what we
want to do
is provide that connectivity and expose
the data that's needed
so that companies like inquiry labs and
other partners
can leverage that so we can really
provide the solutions that people are
looking for in the market
so could you also say
through a tool like inquiry
labs
you can or very suit
um you can really bring
the systems engineering
process which tells us the iso 5288 and
so on
to bring that really to life and to
digitalize this one
i think that's a really good observation
and it it's consistent with a lot of the
conversations that we have internally
um you know at zukin at vitec and
conversations we've had with with ishman
that
this is about the process it's about the
engineering process it's about the
workflow we have to consider who needs
to consume data where
we're too focused sometimes on on the
technology as you know
and not focused enough on really
enabling the work
and at the end of the day
it's the work that gets these products
done
um so bringing that to life i think is a
really astute observation
can we use that for our marketing are
you okay
i'm okay with that
okay
so if you connect many models and tools
i think you it's important for you to
rely on some some standards so are there
some standards uh used by inquiry or
research yes
yes of course of course so so there are
i think that the standards that we rely
on are basically on two levels
rely on a lot of technical standards
which are not
uh necessarily uh you know the euro
standards but maybe defacto standards in
the web-based engineering world such as
uh you know swagger and open api and
many other related things like oidc so
open id connect for example which is the
way that you authenticate and authorize
yourself when you log into the inquiry
suite
but we also make extensive use of omg
standards for example for enabling
various systems engineering use cases
right so we have
obviously a quite high level of support
for uml csml
um and and all the the various domain
specific profiles uh based on these
languages you know like the application
frameworks and
which are relevant in the bod context uh
for instance
and of course
one of the one of the core features of
the inquiry model analyzer which is a
solution uh as a part of the inquiry
suite is to to to be able to perform
scalable you know syntactic and and and
structural validation of system l models
for example against
the these rules which are included in
this standard so that's basically one of
the core features
yeah speaking of the features um we have
already talked for around 30 minutes so
let's let's have a look into the tool oh
yeah yeah
i really didn't see it
yeah i also know all these um
some screenshots from the website and
considered an early christmas gift
[Laughter]
ishvan you are muted yeah i know i know
so we should start with the original
we should start with the original
example like the first one this this e3
genesis connector and i will let enrique
narrate this one
yeah so you know as i mentioned earlier
that transition from
from architecture to detail design is
very painful for most organizations
over the last six years as i've worked
with different companies
i've seen many companies show a lot of
success and a lot of
maturity in that upper left part of the
v
but
moving down to that detailed design
is is a very painful process for
most of the organizations i've i've
engaged with over the last six years
so
if we want to
move to the next slide
so this is a quick video
that is showing genesis it's a simple
drone model
and as we in introspect this model we
will see that it's very simple it's just
an example it has two components
you know a link and an item or a signal
that's being sent across that link
there are also these these two
components have have types assigned to
them so power electronics and type ecu
and that signal that we referenced
earlier there are actually two signals
battery voltage positive and negative
so now what we're looking at is e3 this
is the actual wire harness tool and that
little box that popped up
is the interface for the connector
so the electrical engineer actually
browses the model repository directly
finds
the part of the project they're looking
for
and actually loads it straight into
the topology diagram where we already
have an existing mechanical drawing
right so now the electrical engineer can
start doing their work laying out
components
and where you see that dashed line that
means that there's
there's a a
signal but nothing defined yet to carry
it so the electrical engineer starts to
create that
and now what you're going to see is that
two-way link
where we're actually going to
cross-check
that
that component we saw in the model is
that wire in the diagram
so it's just a simple example to show
how we bring that over
how simple it is it is designed
primarily for the electrical engineer
what you didn't see in there native uh
right now is that
all of the information related to
to requirements and other diagrams that
help the engineer understand the context
of what they're working and that's
included in this design envelope that's
provided
um so of course this is a first gen
first generation the electrical engineer
can access the the requirements that are
connected to the
uh
uh system element or wasn't wasn't
systematic it was uh
the white core language
yeah yeah so they they can see
all the requirements that are related
to the
the elements needed
to realize their design
okay so maybe i will take over for this
particular slider because this is a this
is not a dumbbell yet it's just a
screenshot and you will see similar ones
in the demo later on
so so the the thing that we developed in
connection with this connector is is a
is an analysis uh
let's say rule set that you can run in
the inquiry model analyzer
which is useful for doing something that
we call the so-called 3c analysis 3c
stands for correctness completeness and
consistency
and this kind of analysis over the
digital thread
is special because it doesn't look into
one particular artifact only so it
doesn't just look into the vitec systems
engineering model
or the e3 ecad model but it looks into
the combination of these models so it
looks looks at both of them
at the same time and also between the
traceability links and these models
which is created by this genesis e3
connector
and what it looks for is
weather
during this transition phase the
engineer
engineering team
could maintain the correctness
completeness constancy of the mapping
obviously
the
correctness and the completeness is more
down to the automated connector in this
sense so when we run this analysis what
we will see is that the completeness is
pretty good meaning that a large part of
the original systems engineering model
has captured in genesis was actually
successfully mapped or represented on
the eca side it's not complete because
as you could see in the demonstration
the engineer actually checked the tick
mark
unselecting one particular
component from the original model and
that's why we only have a partial
mapping here
but what is more interesting i think
from analysis point of view is that it
reports
inconsistencies on the electrical
engineering side the reason for this
inconsistencies are that there are
things that
are not present actually in the systems
engineering model and it cannot be
processed and and created by this
connector automatically which is
essentially related to
the wiring information that is specific
to the electrical engineering domain so
the the corresponding findings rule
findings which you see on the right side
of the screenshot
tell the electrical engineers that you
need to look into your ecat model
because there is work to be done
you need to create wiring information so
that your electrical engineering design
model become consistent with the high
level information transfer that is
expressed on the systems engineering
side okay so this is the the basic added
value of the 3c analysis over
such a transitionary scenario that we
can make the electrical engineer aware
that what they are working on what they
have in their own workspace is not
consistent with an upstream artifact the
systems engineering model okay and this
is possible without
making the electrical engineer actually
open you know uh vitek genesis and have
a look at the model themselves this is
the power of digital threat analytics
right so so um basically
propagating this very important quality
related information across an
engineering tomb team who work at
different stages of the remodel
the next one is a
i think for enrique
i'll have to see if i remember this one
[Laughter]
well what happens here is basically
realizing this the electrical engineer
then it's to create the wiring diagram
yeah so
yeah so it's taking the information that
was primed into the
into e3 and now the detailed work is
starting to happen
yeah right so now we're getting to the
point where there's not just a connector
and a a harness but now individual wires
and pins
right so we need to know that that
signal
has a wire and that there are there's an
actual complete connector for it
so i mean that that's what we do on the
detailed design side that isn't
necessarily reflected in the higher
level model right the higher level model
we know there's a link
but we don't necessarily know how many
wires make up that connector or what the
end points what type of connector it is
but we do have to make sure that if
there's a critical signal or an item
that needs to go across that signal path
that it is accounted for in a correct
way and in a consistent way
yes and once this is done once this is
done
then the electrical engineer
you know saves their work
in some after some background
processing you know the new version of
this electrical design is going to be
pulled into this digital uh thread the
knowledge graph we can then rerun the
analysis and then find
that because of what has been created in
the previous sequence now there is one
less pair of rule violations so the
overall quality of this model of models
has been improved because this
consistency problem or one let's say
instance of the consistency problems
that existed between the high level
artifact and the detailed design
artifact has been successfully
resolved so this is a very basic
let's say use case or unit of work that
the the combination of the suit and the
connector can power
and and what what what this can be built
into
is basically a project management or a
quality management dashboard
so to say which is also directly
possible using the inquiries within
various different ways
that can actually act as a kind of a
progress bar on a complex engineering
process right because we can we can turn
these
reports into numbers that can power
charts right uh that correspond to
to what is the gap uh you know the
validation gap that you have to close
as par
in preparing for a release for example
of the design artifact so this chart
actually shows you know as the progress
of work is is going forward across
various revisions in time
because what is very important to know
about our knowledge graph is that it's
not just a snapshot of your engineering
data
but it's it continuously evolves with
your work because your work is usually
maintained in a version control system
like you know git or timber cloud or
some other technology in the case of of
zooken tools and our connectors
actually are virgin aware so they not
only retrieve snapshots of the
engineering data but metadata as well
with versioning information which allows
us to do historical analysis as well
which is which is basically what is
happening here under the hood
okay so
moving on in the demonstration uh this
was the the the initial part that we
have shown previously and now is the new
part which i have specifically paired
for today and for today uh for the
demonstrating the further capabilities
of the inquiry suite we are going to
look at a similar scenario but something
which is happening let's say one
step higher in the v model again a kind
of a transitional scenario but the one
which happens
between let's say the high level
requirements analysis
and the the you know system uh level
design and the context of the
demonstration is going to be a tool
chain
on the one hand
that is consisting of you know um camera
collaborator camera systems modeler and
timbre cloud the tool chain
from the magic or dassault which is i
think very well known in the community
and very well respected
and in combination with these systems
engineering tools we are going to be
using confluence for the purpose of
documentation management and maintaining
the overall let's say knowledge base of
the engineering team and the engineering
process we are going to be using jira as
a lightweight
requirements management tool on the one
hand and on the other hand also for the
purpose of
managing the engineering process itself
so checking the tracking tasks um in in
jira
and we are going to connect these set of
tools together using the capabilities of
the inquiry suite for the purpose of
checking and quality analyze
the various artifacts which are found in
this
process and also on the other hand
performing another kind of 3c analysis
looking at the quality of model of
models as we cross
tool boundaries okay so the first demo
sequence is just
for you to show and get familiar with
the context of the example for this
particular demonstration we are going to
use the forest fire detection system
which is a very nicely elaborated
systems engineering example
uh you know incorporating many different
aspects of csml as a language including
you know
component level design requirements
many other things
including very nice limit diagrams i
think this is something which is a
really good example for demonstrating
the power of mbsc and mbs related tools
as well here you can see this model in
camera collaborator which is basically a
web-based platform for showcasing the
contents of a system model as an
interactive and structured document that
you can browse and navigate
along
you know the standard web-based user
interfaces
and um
you know this model has got a lot of
different types of documents and
diagrams as well
block diagrams uh use case diagrams many
other things which are going to play an
interesting role in our demonstration
today
in addition to this as you could see we
had
some documents in confluence here on
this uh tab but we also have a jira
project set up you know jira is also an
atlassian tool
that you can use to manage
issues and and essentially these issues
can either be corresponding to tasks
that we have to follow on on our
modeling project as well as
requirements actually you can you can
use jira for the purpose of enumerating
that so
basically this is the starting point for
the context of the demonstration for
today
and first i'm going to show you how
these tools are actually then pulled
into this knowledge graph representation
this is run through
the inquiry servers workspace manager
which is what we are going to engage as
you can see in this demonstration
basically almost all the tools of the
inquiry suite are web-based tools so
that's the reason why we see all the
interaction happening in the browser
window
here on this interface you see workspace
manager
on the left side we can see the various
data sources uh that are configured in
this particular installation so as you
can see we can access our confluence
invert cloud instances and also the mms
is here but we are not going to be using
that for our demonstration today and on
the right is what we call the workspace
so that's actually the portion of the
knowledge graph that our current user
who is logged into the system can use
and populate and this is what our user
is actually going to do now so we are
going to navigate to the forest fire
demonstration as it's stored on finger
cloud
we are going to select a particular
project on a branch in a particular
revision so this is what i told that the
connector is version aware and we are
just going to add it to the workspace
very quickly it's a matter of just a few
seconds
it's uh basically happening all the data
processing in the background
and the same thing we are going to be
doing for the jira project
add to the workspace to have this
representation
as part of the knowledge graph as part
of our
you know digital thread so it is very
easy to to pull in
various parts of you know your
engineering data into this system this
is one way of doing this the manual way
but it's also important to emphasize
that we have a way of automating this
you know that it happens automatically
in the background as revisions are
checked in for instance
now the first thing that i want to show
to you is
what if we just want to analyze one
particular artifact in the digital
thread so not yet across two boundaries
but i just want to see if my system
model is okay
for this purpose we are going to be
using um this information flow integrity
analysis which is essentially
something that i think is also described
in the standards but in this particular
sense we
example we extended it a little bit with
some custom logic
it's an example of a verb from less
validation rule right so
we are going to look for a condition
around the way information flows are
modeled in the system model
which can be a source of a problem so if
there is a presence there is a match
found by the analyzer that means that
that's actually a quality issue that we
have to address on the systems
engineering level in order to do this uh
the solution that we use in the inquiry
suite is what we call the inquiry
modalizer
we use an analyst bridge to manage this
automated validation analysis reports it
supports the standards that i already
mentioned such as system upd and uaf as
well as open source libraries such as
the sai digital engineering validation
tool which is a very nice set of rules
for doing exactly the same thing
and it has got a standalone web-based
user interface as well as a very good
integration with the jupiter
ecosystem that is an open source uh
document meditation management platform
originating from the data analysis
community
and what you are also going to be using
in the demo is another solution that we
call inquiry model viewer which is a
generic web-based visualization tool for
looking at the contents of the knowledge
graph as it is stored
inside the inquiry suite so in order to
use this feature
we are going to launch the model
analyzer on this particular artifact
we are going to
select this custom flow integrity
validation suite which is documented in
the confluence as you could see in the
previous example so that's where the
screenshot was from this this page
describes to the systems engineer in
detail what is the logic that is being
checked here and what's the relevance of
such a rule and if you have found the
match in the analysis core then how to
resolve that match
and once the analysis is complete you
can see that we could run this analysis
rather quickly even if there is 2 300 or
even millions of modern elements
you see a detailed uh
report essentially that contains
how many instances we have found for
violations of a particular validation
rule and for each violation you get a
detailed
uh
table basically
that tells the the systems engineer
where exactly the model that problem
resides and
now we can actually navigate to that
location using that link opening uh the
model viewer focusing on that particular
model element right this connector here
this is this is a system model that you
see in this screenshot so this is what
what you would actually see inside uh
magic draw or camel systems modeler or
team or camel collaborator which you
will see in a moment but we also see not
just the structure of the model you know
packages classes diagrams connectors
properties etc but also
here on the right side of the screen you
can see the various attribute values for
example and all the cross references
which may craft structure this model
okay
so the modal viewer is a generic
interface it's it's customized in this
case a little bit to csml so there are
filters applied for example on the left
side of the screen
but in general the same kind of user
visualization applies to everything
which is stored in the knowledge graph
so jira you know modelling and all the
other
tools that we have connectors for can be
visualized and open the very same way
very quickly integrated
into this suite
and from here this model viewer it's
also very easy to navigate back to the
original tool from where the data came
so from with one click of a button we
can go back to
camera collaborator for example
in this instance to see in the original
context you know where the the rule
violation is coming so from so where in
the system model uh it will need to be
uh you know fixed at this point i think
i will make a little bit of a break and
ask if you have any questions related to
all the things that i have shown so far
i think it was crystal clear so far and
straight on
very impressive
okay so let's move on uh because now i
want to show you another capability that
maybe a little bit slower so as you
could see
the modalizer analyzer is not just
capable of running built-in
business logic so these validation
analysis rules but it also gives the
power of running custom rules queries
essentially obviously to a more advanced
user okay so in this case this is the
functionality that we are going to show
off
here
i think we are going to you know it's
still the same sorry so maybe this one
is the best one yeah so we are going to
run the model query part yes
and here
uh there is obviously a couple of
built-in queries example
the ones that are related to uh this
custom flow analysis in in in this
configuration of the inquiry suite there
are three query languages that the user
can select from
week well sparkuel and elasticsearch
elasticsearch is uh is a is a full text
engine uh that has also some structural
uh constraint capabilities it's very
powerful in technology
um spark ul is the standard
query language uh based on you know
cement uh
data structures and ontologies and stuff
like that and vql is very similar to
spark ul but but it's coming from a
different community it's coming from the
the eclipse modeling community and it's
also a pattern-based language so this
particular rule that you have seen here
is was defined in the week well language
if you know there is interest i can talk
about this but maybe we should focus
more on the functionality so what we're
going to do now as part of this
demonstration is we are going to
redefine
uh this query which was written in the
sparkvue language and redefine it into
an elastic search or a losing
query to look for
let's say things in the system model
that
have the string data
and something which
begins with the word track
in in their value so this is what this
query is intended to mean you can run
such a query freely as you could say you
can really find it very easily and you
will get
results and these results again are you
know corresponding to particular hits in
the system model so you can run the full
text search on a system model
in this case it will give you a short
list of those elements which are hit to
this query and also show you why you
know it considers this is a hit this is
what is shown on the right side of this
table and again even from this interface
it's very easy to navigate first to the
model viewer
representation and from the model viewer
again you can go to the camera
collaborator or
if you have that project open in your
workspace too to canal systems modeler
directly
okay so this uh concludes uh let's say
the the first part of the demonstration
and if we have some more time i can also
show you how we can do the the quality
assurance across tool boundaries
in the context of jira and csml this is
also very similar
to what we've been doing with you know
genesis and e3 but with the combination
of different tools
and of course the three seed challenge
is also valid in this particular context
as well so
if i use jira
to to to
capture all the high-level requirements
that i need to process them further in
the systems engineering design it's
obviously very important capability that
i want to represent these requirements
i want to make sure that i get them all
so i have the correctness
the checkbox
i want to make sure that they are mapped
to correctly to properly type system
structure
and of course i also want to make sure
looking more inside on the system side
whether all the lower level requirements
which i may have added on the system
side whether they are properly traced
back to this high level requirements
so this is exactly what we are going to
create as a as a validation
configuration but what is an interesting
twist
here that in this case we are not going
to rely on a bridge tool to pull in the
requirements to the systems engineering
artifact and instead
we are going to use the native tools so
jira and magic draw to establish
traceability links
across these tool boundaries in a very
easy to use and lightweight way for the
purpose of using these traceability
links to power this completeness
correctness and and consistency analysis
so the question is how you create such
lightweight traceability links
and you can do this actually from both
directions right so uh if you want to
link uh let's say uh um
sysml uh you know issue to uh uh uh
i mean the jira issued a system model
you just have to essentially apply a
special stereotype
in your model
as well as add a tagged value and and of
course with the corresponding value
actually that will be a link
with the url
to the jira issue so this is one way of
establishing such a lightweight
connection the other way is the other
direction so what if i want to
establish a link from
jira into a seasonal artifact i can do
that one as well
very easily
uh hopefully i'm showing the right one
so you can actually
um
you know use the url as you see in your
address bar the browser address bar and
then put this url here on the jira site
like this like a simple copy paste okay
and after you are done with these
operations this link is established it
doesn't matter really from our point of
view whether you add the url to the
system model where you add the url to
the jira issue it's going to be a
logical link that is going to be used
for the purpose of across the analysis
and the cross domain assist in this
scenario is going to happen on other
kind of user interface of the model line
analyzer which is the jupiter framework
i don't know to what degree you are
familiar with jupiter it actually looks
like a browser-based
programming environment would there say
almost but it's actually more than a
programming environment because it's
actually a documentation
creation environment as well and the
documents that you create in jupiter
consist of documentation parts so
things that you can format as a document
and put in you know formatting and
hyperlinks and images and things like
this but you can also put in code
snippets originally in the python
language but now there is many more
so-called language kernels available for
jupiter so we have a python
we also use jupiter for the system lv2
pilot implementation yes yes so we
provide we provide an open source python
connectivity library for interacting
with the inquiry suite that you can very
easily embed in a jupyter notebook
and then using this final python
connectivity library you can actually
take advantage of the api functionality
that is exposed by the inquiry suite
right so typically how such an analysis
notebook looks like is that on the
beginning you have to set up the
connection to the inquiry suite so
locate the api endpoint and provide your
user credentials and things like this
and after this is done
then there are built-in widgets for
selecting the particular
let's say component of the digital
thread that you want to work with so the
workspace resource branch and revision
so in this case to select the forest
fire detection system
and once this is done then we can use
the again a built-in user interface
component for
configuring the so-called filter so we
are going to be using a package filter
in this particular scenario because we
only are interested in the connectivity
analysis in the context of one
particular package in the system model i
think this is a very frequently and
often used feature by systems engineers
because you're not interested in things
all over the model just in one
particular packaging on one particular
epic in this sense and all the rest of
the analysis notebook can be run fully
automatically
and this notebook is going to create an
interactively browseable html document
for you based on the forest fire
detection system that contains this
mapping information this corresponding
correspondence analysis information
between the jira
let's say part of the the knowledge
graph and the system part of the
knowledge graph so as you can see here
you can you have a list of um jira tasks
that are correctly mapped to the systems
engineering model
and you can also see a list of the jira
attacks which are unmapped to the
systems engineering model so this is the
fundamentals of the correctness analysis
things that you have already done and
things which are yet to be done of
course in jupiter you have access to
nice visualization and plotting
libraries that are able to generate
nicely looking diagrams as well this is
all accessible very easily from this
environment
and the these jupiter notebooks are
actually files themselves that can be
stored in a version control system like
a git repository
and we also have a connector
that allows you to process a jupiter
notebook like as a part of this digital
thread analysis and the knowledge graph
so you can actually turn this again on
on its head and use our analysis
capabilities to look inside the jupiter
uh
okay
so this is how
this is how the 3c analysis looks like
in this this environment
pretty powerful so we
we also filled up a whole hour with with
all this stuff that's amazing
great i have what questions so um
which role in an engineering project
will typically use your tool is it the
systems engineer the requirements
engineer the electrical engineer or is
there a special role that
the digital threat engineer that that
works with the inquiry suite
yes
all of them all of them but this role
this digital thread engineer in
many of the organizations that we work
with is called the model integrator i
don't know if you have ever heard this
term before maybe i'm i'm totally wrong
but but they are called integrators so
they are the ones who are actually
responsible for uh you know looking at
or consuming more like the work of of
other stakeholders in the process
systems engineers and other engineers
and making sure that
you know there is a there is a
consistency among the work of those
people and it is this person
who is i think the primary target
audience
of these more advanced features of the
the suite but of course as you could see
we also they were out of the box
validation logic that is i think very
useful to systems engineers
and
what i would like to emphasize again is
that all the tools that i have been
showing to you today are web based right
so they work fast
long fast
you can open up the tmt model or or a
model with millions of elements in your
browser in a matter of seconds
instead of you know having to go through
the
more traditional way of checking out
projects and opening them which can take
a lot longer so the the intention of us
with this kind of architecture is to
empower
the engineers and make these processes a
lot faster and a lot more you know
pleasant and easy to use
all right so you you have uh still other
stuff is fun because uh we are
pretty a little bit over time right now
no no this is this is this is all i
wanted to show okay great yeah and you
and you guys are at the end of your day
i still have meetings to go to oh that's
true yeah
uh how much are you ahead uh eight hours
nine hours
seven
seven okay
seven hours
all right
this happened during my lunch time
[Laughter]
yeah so it was extremely interesting
yeah
really really nice stuff that you
already
that you already can do and and we
already heard that you will do even more
in in
near future
and uh yeah maybe we should talk a
little bit uh
together uh outside of the
podcast because zuken and contact
software so my employer have a tight
relationship and
therefore maybe
this could be a good uh good good start
for it for another demo
could be could be i would definitely uh
appreciate that guys this was fun this
was a lot of fun
thank you guys for extending the
invitation and and having us here giving
us the opportunity absolutely um
hopefully as things get back to normal
we'll be able to do more than just
podcasts yes oh yes yes absolutely
if we are very lucky we see each other
in december yep yep at least i do have
to i do have to get on another call so
okay
to say goodbye
thank you so much okay thank you thank
you for having me thanks very much
thank you
thank you bye-bye
goodbye
okay so well that's it well then um
what's our next topic the next episode
is uh yeah surprise right the next
episode is still a surprise it will come
on december 1st
yeah but more we won't
won't tell you
[Laughter]
right and well then um do not forget
trust us we are systems engineers
goodbye
bye bye
thank you