Welcome to the 17th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
Today we take a look at the
modeling of parametric
The parametric diagram depicts
a network of constraints
that constrain properties of the system
If your modeling tool is able
to execute the parametrics
it could be an extremely
effective modeling approach
So, let's have a look at it in our model
First, we need the expressions
which are defined by constraint blocks
The lower constraint block specifies a
min max expression using three parameters
"minValue", "maxValue", and "value"
which are each typed by
our value type "Centimeter"
The constraint block
"TrunkStandConnectionConstraint"
verifies that the trunk
fits into the stand
It does not define a constraint
but owns a constraint property
typed by our min max constraint block
The parametric diagram is a special
kind of an internal block diagram
which depicts how parameters
of the constraints
are connected with other
parameters or value properties
The parametric diagram shows
the internal structure of the "Trunk"
then connect to constraint
which simply connects its parameters
with the appropriate internal
constraint parameters
of the min max constraint block
We defined a constraint property of type
"TrunkStandConnectionConstraint"
owned by our system to use this constraint
for the MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree
In a parametric diagram of
the TMPCT Base Architecture
we connect the parameters
of the constraint
with the appropriate
value properties of the system
The value properties already
have defined default values
however they could be redefined later
by the specialized properties
in the Physical Architecture
We also added another
interesting constraint property
which is the constraint block
"Height of The Tree"
which is a constraint block and
a requirement at the same time
since SysML1.5, any named model
element can also be a requirement
The requirement and constraint
block "Height of The Tree"
requires and verifies that
the height of the tree
is between 150 and 200 centimeters
The parametric diagram
of the system element
the MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree
shows how everything is connected
Our modeling tool can also
run the constraints
When we instantiate our
TMPCT system element
we see in the output that
constraints are satisfied
The tool then displays the
corresponding area in green
So much for the 17th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 17th of December
Goodbye
Bye-bye