welcome to the 17th door of our mdse
podcast advent calendar today we take a
look at the modeling of parametric
the parametric diagram depicts a network
of constraints that constrain properties
of the system
if your modeling tool is able to execute
the parametrics it could be an extremely
effective modeling approach
so let's have a look at it in our model
first we need the expressions which are
defined by constraint blocks the lower
constraint block specifies a min max
expression using three parameters min
value max value and value
which are each typed by our value type
centimeter
the constraint block trunk stand
connection constraint verifies that the
trunk fits into the stand it does not
define a constraint but owns a
constraint property typed by our min max
constraint block
the parametric diagram is a special kind
of an internal block diagram which
depicts how parameters of the
constraints are connected with other
parameters or value properties
the parametric diagram shows the
internal structure of the trunks then
connect to constraint
which simply connects its parameters
with the appropriate internal constraint
parameters of the min max constraint
block
we defined a constraint property of type
trunk stand connection constraint owned
by our system to use this constraint for
the mbse podcast christmas tree
in a parametric diagram of the tmpct
base architecture
we connect the parameters of the
constraint with the appropriate value
properties of the system the very
properties already have defined default
values however they could be redefined
later by the specialized properties in
the physical architecture
we also added another interesting
constraint property
which is the constraint block height of
the tree
which is a constraint block and a
requirement at the same time
since sysml 1.5 any named model element
can also be a requirement
the requirement and constraint block
height of the tree requires and verifies
that the height of the tree is between
150 and 200 centimeters
the parametric diagram of the system
element the mbse podcast christmas tree
shows how everything is connected
our modeling tool can also run the
constraints
when we instantiate our tmpct system
element we see in the output that
constraints are satisfied
the tool then displays the corresponding
area in green
so much for the 17th tour of our mbse
podcast advent calendar and we wish you
a great 17th of december
goodbye
bye