[Music]
hello and welcome to our new episode of
the mbse podcast
today we are talking about
and framework for the first time
and we are talking about the unified
architecture framework also known as omg
uaf
and therefore we have a guest
and i would say a friend
uh aurelius
so okay
nearly nearly perfect
but uh yeah our videos introduce
yourself and i guess you can pronounce
your name better than me
thank you christian uh hello everyone
hello tim uh
as
christian introduced my name is aurelius
markavichis
and i'm
working for the system as the expert on
mbsc and enterprise architectures and
also as a leader of experts a team of
experts in the mbsc and enterprise
architecture focusing on
sesame
and also uaf and nato architecture
framework
consulting and
teaching and expertise to our clients
and also probably more important to
mention in this context is
my work with the omg and
co-chairing
the uaf standard in omg for for more
than 10 years already
wow
wow that's a long time so
yeah so welcome already thanks for
joining us in our podcast um
yeah the uaf that's quite interesting um
let's start with the
um
with the framework of architecture
framework what what is it what what is
an architecture framework now is it is
it a is a method or a methodology and
how do you define architecture
frameworks
uh that's that's exactly a good question
is um
now it's really um called the
architecture description framework to be
very precise
according to iso 42010 this is kind of a
new thing for us as well
and and that really stands for some you
know uh best best practices um for for
some um structure
um which
allows you which gives you some some
basic background of how you um
create the the model of the system of
interest or
the enterprise really depend on what we
are talking about
but it not always include the
methodology behind it or or a method so
that can be a part
like looking into toga for example but
in some other frameworks it's it's it's
not the case
and
really this is this is the point where
uh i think i i wanted really to um
emphasize a little bit about the book
that
uh i wrote recently we think of the uk
that uh don't panic
um sirius which is the absolute
beginner's guide to the architecture
frameworks
so if you if you want to learn more
you're welcome to to look for it online
there is a book available and it has all
the explanation of all those
you know terminology things
all right okay so um
uaf like it's called today has a long
history and even
omg it was called updm before and
even there before there was some history
can you give us a brief introduction to
this
absolutely actually at the beginning it
was called updm the unified profile for
dodaf and modaf which initially uh has
been released in 2009
uh prior this
it's been it's been a long work to come
to this point but
basically the need was to unify the
department of defense architecture
frameworks and ministry of defense
architecture frameworks this uk and and
us
common military projects
later later on it evolved
but only in in 2017 we actually renamed
it to uaf
uh and and of course
why uif uh you can ask it's because we
we wanted to
commercialize it or sometimes we call it
demilitarize it
whatever you can you can look from both
sides
and
this was the idea of changing the name
because updm was very very uh related to
the military
background and
also in between the lines
the updm
also became an iso standard into 2017
and now we are working with uh iso to to
publish uaf uh version 1.1 and this this
should happen pretty soon because
the votes were we passed already and
it's just a question of uh
editing and publishing procedure and
then of course you know looking looking
further is
continue working on on the uaf and
specific focus
um
to the needs not only of defense clients
but also on the commercial clients that
we have
okay
so
well it's
based on modaf and dota or that's
part of their history
also mentioned togaf
and
there's another architectural framework
a military architecture framework called
enough
the nato architecture framework so is
there a relationship from uaf to togaf
and uaf to naf
uh
yeah actually at least with naf there is
a strong relationship and
we started with the release of the nato
architecture framework 4 which happened
a year ago
just probably a year before we started
close collaboration with the nato
architecture capability team
where where we had um
some some common meetings uh either them
coming to the omg meetings or we uh
going to the uh nato uh architecture
capability team meetings and uh
officially uaf is
one of the two meta models for nato
architecture uh version uh nato
architecture framework version four
the other being archimate uh and um
uh there is no
metamodel developed by the nato uh today
because it's it's really
um
a lot of resources demanding uh
endeavor and then they decided to go
with some standard
bodies like omg for example or the open
group
the relationship with togaf is um
is obviously not so clear it's it's not
clearly described in in any of the
specifications nor in uaf and either in
togaf
and and as they're really coming from
the very different worlds it's not not
so easy to connect and specifically
we're facing this within nato where we
have models produced in archimate which
is also the open group so it's similar
to
um to togaf um in in its um let's say
from the terminology point of view and
this is where we sometimes have a need
to be able to interchange these models
but
it's it's work in progress
i would say and at the moment there is
no clear
description of it where in some examples
people are taking uaf um and they are
using togaf architecture development
method
which provides steps of how to create
the architecture and and that this
happens because we didn't have one
uh the method in in uaf before and we
still don't but in the next version in
the in the 1.2 version coming out
next year we're going to introduce the
ua so-called uaf guide as the appendix
to the spec
which is the um kind of a method
approach how you go from you know a to z
in in creating the the uaf models
okay okay
and
uh chris everyone my question regarding
the military stuff uh
you said you uh removed the military
stuff from from
upgm which creates then uaf um so what
exactly did you do how how what should
what was removed from from the the
standard uh to exclude the military
stuff and at the same time it's uh
conformed to the the naf and and the
other stuff so
it's it's it's mainly about terminology
um the name itself like updm uh it talks
about dodaf and modaf so we just change
it to to the uaf um and then
some terminology some concepts that we
had like for example in in in in dodaf
world there is a concept of a node
is the same in modaf which represents
you know some structural block
uh in the operational scenario
uh we we
replaced it by the operational performer
which sound more um
let's say
universal right more genericized than
than the node
um some some other terminology
that that we also had like uh you know
doctrine doctrine
um and and and
it's basically basically basically
around that
but then we
solved
the traceability question by
creating
a additional
document
with the specification called the
traceability document and it has all the
mapping to the different frameworks
just to make the terminology clear
okay great
yeah and uh one thing that would be
interesting for me is
how did uaf or its predecessors become
an omg standard why why did military
come to omg
uh
yeah it's uh it's it's a it's a long
long story but um
it was really at that time there was a
big involvement of the uh
dod within omg
and and uh the big representation from
uh
big big names and um even even a dod cio
has been a common participant in in the
omg meetings
clearly expressing the need of
interchange uh and and this this was
where the idea of of updm started
strongly driven by the ibm at the
beginning uh later we had some some some
issues and conflicts between the
different group of groups of interest
um ibm even uh vetoed the first release
of the
of the uaf and uh that
a little bit uh you know um
postponed the release of the
specification of the uptm specification
but uh well nevertheless
later on the obstacle obstacles were
were gone we found an agreement and
there was the the
the updm released and
after that
as i said uh you know we we really got a
lot of requests from other industries as
well not not purely from the defense and
other frameworks like even in defense
like naf
which was not
a part of the updm at the beginning
with nato architecture framework and
later on we just had more frameworks to
incorporate
more frameworks to support more more uh
communities to to support
and and this is where the idea of
uaf um
came to our mind we we had to fight
strongly to get this name because you
know other
groups of interest especially coming for
from business architecture said no no
this is this cannot be unified you know
because we have different frameworks
from bpmn and other stuff
um but but finally we managed to to
register it so it's registered trademark
of omg and it's um
it's it's it's now said that it's for
multiple purposes right is for for
defense
for for uh industry and for for and also
for for uh federate uh federal
government
so it can be used for for different um
purposes and use cases can i also use it
for for enterprise modeling so for
enterprise architectures
or only for systems or products
we can with the uh of course we try to
talk about this this idea and we really
think that that the future of the
enterprise uh
architecture is really in uh what we
call um enterprise as a system
uh so so this is where
you know enterprise is just a complex
system or or even the system of systems
at some point depends how you look at it
and it can be analyzed
similar way as any kind of other system
it can be um you know
some of the things can be simulated
within the enterprise
and and it really lacks today more
precise description to be able to do
that if we look into today's
architecture frameworks it's
enterprise architecture
and how it's done in different
organizations it's really powerpoint and
and and and visio and
well sometimes togaf but
then what what togaf is if if you look
into togaf that there is meta model but
there is no formal way of um really you
know uh implementing that meta model so
so you can use uml or user
you can use you know bpmn or some other
language
but but that's that's not really
getting uh getting to to to the right
point where you have everything unified
and you can you know validate your model
simulate your models and this is where
we're we're going with uaf it's yes it's
coming from the different world it's
coming from the engineering world it's
much more precise uh and it means that
um even if the complexity is higher at
the end you can achieve
a better consistency um in in your
architectural uh description
and you create for the enterprise
okay
so
i'm
still not sure if our listeners
know what uif is and what you can do
with uif and
to my knowledge you are modeling
structures and behavior and missions and
something that
that has to be achieved and to my
knowledge you you use many other
standards can you give us a little bit
of insight to that
we do
so
first of all probably i would say that
uaf
has a couple of parts within the
specification one of the parts is the
conceptual meta model
which is um
based on on uml but it's not really you
know the implementation or the languages
it's just the conceptual metamodel
providing a number of
concepts and their relationships
and and how they're used and where they
supposed to be used but going further
there is
the standard implementation of the uaf
today it's called uaf profile and
tomorrow is going to be called
uaf modeling language
so so we're changing that to make it
more obvious and more aligned with sml
for example which is systems modeling
language
and
specifically uif modeling language is
based uh
as a profile of uml of course it's first
based on on the uml
but it's also based on sml with the
tight relationship to sml
and
we use systeml diagrams to represent
uaf data
um so at the end
you know it's it's strongly dependent on
on this sml
today because we don't define our
notation we use the system of standard
decimal notation we just define the
the the number of elements that you
would use within um sesame diagrams
uh then we have some dependency on bpmn
it's not exactly dependency it's more
it's more how you use both together
you can use bpmn
to be more precise the the profile
uml profile for bpmn which is a
different standard than bpmn
to express
process models so like operational
activity models or function models
uh security processes models and and so
on and there are some other standards
where we have some hooks too it's not
that we incorporate them uh or we use
them so we we have some relation to niem
which is national uh information
exchange
model or ieppv which i can hardly uh
spell
then the base profile
recently has been developed
so
base profile for uaf is really extending
uaf towards
supporting face standard that's here
airspace here for standard and then
possibly we will have some relationship
to a risk analysis and an assurance
modeling language
which is
upcoming standard
in the omg so so there are tight
relationships and of course for data
exchange it's it's xmi
uh
standard
okay so
and yeah you mentioned you have uh but
you have this this meter model of uaf
and system l
and i assume also b and n all this other
stuff is only
one possible implementation
of this beta model so theoretically i
could also use um
capella
for uaf
and and any other
systems modeling language uh like yeah
capella or uh or opm uh and maybe the
other around
uh this is that true so system is just
an implementation of the meter model
that's that's that's correct it's uh
it's just we call standard
implementation because we have a
published omg standard for that
okay
and of course it's much easier to use
the
system then creating your own modeling
language and then the tool vendors must
create their own tools and so on
um yeah speaking of tools um is url
bound to a specific tool but do i need a
uaf
tool uh
it's actually it's it's it's not too
specific so it's like a standard it's
too agnostic
i would say it's really um you know two
vendors are highly involved in
development of the standard um
so so for this
historically we we had and still have
many tool vendors attending
um and and um a lot of them are our
system well as we just discussed so so
there are some um
tool vendors coming from
different world
like like mega for example and mega opex
tool or or the system architect
which is also not sesame based
so there are there are examples and
as you said there might be different
different implementations of it
so so it's really not um
not dependent on the specific tool but
on the other side you know um
probably
tools that implement uaf specifically
and and they highlight that they
implement uif they provide um
slightly different experience towards
you know creating uaf models than
if you would do it without the specific
tool
okay but that means that a tool that
supports only so small would not be
enough
uh well definitely uh
probably not
theoretically it could could could be um
you could could use it for one or the
other view when you say okay i'm just
using uaf um grid which just have a list
of views that you need to create
and and then you create them in the
different
sesame diagrams but at the end to get
you know the full experience the the
metamodel compliance with the omg
standard
you you need you need to have um uaf uh
specific tool but at the end just adding
adding to this point you know what we
see sometimes in industry and not
necessarily in defense
that uh people take a small and and they
highly customize it
they highly customize it they extend it
and at the end they they come very close
to to what really uaf is today
what do we have what do we do in systems
engineering we do operational analysis
uh we do functional
architecture we do logical architecture
and you know this actually corresponds
to the to the views that that we have in
in the uaf
sometimes you know you need features you
need capabilities it depends on on which
which
industry you are
and and and those kind of concepts you
know are are also um something you you
extend
so sometimes you know you you you get
close to it just
over customizing system now
not not even knowing that you do that
so um so if but if i use a standard
system a tool um to to yeah apply uaf
um and also an um bpmn modeling tool to
apply uaf so the bpmn part of uaf
now i have two tools with two models uh
and i need some kind of exchange of data
and have this inter operability issue so
is there a standard exchange format for
uaf
models what data
the the standard exchange is is for a
sml implementation
only so if you are
you if you if you have uh you know small
if you if you implement uaf modeling
using qf modeling language which is
based on sml then you can use xmi to
interchange or diagram interchange
format which which is there by omg so
i'm not sure that there are tools really
implementing it but theoretically
theoretically should be
should be possible
using those standards but if you use
some proprietary implementation then
then you probably have to have some
exporter into the correct xmi format
okay
so
as uif is a huge framework
we cannot go into every detail today
but could you give us some example
aspects of views that are created or
covered by uaf
uh
yeah absolutely you know saying huge
it's uh it's probably the right word but
uh we used to say that when you when you
look into uaf for for some people you
know this this grid that we have reminds
us reminds the uh periodic table of
elements that we learn at school
um and and you know but you usually
don't use the all the elements there to
to to create um new composite material
you just take you know somewhat what you
need like hydrogen oxygen for the water
so so it's similar here we we just say
okay so it's like foundation giving you
everything and you just need to pick the
right things and primarily you know the
the core uh core viewpoints that we uh
have is the strategic operational and
resources
um where you know uh really represent
three different layers of abstraction
starting from one strategy and uh
answering question why
this is about you know capabilities and
their realization in time the strategy
from the enterprise
level how you go from one
state of the enterprise to the other
from one state of the system or system
of systems to the other
how that changed in terms of
capabilities in terms of features
really dependent um on on the goals you
have uh then then we go to the
operational scenarios to to to describe
um
also uh
what we need to do to achieve the goals
and
achieve the capabilities so the
operational scenarios are really related
to the environment to the user uh who's
using the the system of interest what
the the main players how they how they
communicate what are
the the process uh behind it
and and finally you know on
how we implement those operational
scenarios is where we talk about
resources and um
when we talk about resources we talk
about
people we talk about
software we talk about systems hardware
etc natural resources
so there are many different types of
resources that needs to collaborate
together
to to achieve the goals and you know we
sometimes take take an example if you
have um
if you model the missile and um you know
the missile system of interest for for
for for for some and it's been
um for the company that designs it right
uh but if we if we look from the uh
ministry of defense perspective for
example uh then you know they're buying
not only the missile but they need to
understand how they are going to use it
so they need the launch platform they
need some transportation how to move it
from one place to the other or some uh
if it's stationary some some place to
place it they need personnel to be able
to to be capable
to use it so they have to do training uh
they have to have some competencies and
all
these kind of things they can be they
can be captured and modeled and and that
usually goes just beyond the simple uh
you know system of interest
and of course there are some other other
um
viewpoints in addition like security
which quite important these days
you know to cyber security
in any industry it's it's not it's not
specifically a defense on um
some standards and and and services but
it's really about these three and and
how they how they um relate together and
traceability between them
so that's so to say uh the the
the default approach how to start with
your effort the the minimal
uif so to say i think at first glance it
seems for many people daunting and too
extensive but people also say the same
about assistant and human that's too
complex too much and
but they do not understand that it's
only a language
an offer and you don't have to pick
everything
and
uaf um is much much more like if you
open up publications about uaf it's
all these viewpoints and
so
your recommendation is then um if i do
not have a specific plan uh to start
with uif i start with these three major
viewpoints then right straight that's
exactly the case and then yeah okay yeah
that's exactly the case plus you know we
have those uh also columns that
represent different types of diagrams
different xsml that's that's called
pillars sometimes you know like
requirements structure behavior
so we have we have more of those and
then you you can also decide you know
which ones you you need to do so like uh
you know requirements structure behavior
they're usually
what you commonly do
when we go more towards constraints or
you know the
time aspect that's not
something you always do it just really
depends on
you know parametrics the same in small
you know
don't do parametrics all the time it's
just for some specific uh tasks
usually
it reminds me a bit of product line
engineering so i have a set of features
that i can use
and then i also have these uh
feature constraints so if i select this
feature i also have to select that
feature or if i select this feature i
cannot use this feature uh you have
similar constraints in uaf or a
guideline how how i can select the the
right features so at the end that i for
example still have a traceability in the
model which doesn't work if i remove
one important part of the chain
uh so so there is uh probably the uaf
guide that i mentioned that's coming
with the next release is the closest to
that where where we explain you know
every step in in more details what what
is it about and what you need to do and
which step follows the other and what
are the um impacts from one step towards
the other so there's going to be the
impact kind of impact map
for for for every viewpoint so so that's
probably the case but in general uh you
know when you say it's big
i think it's really trade-off because
sometimes if you take the pure
pure systema language and you over
customize it
it's really expensive
to maintain afterwards so maybe it's
better to take the bigger thing and just
cut it down
then to take the smaller and grow it
expand it towards your knees it's the
end of trade-off
and people somehow think about okay we
take simpler but at the end they they
have something like that
yeah speaking of susan l or tim do you
no
okay
yeah speaking of system l um
would
would system lv2 influence uif in some
reason so would you
would you change to system l2 and would
it
be
yeah
bring advantages which you don't have
right now
it would definitely influence heavily
it's just
the the question of time of how we
handle that
our current plan is to
have uaf we two
or faults y
compatible with the system lv2 um we we
would have a good match in numbers um
b2v2
um it would be clear what we're talking
about but
then then we need to think about how we
want to
to base uaf on smr2 because they can be
couple of different practices we can we
can take our conceptual meta model and
base it on the system our v2 and caramel
concepts
in in that case we would not
probably need the separate maintenance
of the implementation in the samal
and the other option is just to make
keep what we have and just add
additional uh
document to the spec which would be
implementation of uaf and the smlv2
um so we have to think carefully because
you know as is
they're not only small tools that that
implement uaf um and not not only some
other users so if we change the
conceptual meta model
uh for them uh that's that's the big
impact
because they have to move towards sml
where they're maybe more like business
kind of tools
uh business architecture kind of tools
and then for them that that gives
additional complexity on the other side
we also want to keep um
support for the system l1.x which we
believe will be at least for 10 years in
the future it will definitely be here
and many projects will will run on it so
we have to somehow keep this backwards
compatibility so at the same time we
have to maintain the implementation it's
a small we want
so it's really in considerations we have
to we have to think of how to how to
move forward
and and that's really you know the tough
work um ahead of us
yeah i think it's for example how to
maintain the the old version
for this movie one when you already have
the new version because according to the
omg policies if you have published the
new version the old version is not
not there anymore it's the same for
system lv2 as soon as it's officially
published there is no system lv1 anymore
so it's well it's not maintained anymore
but of course it's still there it was
published but it's not maintained
anymore no official specifications
it's complicated
plus in terms of a workload you know uh
like like with system we have
different teams working on
uh one.x right different people leading
the groups on one.x and on two um
so it's it's it's really you know the
big big scale you have to somehow manage
it
yeah yeah and i think
yeah and i think uh
when we are talking about a future uml
three i i really can't imagine that
omg says okay uml 2 is gone all our meta
model and and
whatever
uh things they are in uh until yeah
even until moth
yeah it's everything gone we have um
three now i can't imagine that one
and it's similar to this system
right yeah
yeah so you already mentioned that uaf
is stopped only for military projects i
can also use it for for other stuff
can you mention a few of them so what is
a typical use case for a company to use
uaf so i assume not for a normal system
so
what's yeah
i would i would say uif is a relatively
new standard just just look for how much
time it took to um really uh
you know
start using sesame which was first
introduced in 2007 right or 2006. um and
and and now we just see you know that
the heavy adoption in in industry uh and
for the first 10 years it was really
rarely
adopted just you know by some companies
with uaf um it's it's again
that the user base outside of defense is
not huge uh it's growing uh all the time
we we try to emphasize that uh one of
the things is the uaf group on linkedin
so i highly encourage uh for those who
are not on on on the group join it there
is community where publish
many many user stories
also you know the other area is the uaf
annual
summit which we started to do every year
in in march like probably five years ago
and we last year grew to 700
registrations
which almost like in cozy symposium
when it became virtual so that that's
pretty good attendance and we definitely
keep it to virtual or hybrid because you
know we we
think that it it's really uh pays off
and many people join
and and this is where we have you know
some stories to share um uh projects and
in the system of system engineering and
um infrastructure projects like electric
roads um
in sweden
there are some in in gas and oil
industry
um
electric grids
and then there are also you know even
if it's sometimes you know defense
industry but not specifically the
defense use case
so there are there are some on digital
transformation on the enterprise where
um
some companies find it
a useful tool like deloitte consulting
for example find uaf as a very useful
tool to do digital transformation of the
uh of their clients of the organizations
where you can define how you transform
the enterprise from one state to the
other and what resources are needed and
what processes are needed so that's
relatively easy it is
new new use case and and we did quite a
lot in the recent version to to improve
in this area um to define the drivers
for change the challenges we face
um the effects the outcomes such
concepts that we didn't have previously
in in the uaf and um that industry uh
wanted to have in terms of supporting
the the digital uh transformation topic
there are some also some some stories
from from automotive in this area
and we started some more collaboration
with the automotive uh and in
germany on um
uh autonomous mobility uh projects uh
within within the pro step
yeah so we we we hope we can um reach
achieve something uh in this direction
you know perhaps the specifically
adopted guidance
of the uaf and how you would use it so
so we're trying to to expand and to go
into
other directions uh
of course at the same time we still love
our um defense customers and we try to
do the best to them so i just don't want
to scare people
listen to this podcast yeah right
primarily still is still our industry
right so we we survive based on it that
the main people contributing are are
coming from a defense world
um but it it also you know i want to say
that we are looking towards you know
expanding horizons and
um towards the different ways of of of
using uaf
okay
all right so that means so
if i'm coming from a industry which is
not
defense and space um
i already learned i can join the
linkedin group um
can i also just
come to
to the omg meeting and participate or
how does it work absolutely absolutely
definitely you you can participate uh
you can join linkedin group you can
contact me or other members of of the
omg
group um
so yeah yeah we're open to communicate
great
okay
so well i think we are running out of
time
and we are running out of questions
not really though it's a huge topic so
we
could talk hours about it um absolutely
but we already covered a lot and
well so
yeah that's close
this episode
and
this time we already know the next topic
and the next date
next topic is again an episode in our
series about mbse tools
and we will have a look on the ink query
suite
from inquiry
labs i think it's the name of their
company and our guests are one of the
founders espana from that company
and they have a collaboration with zuken
and
yes
you know him very well he will also join
us so and uh the date is november 18th
um
i think it's a thursday or so and again
at 7 central european time
so yeah and well finally
do not forget
trust us
we are systems engineers
goodbye and thank you already for being
with us yeah thank you