Hello and welcome
Here for MBSE Podcast
Today we want to shortly explain
what we do here
and why we do it
Let me introduce myself
My name is Christian
I am a product manager
and consultant and team leader
for the team "Engineering Transformation"
at CONTACT Software
and I am an active member of INCOSE
Since 2015 I have joined the
OMG technical meetings
because I joined it from the beginning
because I join the SysML 2 standard
engineering activity
Since September 2008 I am under
other co-chair of the ManTIS DTF
that is
"Manufacturing Technology and
Information Systems Domain Task Force"
And who are you?
Hello, my name is Tim
I am a consultant trainer
and board member at oose
I am also a book author
editor, lecturer
And I am also an active
member of OMG and INCOSE
At OMG for a long time and currently
I'll follow up with it
And Airbus, the working group
I'm working on SysML 1
And I'm also working on
a team on SysML 2
What are we doing here?
We do MBSE Podcast
And the idea is
that we don't do another
explanatory video
and also books and articles
What is there
enough about MBSE?
Are there still any good
ways to contribute?
The idea is actually to bring out
the stories between the lines
which people also experience
at conferences during the breaks
or at the systems engineering
round table
We all want to do
that in this podcast
And we plan to invite guest
speakers here every time
who help us
What are the topics
of the podcast?
We have already considered it
You have already mentioned one topic
We will let our guest speakers play
We will also interview one
or the other exciting actors
I think we spontaneously invite guests
like Sandy Friedenthal or
Richard Soley or so
Of course, it is not limited
Many other organizations as well
Current events from the MBSE
when something new comes from INCOSE
Or something exciting
happens at GfSE
we want to talk about that
And of course very clearly
because we are very
close with the SysML
But do you actually
run such a podcast now?
That gives modeling
We have to show something
And we just show them
what it is also a video podcast
We are simply going to chat
And we simply publish the audio
track as an audio podcast
Most of the sessions
will be live stream
that is, the posts are then uncut
They are what they are
Authentic
We will start posts in German
We are both German native speakers
It is easier for us to start this way
But there are plenty of
exciting English guest speakers
And then we do this in English as well
Whether we will do in
German or English in the future
Let me consider it
For the future
A good keyword
How often do we do it?
That is an exciting question
because we both do it in our free time
We decided a very rough goal
We will release an episode
once a month
Maybe two
Maybe none
It depends on how we find time
and how the whole thing goes
down with you as a listener
if you show a lot of interest there
Probably it can be more often
But how can you follow us?
How can you catch the information
of any podcast episodes?
It is in the YouTube channel
You can subscribe to it
You can always get the information
You can subscribe to
the various podcast sources
And you can find all the information
about it on our website
http://mbse-podcast.rocks
Exactly
Right
So, how is that for today?
We just wanted to briefly announce
the whole thing to you
We wanted to introduce ourselves to you
And next time we have already
chosen a very exciting topic
we want to work up
the history of SysML
Tim can tell a lot because
Tim, how long have you worked for it?
Since the SysML 1.?
SysML 1.0
Because it started in 2003
Excellent!
That's all the better
It wasn't so clear to me at all
What learned
What learned again
Okay
We would like to do it if possible
on November 5th at 7 p.m.
live with you on YouTube
We would be very happy
about your participation
And we have still something to say
I remember it
"Trust us. We are System Engineers"