hello fellow systems engineers and
welcome back to a new episode of the
mbse podcast today we are launching
a new series and it's the
long awaited tool series
yeah we have a guest here
we have daniel siegel with us and we are
very happy to have him
in this episode we will talk a little
bit about the tool
and in the second half of this episode
we will
show a little bit from the tool we try
to
to make it also interesting just for our
listeners
but if you are interested how it looks
like just switch over to youtube
there you can look up the episode within
with the video and if you are
interested in even more uh daniel
surely will be happy to help you out
yeah but
daniel please introduce yourself
hi i'm daniel siegel i'm in charge of
business development at liber lieber
and i work with liberlieber since 2006
so it will be 15 years this year
and i sold my first together license
together who can remember the old uml
tool
around one around 2000
so it i have been around modeling for a
while
and something that always was a problem
with
modeling is how you work in teams
and this is what we're going to tackle
later i'm also involved in various
standardization groups like prostep i'm
in the standards department at the
incosi
i i follow the omg i do not actively
participate at the moment
and i try to be ahead of the curve when
it comes to systems engineering
great yeah welcome daniel good
but you're here in our podcast um
yeah well uh many of course think of
enterprise architect
and i often hear from people that they
think that libra libra is also the
developer and vendor of enterprise
architects so what's the relationship
between
libra libre and the system it will
enterprise architect
uh if you are nice to us you can buy
from us but we we are not the producers
of
enterprise architect enterprise
architect is done by
spark systems in australia it's
developed in australia
they have a team in australia that does
all all the development of the core
product of enterprise architect
our owner peter lieber became
distributed for the for europe
of enterprise architect around 2004 or
and he has a company called spark system
central europe that is the distribution
arm of
of of sparks in europe so we have a very
good connection
uh peter lieber owns both companies but
it's independent
in a commercial sense from the
australian producer of the tool
okay but the tool we want to talk about
today
is a lemon tree and lemon tree is
originally
your tool right lemon tree is a tool
that is a commercialization from
university projects
so when you look back at the very first
that looked into model versioning it's
almost 15 years now
so just to give you an overview how much
stamina you need
to make it from the first university
research project
uh to an established product in the
market it can be
really a long process and
lemon tree is fully our product it's
developed in-house
and um in the the very early days it
was called model version but in 2016 or
so
when we really went to the market we
we came to this name lemon tree because
it's fresh
and versioning is a lot to do with trees
so this is the idea behind the name at
the moment we have the funny situation
that we are at
we have our current version is three and
lemon tree
three sounds a bit much but that's where
we are at the moment
okay i never got the idea of of
versioning trees okay that's interesting
but yeah it's logical to some extent and
maybe from a dna perspective it's
important
to understand how how our guys
how how we think what is the dna of our
company
we try always to reuse existing proven
stuff
and lemon tree fills the gap between the
established processes
uh from software engineering and the
modeling world
so uh yeah why do i not need
lavender if i have a system l tool like
enterprise architecture or actually
whatever
um i expect that i can do some
versioning and most tools provide some
kind of versioning
so why do i need lemon trees generally
most tools uh provide versioning
uh but there is a pattern that is called
a pessimistic version control
uh which if you tell to software
developers they have to do pessimistic
version control
uh they will send you to a technical
museum
but in modeling it's kind of
state-of-the-art steel
pessimistic version control means i need
to lock
the parts of the model that i want to
modify
and then i can return it back and
after that i have to uh call my
colleague by the phone the model is free
now you can use it and all of this stuff
and i have to ask a guy can you unlock
the part of the model the package i need
to modify it
you have it locked it's cumbersome
process
and with lemon tree you get
the capability due to optimistic version
control
optimistic version control means uh two
people can modify the model
independently if they check in after
each other
uh there is a conflict which is not
something bad it's a normal
normal step in the process and
a conflict requires a merge and
in the case of lemon tree if you use it
with the version control system
lemon tree tries to do the merge
automatically
if there is a conflict where the two
guys worked on the same elements it will
show the user interface
and um give you the option to make
educated uh changes and decide what you
want to bring into the final model
and this is a key benefit because for
all the
modern version control systems like git
you need optimistic version control
capabilities
because they're decentralized there is
no place where you can lock it
and so you need merging capabilities if
you want to do mbse
with kit and this is basically our
global usb at the moment
that enterprise architecture is lemon
tree is the only commercial modeling
solution
where you can use git
does that also mean that
i can somehow arrange
access control in some ways so that i
say i have a
military project for example and certain
people are
should be able to see one part of the
model but not the other one
how would i do that so there is two
things to this story
again our dna
we don't care about access control it's
the job of the version control system
if you use a version control system
where you can
access control the model good if you
have a
free version of git where you can't okay
that's none of our business but with
lemon 3
we have additional set of features where
we can slice
models so you can take out the part a
part of the model
put it in a new model and with this
slicing you can
have a very good way to deliver
stuff to a supplier that shouldn't see
the full car
but only his domain the door for example
if you want the power window you only
send him the
the part of the model that is the
relevant for him
and this is something where we again
with
the new capabilities in lemon tree 3
where we're ahead of the curve
a bit because we have a very good
placeholder handling to reintegrate
after that
okay
i will cover a topic which uh daniel
already
um mentioned right now
so speaking of cars and and automotive
uh industry um i
i know that automotive industry is
heavily interested in mbse because all
of uh yeah of the complexity within
uh electric electronics and software
which
is coming more and more into cars and
all the
safety critical things so
um as i know they
have to to give proof that everything is
all right
and does lementry somehow
help them out in in these cases
the norms are our best salesmen in
reality
if you look at the norms like the iso
it's clearly stated that you should have
all your development artifacts
in a proper version control system so
the big benefit is if you use a
server-based
uh solution from your modeling tool
vendor
you have to go all the steps in the
audits to prove it works right
if you show up with ptc lifecycle
manager
or even svn everybody knows the process
processes around it uh to make it
workable
uh for safety critical norms and this is
one of our key benefits
uh we and uh very interestingly
that the users want you they have lemon
tree and they have these capabilities
they very quickly find out that the best
way to do mbse
is using git flow git flow is a process
from software engineering that's based
on feature branches
so if i tell you to develop a model for
a new feature in my car
for example a new park distance control
you create a feature branch uh you
develop the
the new feature in the model and
whenever you are ready and the project
says yes
we can use this feature now uh you use
lemon tree to merge the branches back
together
so with this pattern you have less
conflicts you have a very good point in
the process
where you can do a review help each
other and so on
so this is really handy and easy to use
because it's well established in the
software engineering department
so if i understand it correctly lamentry
is
based on git right and
no no okay so
we have to uh this uh make a
differentiation a little bit
the classic lemon tree is like beyond
compare for enterprise architect models
so uh it doesn't matter which version
control system you use
uh lemon 3 is just a diff and merge tool
for the model data i can show it later
with csvn i can show it with kit we have
very successful
deployments on on on
ptc live cycle manager but obviously git
is the most established at the moment
and
the best support for processes like
feature
branch development okay so
uh you do the merge not git but
because git can also do a merge but uh
for for the model merge
that's the task of lemon shape yes and
and model merge is well
uh git can merge text files or source
code files
uh and that works very well but watching
a model is a little bit more
sophisticated
um i have the model and you also have
this diagram level
uh and i remember some i don't remember
exactly which tool it was but
you get lots of windows on the screen
and it shows the differences in the data
structure and shows the differences in
the layout you moved a box from
a few pixels to the left and things like
that so how
do you resolve that so so the challenge
of the model is that is the graph
if you version the model uh with xmi
files for example uh your text based
diff tools
uh show nonsense it's not usable you
will not find a guy that tried
and succeeded on a larger model how to
merge it in the text based serialization
so what lemon tree does it builds uh
the the uml or system l model in memory
uh in in a proper graph style way
compares those and and also has
capabilities to show the diagrams
we can even merge diagrams to some
extent
and yes we have several thousand people
on the planet using it
so we have nice stuff like filters
that are called height graphical changes
so i can use a filter and i will not see
the diagrams where just boxes
were moved around for example so
it's really uh with all these years that
we focused on this topic
i think from the usability perspective
we are pretty good but it's a complex
task
and we always try to become better but
yeah that's where we at
yeah so maybe not all of our listeners
are
so familiar with git and what it means
with branching and merging
and maybe we should point out why it
does make sense to do it this way and
not
saving several models or in different
versions on the network share for
example
basically if you if you if you are back
to the safety critical example if you
have a routine how to save it in
sharepoint or on the file system
you have to make sure that you have all
the documentation in place how the
process works
if you let this if you are lazy as i say
and you use a version control system to
do it
it's an established codes tool and it's
rather easy
to prove that what you're doing is the
right thing to do
and you will not lose information and so
on and if you put on top
uh a process or a or a pattern to use it
like i mentioned before git flow
that is very successful in mbsc
it even gets easier
[Music]
i remember that your conference talk and
some publications
you mentioned lemon tree together with
variant management so
what okay this is a good one yeah
what's the relationship between both
so so the the the
the one of the basic stories is uh that
we do not believe uh to some extent that
no
christian is a from a plm vendor they
might have a different view
we don't believe that for uml and html
models
uh this um having this 150 percent
are survivable in an others context for
example
or in an aerospace context because the
models get too complex
and it's basically the same old if they
fell
they had in c source code and it's our
merging capabilities
uh we feel there is better approaches uh
to have 100 percent models
that live in branches and do the variant
management this way
with our new capabilities that we
introduced with lemon 3
we now have the capability to update
only
parts of the model so what we can have
now is you can have
a volkswagen model in one branch a
daimler model in the other branch
and you have a platform branch now if
the platform is upgraded to version 2.0
you can still work with version 1.1
in the volkswagen with the and the
daimler
in 1.2 and if you feel like it you can
update any of those two projects
to the new version when you're ready to
do so
and this is our approach it's again
established from stuff like nuget or
maven package manager for software
components it's the same
rationale behind it and uh this is our
our approach for this topic so
simple workflows then i i start with the
common thing so i model
an engine for example and then i create
a branch for
for a diesel engine and another branch
for a gasoline engine
yes and then i if i decide now i would
like to
if they share the same motor block you
can have the motor block component and
update only the motor block component
okay and that's an interesting approach
and and so again it's vr
software engineers it's our dna and and
we
think we have a solution now that
um is similar to what is established in
software
and this is this maven or nougat where
you have a
library of your components and they can
and you can instantiate them in your
projects
with set version numbers you don't have
to update everything
in a 150 percent model if you have the
diameter and the volkswagen project
in the same model it gets super messy
if i need the old controller in the
diameter project and the new one the
volkswagen project
with all the links uh the graph in the
model has
you get the super complex model and the
minute
maintainability down the road is a
catastrophic
scenario from my point of view this
might be a bit better for plm data
but for but but this but but this is
again you know we we use what we learned
from software engineering and
and uh made it available for mbse
yeah yeah yeah i think in plm it's a
little bit of a different view on
on what our model is and how a model can
be built up
out of different models so you
have similar similarities in in
opportunities and problems with hundred
and fifty percent models so
even if you think of a 150 cat model
um you need to do a lot of work and you
need to
have a very good mechanical cad
engineering process that you
can configure a 100 percent 3d model
which is a totally different view when
you are
looking on the on the parts level
and i have seen the 150 percent approach
uh used successfully for the platform
model
but what they do they instantiate the
project
model with these other commercial tools
that can handle this in this case pure
variants
and then they run the the instances
again in git with lemon tree so they
basically
just use it to
to give birth to the model yeah like a
model configurator
and after that the model again runs its
life cycle
inversion control is a 100 more
yeah and this is something we have to
talk about in
in another episode about variant
management definitely because it's
different different thing and we really
have to separate
the knowledge about your your variation
space
and the configuration of one specific
thing out of this possibility space
and this is very often the case that
people mix that up
and and i think we should uh focus again
today it's more version control
uh revision management and so on but
but obviously yes you end up in this
space
you end up in this space and also
interesting thing is always when you
work with systems engineers
and you bring tools that have names that
they heard from software engineering
and they sometimes panic
yeah one example from code engineering
is if you tell them to type in
c as a action language they they cry
if they you tell them to type in arf
they say oh that's a system engineering
language
in reality they write an equation a is b
plus c and it doesn't matter if it's
javascript
c or or arf
and a similar thing can happen with this
version control systems
so i think uh when you introduce a
process like feature-based branching and
so on
uh we do some stuff to make it easier
and you also have to have a biannus in
the nbc
team or or the guys drive such an
initiative
that you have to take care of the people
and take them with you and not leave
them behind you
uh you said i can use lavendry together
with enterprise architect
so enterprise architect can do system l
models but can also use uml bpmn
and many other things it work with all
of these
models yes it works with all of these
models
there's rare cases with weird
shape scripts but sometimes the diagrams
look not 100
right but all elements and all
connectors are on the diagram
and it supports even the profiling
mechanism of enterprise architect
and uh you just gave me a nice
word to continue and uh lemon tree is
now also available for openmbe
so it's not just the enterprise
architect
that's that's great that's awesome
another episode
yes uh great um but if you're
independent of
uh so oh no what i would like to ask
your your merch algorithm is independent
of
system for example it does not know that
i now
merge a block and another block or
something
it's a graph merge tool yeah i see but
but
look think about it as a graph merge
tool
but for uh some special
things like sequence diagrams there is
something like a profile in place
some special handling and try to keep it
as general as possible
uh but then you at that in the real
world sometimes you have stuff like
sequence diagrams or
maybe some special things in state
machines where there's some special
logic for a specific type
but generally we try to make it as
universal as possible
yeah looking to the fact how you
version the models and and what you have
in the background or you can support in
the background
it reminds me of the system lv2 api
which also handles commits and change
sets
and branches so
could i use uh lemon tree
later on also with system lv2 within the
system lv2 api uh if you
look at the people driving openmb
and driving the system v2 you will see
that there is no conflict it's the same
people basically
and this is one of the reasons why we
decided uh
to go that route and and bring open mbe
as our second uh modeling platform we
support
in the boat because we believe
uh if the ssml v2 takes off
including the api uh we are in a very
strong position
uh to adapt quickly
again what i don't like about the openmb
about this
system lv2 api approach is
that again we start building
back ends for stuff that is already done
there's a lot
what do you mean it's already done i
mean
uh this is what i explained early on
already our dna is to
reuse what's existing and and uh
for example if i'm if i'm a customer and
i'm not happy with subversion
i can switch to git in in three days
and lemon tree and enterprise architect
and everything will still work
with the system lb2 we will have uh
backends that will do something in
databases
maybe in databases nobody ever heard of
in europe
and it will be hard to maintain and run
i prefer to have the data in a
in a format that is easy to run where i
have
choice of vendors and and this is
why i like the version control a lot we
will see when the commercial solutions
for the system lv2 back ends come out
how well uh our part dispersion
management works
but we will build a solution that can
work with or without
yeah okay yeah
uh talking of the tool uh why don't you
show us the tool
one second so
screen share so
as i said before we try to make it easy
for systems engineers to
understand tour so what we have in lemon
in enterprise architect
we have an add-in and you can forget do
some
basic git operations directly from
enterprise architect
so in the in for users that just use it
you don't have to do a big git training
they can
they have five commands and that's
typically enough we developed this
together with an american defense
contractor
that said our systems engineer uh cry
if they have to use software tools this
works really really well
and uh the best feature is here that you
can set your
see your your branches and you can
directly switch between the branches
and this is maybe if if you go to the
git world
you shall not be afraid of branches
branches are not bad
they are your friend
when the second example i want to show
is something
that is really my nightmare uh
when i have a project a model and
my boss comes and tells me can you tell
me
what we changed in june 2018
and uh when you have a bunch of xmi
files you need a lot of time and have
only a certain probability
of the changes you report to your boss
so what i do here
i choose two versions of the model that
are three years old from june
2018 i right click
in the version control tool i choose
compare revisions
because lemon tree was entered as a div
merge tool for
enterprise architect models uh lemon
tree shows up
and uh diffs the models
and it's a matter of a few minutes on a
bigger model in this small model it went
really fast
and we can immediately see green
means changed we can immediately see my
colleague introduced the state
2 in 2018.
if you have a bunch of xmi files we have
all done it
you work three three four hours
and have only a certain probability that
what you report this what
what what was the reality in the past
and with this integration with the
version control system you have
really a good foothold and you have a
lot of confidence that
this is the change he did
yeah that's great and
if this is a small model you mentioned
larger models takes a little bit longer
so
yeah how large can a model be for
elementary
we have we have one customer that has
up to 300 000 model changes
when he runs lemon tree well
uh we survived the tmt model in oakman b
okay that's the third telescope
okay yeah so
and we can split it you know because of
our merge technology and the new
new model slicing we introduced we can
split them all if required
in a good way and yeah
the next thing i want to show is lemon
tree can also be used as a desktop tool
you simply start it and uh
it's a three-way diff tool and this is
maybe
very important if you don't have the
common base
you cannot really defect conflicts if
the order decides
if something was added or removed if you
have the common base you can do
proper comparison in software
engineering this is state of the art for
decades
in the modeling world it is not and this
is one of the key things why
lemon tree is so powerful now i click on
merge
this is a little bit bigger model and
so generally speaking lemon tree reacts
very well if you have nice hardware
we recommend 16 gigabytes of ram and a
modern modern cpu you can see here now
we have two conflicts it's highlighted
in red i click on it a filter is applied
and the conflicts
are seen and i can click on this and i
can
now see for those that don't see my
screen
that i have an operation in
where one guy changed display set line
to one
and the other guy changed display set
line to two
and the original was set line zero and
now i can decide
in a graphical way which one i want to
use
in the merge result and this is
the simple the simple solution because
you mentioned it before i have to show
it
we have a specific filter height
graphical changes on diagrams
especially developed for christian
and then you only see diagrams where
stuff really stuff happened and not
just boxes moved around and the last
thing i want to show in my demo is
that we also can do a graphical merge on
a diagram
uh what the viewers see now is an
activity diagram
and uh in one version uh the shutdown
activity was introduced
uh my version doesn't have it obviously
i win
so i choose the shutdown in the in the
in the diagram i can select the element
in the diagram
and i decide to use the version from b
without the shutdown where the shutdown
is deleted
uh lemon3 live has a has a live
merge preview for the diagram and we can
see the shutdown is gone
and there is currently no connector to
the activity final
i can click on the connect to the
activity final
and say ah we need you and it's here
and i'm done merging a diagram in a
graphical way
and i think this is a very good example
that shows that
if you know your model in your model
authoring tool
you will also know your model in ea
in lemon tree and this is the key
success
factor i see with the lemon rework style
that
it's still the model you have a you have
a containment tree or a project browser
view you have diagrams and you can see
all your properties including packed
values and whatnot
and does lamentry do the diagram
rendering or do you use
then center first architect or another
modeling tool that renders it
uh it depends uh for enterprise
architect we render the diagrams
ourselves
for other tools uh this might not be
true
okay and is it an auto layout or is it
exactly the layout
it's a very close representation
you would be happy if you had the same
quality
of rendering uh in if you do model
exchange between two models
it's very close
yeah this was the demo i don't want to
make it too long for the pure listeners
is there any questions that arose
uh i will have a look in the live chat
no
at the moment no question but i'm
pretty sure they will come afterwards so
most of our viewers and listeners are
viewing and listening to the podcast and
not live but
later on and i'm sure there will come
something
we will we will set up
video marks so that you can
navigate very quickly here in this
youtube video
to the demo piece and
i would say it's valuable to all
also see the demo and not just
hearing what daniel explained
yeah so that's the best daniel if the
people would like to contact you
should we post your linkedin you can
post your linkedin or simply write to
welcome
liberlieber.com but feel free to also
post my linkedin
welcome is your email address now
somebody takes
if you're sent to welcome somebody takes
care that they really answer
okay very
good yeah and in addition we can post
your linkedin profile on our website
absolutely we'll do that it's not there
yet but we will do that
yeah perfect okay yeah but there's one
last question that
arose in in my mind uh when we are
speaking of
versioning at some point in time we are
done with versioning we
want to release the model is there
something
similar like attack and git which
yes exactly you simply there is
not something similar again lazy us have
not developed something special
we use the features that are available
all right create the get intake create
the tag in
git easy
solution absolutely
tim any more questions
for daniel no not
on our current flight level if you go
further below i think i have many
questions
it's very interesting so in particular
when i start playing around with lemon
tree and so
it's a very cool tool but not for now no
okay so i think
we are already in the end of our
episode and uh thank you very much
daniel
for your time for the demo for the
information
um i think it's a topic which
yeah which is for everybody who is
modeling and
uh so from my experience many people
yeah do do not really think about how
how collaboration and versioning within
the team
could look like and could be better than
they use it today
i guess
yeah now our next topic well it's not
decided yet
um christian and i we have lots and lots
of ideas
um but have not started contacting the
people
but we will do that very soon and then
inform you about the topic and the date
on all our social media channels
um and if you have a topic well you said
well it would be really cool if they do
this and that
then well send us a message on linkedin
facebook twitter whatever
directly at our email addresses and
well we will consider it i have a
closing remark which might need
a lead to a topic in the future
i think that if you pretend or say
you do hlm bsc you better make sure you
can merge your models
yeah the point agile mbse is also a
topic on our list
that's worth many episodes this is the
only one
yeah interesting yeah
okay so question
what's refined i would say do not forget
trust us we are systems engineers