Welcome to the 21st door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
Today we take a look at
the death of the actors
That doesn't sound very Christmassy
But we definitely need to talk about it
The actors died a long time ago
Curious?
Let's have a look in our model
Our system context diagram
clearly shows actors
So, who is that here?
Therefore, we need to distinguish
between the concept actor
from the SysML element actor
The model element is that
or rather we bury it
Why?
Let's take a closer look
So, the concept of actor is great
External entities interacting
with the system and so on
with all the methodological
variants that exist
The SysML model element
actor is problematic
It comes from UML and is
there defined in such a way
that an actor may not have
any ports, receptions, operations
attributes, or parts
But these features are
needed now and then
For example, our actor
"power Supply" has a port
or our actor "room" has
a part named "floor"
So if we just claimed that a SysML actor
can't have that why could we model that
Well
Because we did not use the SysML
actor as mentioned at the beginning
The actor is dead respectively
non-existent for us
Formally our actor kinds
from the SYSMOD profile
are stereotypes specializing
the SysML block
So, the stereotypes define the
appropriate actor semantics
By the way, this is not a
nasty work around
but formally mapped correctly
even the SysML specification uses
this kind of actor modeling
in its hybrid SUV model
Thus actors have the
same capability as block
and can have ports, internal
structures, and so on
So, we have by no means trash
the concept of the actor
but the SysML model element
The actor is dead
long live the actor
So much for the 21st door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 21st of December
Bye-bye
Goodbye