welcome to the 21st store of our embassy
podcast advent calendar today we take a
look at the death of the actors
that doesn't sound very christmassy but
we definitely need to talk about it
the actors died a long time ago curious
let's have a look in our model
our system context diagram clearly shows
actors so who is that here
therefore we need to distinguish between
the concept actor from the system l
element actor
the model element is that or rather we
bury it
why
let's take a closer look
so the concept of actor is great
external entities interacting with the
system and so on with all the
methodological variants that exist
the sosumel model element actor is
problematic
it comes from uml and is there defined
in such a way that an actor may not have
acne parts receptions operations
attributes or parts
but these features are needed now and
then for example our actual power supply
has a port or our actual room has a part
named floor
so if we just claimed that a small actor
can't have that why could we model that
well
because we did not use the system
electro as mentioned at the beginning
the actor is dead respectively
non-existent for us
formally our actor kinds from the sisma
profile are stereotypes specializing
this isn't a block
so the stereotypes define the
appropriate actor semantics
by the way this is not a nasty work
around but formally mapped correctly
even the ssml specification uses this
kind of acta modeling in its hybrid suv
model
thus actors have the same capability
cities as blocks and can have ports
internal structures and so on
so we have by no means trash the concept
of the actor but the sesame model
element
the actor is dead
long live the actor
so much for the 21st door of our embassy
podcast advent calendar and we wish you
a great 21st of december bye-bye goodbye