Welcome to the 9th door of the
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
This time we take a look at
the State Machines
Here we use a State Machine to specify
the top level states of our system
And with that the pre and post
conditions of the Use Cases
This State Machine is
owned by the system element
So, let's look at it in the model
The State Machine considers four
states of the Christmas tree
which are "Packed", "Ready to use"
"Operation" and "Disposed"
Do you remember the triggers
of our Use Cases?
We specified a textual trigger
as well as a formal signal model
element for the trigger
The Use Case trigger signals trigger
the transitions in our State Machine
The Use Case Activities are
the effect of the transitions
or internal behaviors of the states
The special learning surprise
you cannot directly set the
Use Case Activity on a transition
or a state because they
must own the activity
however the Use Case Activity is
already owned by the Use Case
The trick is to define an activity with
a single call behavior action
which calls the Use Case Activity
for example, the effect of the
do behavior of the operation state
we find that in this region
there's the operation state and inside
the operation state is the activity
The activity does not need
an initial or final node
It is sufficient to just model
the call behavior action
So much for the 9th store of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 9th of December
Bye-bye
Goodbye