welcome to the ninth door of the mbse
podcast advent calendar
this time we take a look at the state
machines
here we use a state machine to specify
the top level states of our system
and with that the pre and post
conditions of the use cases this state
machine is owned by the system element
so let's look at it in the model
the state machine considers four states
of the christmas tree which are packed
ready to use operation and disposed
do you remember the triggers of our use
cases
we specified a textual trigger as well
as a formal signal model element for the
trigger
the use case trigger signals triggers
the transitions in our state machine
the use case activities are the effect
of the transitions or internal behaviors
of the states
the special learning surprise you cannot
directly set the use case activity on a
transition or a state because they must
own the activity however the use case
activity is already owned by the use
case
the trick is to define an activity with
a single call behavior action which
calls the use case activity
for example the effect of the do
behavior of the operation state
we find that in this region
there's the operation state and inside
the operation state
is the activity
the activity does not need an initial or
final note it is sufficient to just
model the call behavior action
so much for the ninth store of our mdse
podcast i met calendar and we wish you a
great night for december
bye-bye goodbye