[Music]
so
hello welcome to a new episode of our
mbsd podcast
the interoperability of engineering
tools is well it's really a hot topic
now we want to break up the data silos
where the data of the tools is often
hidden
and there's hardly any engineering
project that does not have this as a
challenge
a good reason for us to look at the data
integration standard oslc and our guest
axelrify the ceo of connexus a company
that is all about linking data
so axel welcome and please introduce
yourself
hello tim thank you very much for the
invitation so my name is axel reichwein
uh i'm originally an aerospace engineer
i studied at the university of stuttgart
and towards the end of my studies i was
lucky to be able to work on more exotic
topics
exotic from the perspective of aerospace
engineering
so i worked on
neural net neural networks
reinforcement learning
and also then in 2005 i looked at the
system's modern language
and at that time no
you know i think i was among the first
to really
discover this and i was very passionate
about this i managed to convince my phd
advisor dr stefan rudolph
that i should work with it
and
but systeml was still evolving so i
decided during my phd thesis to work
with a unified modern language which
shares a lot of concepts with the
systems modeling language
and then
a professor at georgia tech dr chris
paredes
he invited me to do a postdoc at georgia
tech where i could continue what i was
doing
but with the system's only language
and i'll i'll quickly say what i was
doing bring my phd and my postdoc
i was actually trying to find out
what would be a good system architecture
modeling language
to describe
dependencies between engineering models
so i was looking at the systems modeling
language or the unified modeling
language
not just to describe a system at an
abstract level but to capture all these
dependencies that exist between the more
detailed discipline specific models such
as between a
simulation model and a 3d model
and
or among different simulation models and
the idea was that
in order to
perform trade-off studies
we would just need to reconfigure the
system model and then that these changes
would be reflected automatically to the
more uh domain specific models
um
and um
so i looked into that for quite a few
years
then in 2012 i stopped my post doc
and roger borchardt
who was working at john deere
gave me the opportunity as a as a
consultant
to
work on a project that required oslc
and so i had to learn what what oslc
means uh what open services for
lifecycle collaboration stands for
and and since then i've been you know
very passionate about it and uh yeah
that's my brief history
okay
very interesting
uh yeah excellent also from my side very
warm welcome nice to have you here nice
to see you after all these years
uh we met sometimes but uh yeah in the
last two years yeah we had contact uh
in in in the word sense um we will talk
about that later on and
um yeah
like tim already said we are talking
about oslc we are talking about data
integration and um
maybe one more question ahead of all so
what is the main difference for you
between data integration and data
exchange so what makes oslc special
yes that's a good question so
i often hear the keyword
interoperability
and then i think of data exchange
between two different applications
so
where one application exports data
and that is then imported by the other
application
and this exchange of data is without
information loss ideally
and this is what i understand as
interoperability between applications
and this has been performed for
decades now we've got all kinds of
data exchange formats
there are still ongoing efforts of
course to improve them
but
it's there's a big difference i think
between interoperability
and connectivity
so
you mentioned data integration
just like data interoperability i think
i i
i think of data exchange
and um
and you mentioned data integration then
i think of data connectivity
and
it's really i think right now
important
to not just copy data around across
applications yeah i think this is the
main difference yeah yeah exactly that
that's sometimes it is necessary
especially i think in mechanical
engineering where
you need really to know the center of
gravity in multiple different simulation
models we need to copy the value to
synchronize the value
across multiple models so that they can
run and provide meaningful results but
many engineering artifacts
just need to be logically connected to
to other artifacts such as a requirement
it's it's not
useful to copy a requirements around
across different applications ideally
you define it in one application
and then you want to describe the
context of this requirement and say well
it has been tested by this test case
this test case was using this simulation
model which created this simulation
result
that kind of
connectivity
across engineering artifacts
possibly across different product life
cycle phases
this is what i call data integration
and we have many data integration
solutions
but
we've got plm alm mbse solutions
but they're not yet
i would say they offered some level of
connectivity
but not yet this complete level of
connectivity at the global level in a
tool agnostic way which oslc supports
okay so also c is a data integration
standard so can you give us an overview
of oclc
so um to be more specific oslc is a set
of standards
for an application programming interface
so
uh imagine all these different data
sources applications and databases in
engineering
and in order to be able to create these
cross-domain links so these links that
cross the boundaries of applications or
domains
we we cannot rely on the existing apis
we need apis that offer a bit more
freedom to create these cross-domain
links
and
these interfaces to all these different
data sources need to be standardized
standardized in order to support the
linking of data
and this is so
yes you can say oslt is a data
integration standard but you can also
more simply view it as an api standard
which helps the creation of links
um and
and and when you think of apis you often
think that the api clients
are programs
and that these oslt apis are only useful
possibly for
for
developers writing some code against
that oslt api but the oslc apis also
expose
dialogues meant to be consumed by humans
so that we can easily
embed certain things
let's
easily embed search dialogues in other
applications
so an oslt api is yeah um
um
supports the linking but not just at the
code level but also at the more
user-friendly graphical level
did you mention it's uh
specific to engineering or is it
could it be independent of engineering
so can i link an accounting system with
a shop system for example
yes indeed so
right now oslc is used
primarily within engineering but all the
concepts
are
domain independent they could be used in
accounting healthcare finance
and uh actually
oslc
if you look under the hood you will see
that it uses standards like rdf
that
web search engines like google also use
to support data
interoperability
um so for example if you look at
schema.org so oslc
the set of standards that are used by
oslt
are very much aligned with
the the web standards
and and
what what's going on in general on the
web to to support connectivity
okay so and when we are talking about a
standard
who is responsible for this thing
yes so
the
organization now
managing this the oslc standard is
called oasis
and
right now it's managed under an open
project meaning that anybody can
actually
for free join the meetings
contribute to the standards
the standards are available to the
public
no need to pay anything so the standards
are really meant to
to be visible and and to facilitate
collaboration uh among engineers to
improve them
how many people are involved in the
meetings typically
and so that's development yes oh i would
say maybe four or five yes
these meetings are very technical
and uh
um
it's it's not everybody's cup of tea
and
but
recently a new series of meetings
was created led by iran gary of
ibm
to
actually just talk about osl oslc at a
higher level and these are monthly
meetings that are i think more
interesting for persons who want to
learn more about oslc and and also where
oslc's heading
rather than these very technical weekly
meetings that are about the
specifications and where you know
honestly it's it's it's often quite
boring sorry
okay so we already learned you are
dealing with oslc for about 10 years
um
is there
uh yeah
how is the adoption rate are there tools
supporting all slc already can you name
some of them
sure so as for any new technology you
have
this
you have different groups of persons who
adopt it you have the innovators these
are the first ones to adopted when you
have the early adopters
uh early majority late majority in lagga
i would say that
because ibm has a suite of tools that
support oslc and these tools are quite
well adopted already
uh and and with these tools you can see
oslt in action you can see the linking
across tools and so i would say that an
early majority of engineers
are actually seeing oslc
now there i would say among these
organizations some are seeing the
potential to use oslc to extend
the ibm ecosystem to non-ibm
applications using oslc
and so i would call them early adopters
and where oslc still used
combination tightly with the ibm
applications
you also have
obviously other vendors supporting oslc
but very often it's
for
an integration with ibm that's often
it's not always the case some also use
it
to to link within their own tool suite i
think ptc is an example
and i would say that you have innovators
a much smaller group
who is looking at oslc really to achieve
connectivity completely independent of
ibm
to really
look at the pure oslc and and what is uh
what can be built with oslc
um and i yeah i i actually think we've
only seen the tip of the iceberg of what
is possible with with all resources
yeah people are talking a lot about it
for
quite some time now
and it's it's very interesting
how long it takes to
yeah to really integrate uh tools with
oslc and i think
one thing is that many tools just
uh yeah integrate the consumer part
they want to
gather in information but they don't
want to expose information
exactly that is confusing and misleading
because many vendors will say on their
web page we support oslc
but actually they're just consuming the
data from an oslc api
and not actually really supporting oslc
by exposing their data as oslt resources
that can be linked than with with other
engineering artifacts
that's indeed
quite annoying yes yes
is there any certification for tools so
that i need a certificate to
announce that i'm also a second form or
is there a validation suite or something
like that available
so
i i think it's necessary to ask
some persons in the oslc community to
give you to be 100 certain i'm not aware
of such a validation suite
but i i think informally one has been
certainly developed and there's one that
is open source
um but now you know you have
within oslc so many different
specifications
so that some of them are domain specific
some are domain independent
um that's also maybe why oslt is
considered complicated because it covers
many aspects
and
so
many
uh
tools that claims for oslt will only
support certain aspects of oslc
and
is it an issue in in practice
that for example a tool
announces that it's also a secret form
but uh well it's not 100 confirmed to
the standard and so it does not work
so like uh interoperability between
system l tools and there's a data
exchange form at xmi but well it doesn't
work very well
so um
yeah as christian mentioned the the
problem is that
the vendors don't specify how they
support oslc
so that's where
you know you think oh it's great they
support oslc but then they they just
consume the oslc
another oslt api they don't expose
themselves in the slc api
which is
uh to be honest
something that
maybe goes against the business
incentive of a software vendor because
you're opening up
your data to to the users
and so
you're
you know
you're possibly losing vendor lock-in so
that's one risk
um which you know some vendors could
also say that
there are many opportunities with oslc
so it makes sense to to fully adopt it
and and offer new applications that can
only be built on top of these oso c apis
okay
so um
[Music]
in in respect to time we can't go into
every detail of oslc but i guess there
are two or three
things we we should have a look into and
axel already mentioned some of them so
he often talked about an oclc
specification
just to drop another name
oslc specifications are around a
vocabulary and this could be domain
specific or
not domain dependent
and
to my knowledge uh the vocabulary is
the real important thing
to
standardize things so that every tool
talks about the same thing even it it
calls it internally different
to the outside over the oslc api
it's called this and that and
it's totally up for that systems
what is meant exactly so
oslc has standards to describe domain
specific resources like requirements
test cases so that's also to support
interoperability to the exchange of
these requirements with other
applications
oslc has some
uh standards describing the domain
independent aspects such as the versions
of resources the change events of
resources but access rules
now
somehow oslc must
define okay what are the concepts that
we're using to define the versions or
these domain specific
entities
and oslc
has looked at the web what does the web
do
and
the an example
actually a great example of data
interoperability at web scale is
schema.org
so
this is where
you have a bunch of concepts that have
been defined so this is a movie this is
a recipe etc
but all these concepts
need to be identified in a unique way
and with schema.org they are identified
using a url an http url
the advantage of identifying these
concepts that you want to standardize
using http urls is that on the one hand
you can test if these are unique
identifiers and at the same time you can
use these identifiers to access
these concepts so
i can do an http gets
and and
access the description of this
concept um
so
you i really recommend everybody
to look at schema.org
and
i really think that it shows i think
how standards should be defined
not just
for movies recipes and not just for nbsc
but actually across all engineering
um it's it's um
i think it makes sense to be aligned
with
data
interoperability practices that are
already so widely adopted
and and and
you need to keep in mind that over half
of the web pages
contain urls that point to these
standardized concepts
defined in schema.org so
okay so basically what i'm trying to say
is oslc adopts
for the different definition of these
vocabularies
the same approach as schema.org
and schema.org is supported by the
search engines like google bing yahoo
and and supported by all the
web content creators and
it's a huge number because over half of
the web page
web pages
have had links just to matter
how are the concepts identified but i
asked such a service to give me the the
specification of a movie so uh what do i
get do i get some some text that
explains what a movie is uh or is it
more formal
so yeah it needs to be machine readable
so that the search engines
um
understand that
uh like a movie database like imdb
contains plenty of movies and their
ratings
now
when we look at this movie page of imdb
we see a rating
but the search engine like google
will need to understand that what we're
looking at 7 out of 10 is actually movie
rating
and
so
there's the html content of the page and
in addition either embedded in the html
or
next to it
you will find some rdf
rdf is some machinable data machine
readable data
saying
that actually we have a resource of type
movie rating
uh it has a rating value of seven the
maximum value is ten
and google
or another search engine will understand
this
and then if you do a search for me for
that particular movie
it will show you the movie ratings from
multiple movie databases
right away
because it has already collected that
information and understood that
information
so
in um
there's really nothing special you know
in defining standardized concepts
it's just that
they need to have unique identifiers
and in our world
the most practical
you
i would say most suitable unique
identifiers are http urls
otherwise we end up with a requirement
to find the cml a requirement to find a
red if a requirement defined in uh you
know step by the step community
and and we need to easily distinguish
them and easily access them also
so if everybody was using rdfs for
example for standardization purposes
we would be able much more easily to see
the differences or the things that are
in common between all these different
engineering standards
yeah
and there we are um yeah quite
near the topic we had with fabian
neuhaus where we talked about ontologies
and distributed ontologies
and this is also a very interesting
point but bringing it back to um to the
engineering domain so
if you are looking to the requirements
management specification you see
it is specified like
a requirement has exactly one id it has
exactly one name it might have a change
date or i made this thing up
but but it tells you
yeah
how you describe a requirement and what
you
must provide if you are compliant to
this specification and what might be and
uh
yeah
might be there in data
and
another interesting thing i find in oslc
is that you have this 80 20 approach
so
these groups defining those
specifications are trying to define the
most common eighty percent uh of
those resources of a requirement for
example
and uh yeah tool vendors or users are
able to extend those specifications
right
exactly and i think
any standardization efforts in general
would have will adopt the same approach
i'm sure within the csml
standardization committee you're also
trying to cover 80
of the most important topics and then
with stereotypes you can always you know
support extensions
so i don't think this is unique to oslc
the extension mechanism with rdf is very
simple because
by definition rdf supports this open
world assumption
and actually we need to constrain it we
we don't want to have chaos and any kind
of
um
we don't want to see a requirement be
defined in
10 million different ways we do want to
constrain how a requirement is defined
and so
within oslc we use shackle or resource
shapes to provide constraints to say
yeah a requirement must have for example
an
identifier um and uh
yeah yeah so
um
just to say that these
what we're talking about there is i
would say not unique to oslc
it's common to any standardization
you mentioned system several times and
you also mentioned several people who
are heavily involved in the system
standardization like um roger burkett
who's one of the co-developer of system
l or aaron gary
who's involved in uml and systemic
development and also in the current
system v2 development so um
there seems to be a relationship between
oslc and system a
so how they are related absolutely so
you maybe remember
this picture of csml where you see a
cube and you see that cisono connects
requirements to structure and behavior
so
sysml is about connecting information as
well
um it's it's just that
um
you're connecting information at a very
high level of abstraction
and if it's the only thing you want to
do
you're good with csml
i would say that so you're connecting
the information horizontally right you
know from requirements to structure and
behavior but at an at an abstract level
yeah the horizontal silo exactly
exactly connecting horizontally
and i would say that
it's useful to connect also vertically
from abstract to specific
because at some point you need the real
simulation models for real simulation
results
that will tell you if your system
architecture is even feasible or if if
it's um
in sync with what's going on
at a detailed level
and that's where oslc then becomes
useful for these vertical
connections that's that's one aspect
also
it's in like i should say this um
we have even at a higher level of
abstraction
we might be using different tools
engineers might be using a tool just for
requirements another just for test cases
um so they might not always be using uh
system errors so oslc
is also useful for for systems engineers
who want to connect the data
at that abstract level horizontally
across different tools
um
and um
i would say that the
i mean the fundamental
um
difference that oslc enables is that
before oslc
these links have to be created within a
specific application these crosstalk
maintenance i either use a plm solution
or an alm solution or an nbs nbsc
solution to create these cross domain
links to say that my requirement is
linked to a blog or a test case etc
you're dependent on one specific
application to do this
and with oslc the creation of links can
now happen in a distributed way
engineers can stay within their domain
specific applications to create these
links they don't have to switch to
another application like a plm alm or
mdsc solution to break these links
and that reduces the barrier
to creating the links
and so um and i honestly think it all
this is inspired by the web
um
if for example
you could only add content to the web
through
one single app application there would
be a bottleneck
and
use all kinds of tools to to create
content for the web right now in a
distributed way and that's why the web
can scale so um
and and
so these cross domain links
in the past we've just reviewed them as
oh it's just another piece of data
within an application
but i think we need to elevate
the concept of these cross-domain links
and view them as first-class citizens we
have the domain-specific data
and at the same
level of importance we need to manage
these cross-domain links
and ideally we need to manage them
in a way that is independent of a
specific application that's the only way
we can manage them in a scalable way in
the long term i i'm sorry that my answer
went a bit
was a bit longer but i think these were
ideas that were in my mind that i wanted
to it
it brings to a point what what's the
idea behind the new system lv2 api and
i think it's no coincidence that there
were people who said okay we also want a
platform-specific binding for oslc for
this uh system lv2 api just to
yeah to realize exactly that what what
you axel what you described right now
exactly keep in mind that this idea of
using platform independent and platform
specific bindings
it might actually
create by design a lack of
interoperability so i remember for uml
and csml you have this nice separation
of platform independent platform
specific then you could define
stereotypes and xmi many different ways
and we didn't have interoperability
between csml tools so every time i hear
oh we have something platform
independent something platform specific
i i i see the potential for
a gap between the platform independent
and platform specific
and the possibility for many different
platform-specific implementations that
end up not being compatible
so i really hope we learn the lesson
from system lv one when it comes to the
system rd2 api in that we can actually
be very specific when it comes to the
api and it's only by being specific that
we
avoid any misinterpretations and and and
and you know uh problems with
interoperability
it brings to my mind just right now that
if you're digging very deep on the omg
servers you will find a
sysml
v 1.3 oslc binding from axel i guess i
remember finding something like that
from from you
it's
years ago
i don't know i it doesn't mean you're
better
i i will look it up
variations of xmi
and it was a pain and
i i really hope that
this
these problems can
sting the things
yeah i remember this this is
also i see stuff somewhere yeah
maybe you're thinking of the oslc for
mbsc working group
it was yeah maybe
in
2013 or 1415 yeah yeah 2013 it was
so
that's where we converted the
system l standard was it which is
defined
um
uh
you know
well in xmi
and the whole meta model is the finding
xmi and we converted that into
an equivalent
rdf vocabulary
um
so it's it's very easy to take existing
standards
and make them web compatible if you want
to say
and
unfortunately you know the the
i don't think that there was enough
traction to continue these efforts
maybe you were a little bit ahead of
time yeah
certainly certainly yeah yeah
okay so coming back to the topic
maybe more interesting for our listeners
instead of omg arc archaeology
what's what's the the english word for
is um
maybe it sounded interesting for for
somebody and he would like to play
around with oslc so so what's a good
place to start
oh my god good luck um
i'll say pokemon star
so obviously you should check out
some videos
some articles some primer articles
then
you should
look at some open source solutions
uh there is a slack workspace
uh where you can ask questions there's
also a forum okay where you can ask
questions
um
i think that
many users who actually have questions
about
the need to use these oslc apis are
actually using the oslt apis of ibm
and and they they use the jazz form for
these questions
so um
when it's purely about oslc yeah that's
then it's it's useful to use the slack
workspace of osmt or the forum
and are there any open source tools
using alsoc so two different kind of
engineering tools like a requirement
tool and then systems modeling tool or
simulation tool or so
so there are quite a few implementations
yes that are open source
um
and so i would look at eclipse neo
as the internet github there's an oslc
project on github and there's eclipse
video
now keep in mind that any
oslc
api for a specific tool it needs to be
maintained in order to to stay up to
date because
the tools have a native interface that
changes over time
and
even the whole
the many libraries that oslt apis use
evolve over time so
um you you will find quite a few open
source solutions that are just
completely outdated that you cannot even
compile okay it's just because
um
nobody is maintaining them right now
so
um
but
you can still i think
see examples of how to implement these
oslt apis in java
and with a few questions you can
certainly update them and run them on
your machine
there's also if you prefer python to
java there's the pi oslc
project
which i think
is it takes a different take on oslt
because
it assumes that
you don't want to modify anything of
your of your application onto which you
want to add this oslt wrapper
and so it explains how you can
do this oslc extension in a more
seamless way
and i think that's the right approach in
the long term also
um
and what else um
yeah yeah i hope i answered your
question um
you won't find perfect documentation
that's the problem
so you really need to be a bit more
proactive ask questions if you're stuck
you will probably get me stuck
and
there's just right now not enough
persons in the oslt community to to
create that high quality
uh level documentation that that helps
people get into the topic uh easier
and faster
yeah but this was exactly uh
one thing why my employer contact
software we asked ourselves why is there
no python implementation why is there no
python python sdk
and that's where we when we went to axel
and we are developing it
in
in common we are sponsoring all the work
and we will
yeah truly publish it uh open source
because
it is
reminds me of jupiter lab so can i use
this
pi over olc
with jupiter lab and can easily play
around with it
i don't know um
the thing is that you
know slc api is is not you know
some algorithm to create plots where you
know that's the more typical application
to use jupiter notebooks
so
typically the api code is is written in
a in an ide
and you want to yeah
you need a server you need to deploy it
on your server like quite a few things
involved so it's not
your simple application that you know is
runs
autonomous or in isolation in your
notebook
yeah but i could imagine that
taking pi oslc as a basis
it should be able or someone should be
able to write some kind of plugin for uh
for jupyter notebook
yeah to enable
yeah let's say a notebook to to import
requirements
or something like that
absolutely um
in general i think many organizations
would like to be able to add a tag in
the source code
so that
somebody reviewing that tag can actually
click on the requirement
that actually the source code tries to
satisfy it so there is and
whether it's java code or python code
um
that connectivity between source code at
a very
detailed level in a specific line of
code with a requirement
is something that i think is very useful
okay so
maybe if people are
still interested in oslc with all its
its complications
um
i heard you are
[Music]
also organizing a conference about oslc
each year i guess
can you tell us about it
so
we had three editions of the oslt fest
the first one in 2018 the second one in
and then the last one
last year at the end of last year
and i think it's the
great way to see who is doing what with
oslc you will see many demonstrations of
vendors
and we are seeing
over the years more vendors doing stuff
with oslc
discovering oslc and gradually
supporting more aspects of oslc so
um
if if you want to
get an idea yeah tip your toe into this
oslc world i really recommend checking
out the the oslc fest
videos that are available online
either on youtube i think they're all in
youtube yeah
yeah yeah we can link them
under the video
and will there be a conference this year
i think so yes um
i need to check with my co-organizers uh
that we
i think so probably in november of this
year yeah um
as you can see we're not perfectly
organized
we're not like the omg where we know
exactly what we're doing but um
uh you know people are welcome to
to help obviously with the organization
of that uh event
and
we we
when we um released the call for for
presentations we received many
uh submissions and we even had to reject
some which we can then accept probably
for the next uh event
so um
yeah i i'm very optimistic there will be
one this year and we encourage
the early adopters that are doing
something with oslc to
come out of their
bubble and share it with the world
because there are many companies i think
who are doing stuff with oslc but not
yet
publicly sharing it out of maybe fear
that it's not yet
mature enough but i think it's it's
interesting for other engineers to see
the the thought process of why
an organization is
uh starting to adopt oslc how they're
they're doing it
and and
you know the oslc fest is
intended to create
connections among among persons
interested in oslc and and that we can
benefit from each other from the
experiences of each other
okay
it is always at the same location or
in the world
europe or in the u.s so the first time
it was a normal in-person conference in
sweden
at kth and the next two editions were
online yeah so yeah exactly
and i have a feeling we will keep it
online because
i don't know it did work quite well
okay
so yeah baby one final question uh an
outlook so what are the future plans of
ocrc
so
impossible for me to predict of course
but
we will see more
integrations with ibm elm based on oslc
then i think that
at some points
we will also see the adoption of oslc in
the within
the engineering domain but independently
of ibm tools
um
and i think the in the middle or long
term
we will see the adoption of oslt in
other industries
in the machine learning or healthcare
industry
and
but for this to happen you know the
documentation i would also say the tools
around oslc
need to become more accessible
more commercialized more mature
and
so you know
oslc is still mainly used
by innovators and
and early adopters
and i think we will slowly see yeah this
um
a growing maturity and it's possible
that
if oslc
gets this
reaches this adoption outside of
engineering it might look also a bit
different
because um
some ideas of oslc could be realized
in a slightly different way maybe
without relying necessarily on rdf
still using ref to define the
standardized concepts
but maybe not
for each api resource
and
to give maybe an idea of what this could
look like so
in order to manage distributed
microservices
we have seen tools
that have been released to manage these
service mesh architectures so these are
tools to manage the service to service
communication
when you have a bunch of different apis
and you want to manage how they
communicate with each other
and inspired by what we're seeing
to manage the communication between
services
we
i can imagine very similar tools in a
very similar architecture to manage the
linking
of of api resources
um
and
i don't know what it would what it would
be called um i've noticed that the
keyword data mesh is already taken and
it's it describes principles that are
high
at a high level of abstraction so it's
not very clear how you you implement
these data mesh principles
um
so so
it's i don't know where the journey will
lead to but i'm convinced that linking
data
will
become
more and more
prevalent it's
it's the only way you can
uh understand the data if you understand
its context if you can discover its
context and in a complicated world that
becomes uh increasingly important
right
yeah so
thank you axel for your time so
if anybody is interested to integrate
his tools with oslc or whatever
just contact axel it's it's his everyday
job to to create
oslc
integrations
um
yeah it was very interesting longer than
i expected
and we we skipped many many of uh
interesting topics on it yeah we had
many more
okay but tim what's next on the agenda
well yeah so the next topic you know the
next date is
finally set but will be probably
something about the small v2
this is on the final run
last week at the omg meeting in
washington we decided that we will
submit this will be too definitely this
year end of this year
and there's many interesting sub-topics
the the language itself not the features
of language the api with oslc
um would be another interesting topic
or uh the transformation from system lv1
to the smell v2 uh which will also be
part of the system ob2 standard so
um yeah we will select one of those
topics i guess
and then we
send a notice in our social media
channels and so
okay great yeah
and well the date is not finally set but
around about in a month i guess
typical frequents
one podcast per month
yeah and then well
do not forget
trust us
we are systems engineers
bye-bye goodbye