welcome to the 20th store of our mbse
podcast advent calendar
today we take a look at non-systeml
views
systemrt defines nine different diagram
types such as the use case diagram the
block definition diagram and so on
additionally tables and matrix views are
defined
other views are perfectly possible even
if they are not covered by the standards
so let's have a look at some of them
the relationship map diagram is a
special diagram of the coming of systems
modeler starting from one element a tree
is spent on defined relationships in
this example all elements are in the
namespace of the previous node which is
shown it shows all use cases and the
selected package and then all contained
use case activities
the classic is of course excel some
modeling tools offer it directly out of
the box to export model elements to
excel
some can also make the return trip and
import excel data back into the model
needless to say that you can also
generate text documents from a model the
text document is another special view of
our model
other interesting views are dynamic
diagrams such as those offered by the
graph database neo4j
the cinder tool from intercax can export
the small models to neo4j
there the model can then be viewed in
the dynamic graph diagrams for example
to identify patterns and derive insights
you can find the link to this website
from interhex in the blog post about
this episode on our website
mbsepodcast.rocks
so much for the 20th door of our mbc
podcast
and we wish you a great 20th of december
bye