Welcome to the 20th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
Today we take a look at non-SysML views
SysML defines nine different diagram types
such as the use case diagram, the
block definition diagram, and so on
Additionally tables and matrix
views are defined
Other views are perfectly possible even
if they are not covered by the standards
So, let's have a look at some of them
The relationship map diagram is a special
diagram of the Cameo Systems Modeler
Starting from one element, a tree
is spent on defined relationships
In this example, all elements are in
the namespace of the previous node
which is shown
It shows all use cases and
the selected package
and then all contained
use case activities
The classic is, of course, Excel
Some modeling tools offer
it directly out of the box
to export model elements to Excel
Some can also make the return trip and
import Excel data back into the model
Needless to say that you can also
generate text documents from a model
The text document is another
special view of our model
Other interesting views
are dynamic diagrams
such as those offered by
the graph database Neo4j
The Syndeia tool from Intercax can
export the SysML models to Neo4j
There the model can then be viewed
in the dynamic graph diagrams
For example, to identify patterns
and derive insights
You can find the link to this
website from Intercax
in the blog post about this
episode on our website
mbsepodcast.rocks
So much for the 20th door
of our MBSE Podcast
And we wish you a great 20th of December
Bye-bye