Welcome to the 7th door of
our MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
In this episode we take a look at
the System Use Cases Activities
Behind each of our use cases
we define an activity to model
The functional decomposition
including control and object flows
Let's look at it in our model
In the containment Tree
you can see that the activity
is owned by the use case
The activity diagram shows the
execution order of actions
We've modeled each action as
a call behavior action
which means each step of
the "Christmas Tree Installation"
is detailed and defined
by an another activity
This defines the entire of system behavior
of the use cases with the activities
which has many advantages
It is a prerequisite for the FAS method
for deriving Functional Architectures
which we will have a look
on another episode
An another special feature in
our modeling is the separation
Functions are responsible for
input and output functionality
from and to the actors
and the other functions
We have modeled this
with the activity partitions
This is analytically useful and also a
good preliminary work for the FAS method
The stereotype "IO" comes from
the profile for the FAS method
The outgoing "Transportation Net"
parameter of the activity on the left side
is a so-called streaming parameter
which means the object can flow out of
the activity during the execution
The input parameter "Transportation
Package" flows into a data store node
to make the object available
several times for the protections
Finally, we show another example of
our "MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree"
The continues use case
"Enjoy Christmas tree"
Continues use cases represent
a continuous behavior
The "Flash lights" activity
runs continuously
until the tree is stranded off
That behavior is model
in the state machine
that we will present in another day
So much for 7th door of
our MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 7th of December
Bye-bye