hello
behind the fifth door of our mbse
podcast advent calendar we take a look
at the system context
we already defined a context for the
base architecture behind door number
four or advent calendar
the base architecture context constrains
the context of our system of interest
we model it by defining a generalization
relationship from the system context to
the base architecture context let's
check that out in the model
you can see that the part property the
mbse podcast christmas tree is a
redefinition of the inherited system
based property
base
tmpct from the base architecture context
in addition to the inherited actors from
the base architecture context the tmpct
system context has an additional actor
christmas tree seller
the system context elements are sml
blocks with applied stereotype system
context from the sysmod profile
it is just a marker profile that
introduces a new name and additional
semantics but no new properties
the internal block diagram of the system
context element depicts the well-known
system context diagram
the inherited elements from the base
architecture contexts have a circumflex
prefix symbol this little roof before
the name
and in our system context all actors are
inherited except the seller
like tim explained before
this map provides only the general
concept of an actor it is useful to
define different actor kinds to
emphasize the different methodological
approaches at least you should
differentiate between humans and
non-humans
in the show and context diagram you can
see four different actor kinds
human users for the system for example
center class
external systems for example the power
supply a mechanical system is a special
kind of an external system that has only
mechanical interactions with the system
here it is the floor of our room
and the planet environment to consider
the impact of the system on the planet
all actors have some kind of interaction
with the system
and you could specify the interaction
point by ports
and here we have the little surprising
learning in this episode
stakeholders are not in the context or
only when they interact with the system
for example
we
mbse podcast hosts are stakeholders of
the system
but we are not actors of course as
people we could take on the role of user
of the christmas tree but the mbse
podcast host role is not an actor and
thus the system does not provide any
special interfaces or functions for us
vice versa all actors are stakeholders
of the system
sometimes they are not directly
stakeholders but representatives
for example things like the floor are
not a stakeholder but the owner of the
floor is the stakeholder
so much for the fifth door of our mbse
podcast advent calendar we wish you a
great 5th of december
goodbye
bye