Hello
Behind the 5th door of our MBSE
Podcast Advent Calendar
we take a look at the System Context
We already defined a context
for the Base Architecture
behind door number 4
our advent calendar
The Base Architecture Context constrains
the context of our system of interest
We model it by defining
a generalization relationship
from the System Context to
the Base Architecture Context
Let's check that out in the model
You can see that the part property
the "MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree"
is a redefinition of the inherited
system based property
Base TMPCT from
the Base Architecture Context
In addition to the inherited actors from
the "TMPCT System Context" has an
additional actor "Christmas Tree Seller"
The System Context elements
are SysML blocks
with applied stereotype "systemContext"
from the SYSMOD profile
It is just a marker profile
that introduces a new name and additional
semantics but no new properties
The internal block diagram of
the System Context element
depicts the well-known
system context diagram
The inherited elements from the
Base Architecture Contexts
have a circumflex prefix symbol
this little roof before the name
and in our System Context all actors
are inherited except the "seller"
like Tim explained before
SysML provides only the
general concept of an actor
it is useful to define
different actor kinds
to emphasize the different
methodological approaches
At least you should differentiate
between humans and non-humans
In the shown context diagram
you can see four different actor kinds
human users for the system
for example, the "santa Claus"
external systems for example
the "power Supply"
a mechanical system is a special
kind of an external system
that has only mechanical
interactions with the system here
It is the "floor" of our "room"
And the "planet Environment" to consider
the impact of the system on the planet
All actors have some kind of
interaction with the system
And you could specify
the interaction point by ports
And here, we have the little
surprising learning in this episode
Stakeholders are not in the context or
only when they interact with the system
For example
We MBSE Podcast hosts are
stakeholders of the system
But we are not actors
of course as people we could take on
the role of user of the Christmas tree
But the MBSE Podcast
host role is not an actor
and thus the system does not provide any
special interfaces or functions for us
Vice versa, all actors are
stakeholders of the system
Sometimes they are not directly
stakeholders but representatives
For example, things like the
"floor" are not a stakeholder
But the owner of the "floor"
is the stakeholder
So much for the 5th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
We wish you a great 5th of December
Goodbye
Bye-bye