Welcome to the 19th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
Today we take a look at
the modelling of variants
Very often a system contains variants
So does our MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree
We provide trees with different Christmas
stars, balls, stands, and fairy lights
So, let's look at our model of
how to define the variants
We restructured our model
from the simple system model
to our product line model
To do this, we have defined three
new packages at the top level
A "Core" package that contains all
elements that apply to all products
A "Variation" package that
contains the variable elements
And a package that
contains the configurations
For example, product definitions
Our previous packages are now all
rearranged below the Core package
In the "TMPCT_Variations" package
there is a package diagram that
shows the product line
in the form of a feature tree the
A Variation packages represent
the discriminator variability
Here it is generally only the kinds
The "minVariant" "maxVariant" properties
specify how many of the variants may be
in a valid configuration at the same time
Mostly it is exactly one
An exception here is the
"Christmas Ball Kinds" variation
Here also two variants may be contained
at the same time in a configuration
The variant packages each contain all
exclusive model elements
only required by a variant
Constraints can be defined
between the variants
Typically variant constraints are
"REQUIRES and "XOR"
A "REQUIRES" constraint is defined
between the "Premium Star"
and the "Large Stand" variants
In example
if the "Premium Star" variant is selected
the "Large Stand" variant must also be
selected for a valid configuration
The variant "Premium Star" defines
a special Christmas star
that has an LED starlight
The "Premium Christmas Star" block
specializes the common
"Christmas Tree Star" block from the Core
The Configuration package contains
the variant configurations
which are specifications of concrete
products of the product line
Three defined editions of our
MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree
are "Echo", "Premium", and "Standard"
Each configuration selects
the contained variants
which can be perfectly done in a matrix
The selection is modeled by
a package import relationship
Here we have intentionally included an
error for demonstration purposes
The configuration
"TMPCT Premium Edition"
has selected the variant premium style
That requires constraints
described as requires
that the variant "Large Stand"
but then also be selected
But we have selected
the variant "Standard Stand"
The arrow is automatically displayed
in the matrix you see the red one
As already mentioned
the requires constraint is
a stereotype from the SYSMOD profile
and also contains an OCL constraint
that checks compliance with the rule
This is completely based on standards
The only tool specific here is that the
tool is able to evaluate the OCL statement
The block definition diagram shows a part
of the definition of the
"TMPCT Premium Edition"
The edition itself is a system element
that specializes the system
element from the "Core"
As an example, it is shown how the
"Premium Star" edition is implemented
The premium Christmas star is
explicitly defined as a part property
that redefines the inherited
property of the general star
So much for the 19th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 19th of December
Bye-bye
Goodbye