welcome to the 19th store of our nbc
podcast advent calendar today we take a
look at the modelling of variants
very often a system contains variants so
does our mbse podcast christmas tree
we provide trees with different
christmas stars balls stands and fairy
lights
so let's look at our model of how to
define the variants
we restructured our model from the
simple system model to our product line
model
to do this we have defined three new
packages at the top level a core package
that contains all elements that apply to
all products
a variation package that contains the
variable elements
and a package that contains the
configurations for example product
definitions
our previous packages are now all
rearranged below the core package
in the tmpct variations package there is
a package diagram that shows the product
line in the form of a feature tree the
variation packages represent the
discriminator variability
here it is generally only the kinds
the min variance max variance properties
specify how many of the variants may be
in a valid configuration at the same
time
mostly it is exactly one
an exception here is the christmas ball
kinds variation
here also two variants may be contained
at the same time in a configuration
the variant packages each contain all
exclusive model elements only required
by a variant
constraints can be defined between the
variants
typically variant constraints are
requires and xor
a requires constraint is defined between
the premium star and the large stand
variants
in example
if the premium star variant is selected
the large stand variant must also be
selected for a valid configuration
the variant premium star defines a
special christmas star
that has
an led starlight
the premium christmas star block
specializes the common christmas
tree star block from the core
the configuration package contains the
variant configurations which are
specifications of concrete products of
the product line
three defined editions of our mbse
podcast christmas tree are echo premium
and standard
each configuration selects the contained
variants
which can be perfectly done in a matrix
the selection is modeled by a package
import relationship
here we have intentionally included an
error for demonstration purposes the
configuration tmpct premium edition has
selected the variant premium style
the requires constraint described
requires that the variant large stand
but then also be selected but we have
selected the variant standard stand
the arrow is automatically displayed in
the matrix you see the red
one
as already mentioned the requires
constraint is a stereotype from the
sysmod profile
and also
contains an ocl constraint that checks
compliance with the rule
this is completely based on standards
the only tool specific here is that the
tool is able to evaluate the ocl
statement
the block definition diagram shows a
part of the definition of the tmpct
premium edition the edition itself is a
system element that specializes the
system element from the call
as an example it is shown how the
premium star edition is implemented
the premium christmas star is explicitly
defined as a part property that
redefines the inherited property of the
general star
so much for the 19th store of our mbc
podcast advent calendar and we wish you
a great 19th of december bye-bye
goodbye