[Music]
hello fellow systems engineers
welcome back to our new podcast episode
this time with a guest
and i would say a good friend from the
united states
jason mack c smith
here he is there he is
would you like to introduce yourself
sure thanks kristin
um first thanks to you and tim for
having me on today this is
this is exciting uh i'm jason mccomb
smith
and i'm the vice president and technical
director of the
object management group or omg
probably the best acronym ever
accidentally created
and uh i live in the u.s i'm up in the
seattle area
of washington state um where we hope to
see the sun sometime by april
and uh the my background
is actually i come from academia and
industry
and now i'm at the omg doing
specifications development
okay and well when did you come to the
omg
so when did you join oh boy um
i actually started as a member
representative
uh 2010-2011 um my employer at the time
was
a long-standing member of omg um
still is and they were the ones who
introduced me to the community as
uh as a member just coming in and and
working on technical concerns
um yeah they they're they're still yeah
they're still with us
and a lot of our a lot of our member
companies actually been around for a
decade two decades
um a few of them actually with us the
entire 32 years
uh anyway i was a member um i chaired
the architecture
driven modernization task force and
wrote co-authored a couple of
specifications um
then i was elected to the architecture
board which is an oversight board within
the omg and all of this is as a member
and then
in october of 2019
omg the organization to actually come on
board as an employee
and i have to say it's been a very
interesting 14 months on the job
absolutely almost nothing about the
organization
is the same as when i started um yet
we've worked exceedingly hard to make
sure that the uh
the essentials and the critical elements
have endured through all of this
in our transparency and our processes
and
fidelity of technical excellence and all
that is
has absolutely maintained through all of
this but
yeah i've been uh i've been with omg in
various capacities for just about 10
years
i loved every minute so
what we like to show our listeners today
is
how omg works but before that
maybe you can describe
one one more time what the omg is and
what the omg does
uh jason i fear we lost your audio
yeah we can see you very well but we
cannot hear you
still not
of course no
well it worked all the time but yeah
worked half an hour before
so i think we need a new screen uh
solving to have technical issues so
well trust us is that better oh much
better much better
so you can hear me now yes yes
excellent okay
it's always a technical difficulty
somewhere along the lines in there
so uh what is the omg
um omg is actually uh well
clear something up there are two
entities that operate as the omg
uh and they you'll hear them both
referred to by that name so just to
clear it up real quick
uh first is the community that i'm here
to
mostly talk about with you today which
is the specifications development
organization or
sdo uh
a lot of people would refer to it as a
standards development organization but
there's a distinction there we can
talk about later most sdos have a focus
including ours
ours happens to be on modeling and
ontologies
so uh ways to describe complex systems
such that they can be
expressed precisely communicated with
others and reasoned about
in in formal ways um we're kind of the
the watering hole in the oasis on the
savannah where all of the animals come
together
uh we're the neutrals area where
competitors
in industry come together to collaborate
and work on
common solutions to common problems the
second
omg entity is the organization as a
whole
and the originally the organization
and the sdo were one of the same but
over time we realized that
we're actually rather good at creating
and supporting communities
and we had other communities pop up in
2010 we had
sisk the consortium for information
software quality
and they work closely with the sdo to
create and shepherd specifications into
our system
we also in 2014 we had the industrial
internet consortium which is sort of an
industrial iot
group uh 2019 we had dds foundation data
distribution services
foundation as well as bpm plus health
for business process modeling in the
healthcare space and last year we
launched the digital twin consortium
which is everything to do with digital
twins simulation prediction
uh calibration synchronization all that
good stuff
so we're really now we're a community of
communities we're a whole ecosystem
around this
and the sdo operates as the uh sort of
the linchpin in a lot of ways
for uh specifications and
providing process support to the other
communities
when they have something that they would
like to to get out there into industry
in a more formal way
all of our communities are volunteer
based
they're the ones who make it all happen
we say that we are a member-driven
organization
and we mean that very very clearly and
and precisely um everything that happens
at omg happens through our membership
uh whether it is deciding the policies
and procedures
or determining what the shape of our
conferences are going to be
and every bit of technical work that is
done at omg is done
by our our membership omg the
organization simply provides the space
for them to do that and the support
for their communities but it's uh
everything that that is published by omg
in the end
actually originates from our membership
and how many members are under omg
we have over 300 members right now and
we have
what we have is member companies some
organizations have
individual members we only have
companies as members
we have i think it's a just shy of 350
actually at the moment
but uh they range in size from you know
international global con
you know conglomerates down to single
individual consultancies
uh and they are everywhere in the world
okay and yeah tim go on
the omg has branches in other countries
i remember in germany there was
an organization that they said they are
the omg or responsible for
stuff and uh did a lot of obg
information days
uh so one day conferences yeah we
actually have
we have groups that we work with all
around the globe
the we have representatives and uh
uh sort of satellite offices pretty much
everywhere
um i think we're i think we're actually
in six of the seven continents and i
keep hoping for antarctica but nothing
yet
so okay and then you mentioned
uh an interesting fact so you said
omg is a standards development
organization
so what is what is
the difference between standards and
specifications
or is that different there's actually a
that's a good question
um there is a distinction in a in a very
technical and legal sense
standards are uh adopted by
nation states countries so like iso
international standards organization
their membership
are nations they're not companies
they're not individuals they're actually
nations so a standard is
one that has been adopted by a a
national government body um
otherwise it's a technical specification
it's a technical document that has been
adopted by a community or an industry
and you know of course informally most
people
will refer to specifications as
standards you know the html standard
or you know uh what have you um
but there actually is a distinction so
when we talk about
uh what we produce we try and always try
and always use the word specifications
but
sometimes we slip out and refer to them
as standards
but yeah correctly their specifications
okay and some omg technologies
are also iso standards right so yeah i
think
uml and system i know that for sure
uh so what's the relationship between
obg and iso
so we have um i think the current count
is 13
specifications that have been ratified
as iso standards
and we have a bit of a special
relationship between omg and iso
um what uh what we've done over the
years
is work closely closely with iso to make
sure that
what we do is more or less iso
conformant
if you look at an omg published
specification
the the format the document etc it is
the iso format
in fact if you take if you grab one of
the
the omg's specifications for like uml or
ssml
off of our website and you then go to
the iso
site and pay for theirs ours are free
there's a paid
uh the only difference is the cover page
that's it everything else is exactly the
same
so it's uh um yeah we work extremely
closely with them we have
what is uh called a publicly accessible
standard status
which means that they have vetted our
processes uh they have taken a look at
the quality of
our output over the years and we're
essentially on a fast track
so if we take our specifications into
iso
um we have a uh
a unique position within the within
their processes
and frequently it's a six to nine month
process to get one of our specifications
through
iso in fact we tend to be so much faster
than they are
that our process time plus
getting the fast track time is usually
less than their
regular process time so
it's uh it's an option for some people
so they never do changes to the
specifications except
the cover sometimes they do sometimes
they do there are sometimes minor
requests that are made um but uh
yeah for the most part it's it's exactly
the same document
yeah okay and
so let's let's go a little bit deeper
into how how omg works so one
one of the places where these
specifications
are worked out is a technical meeting
can you explain to other listeners what
a technical meeting is
sure so a technical meeting is a
conference that happens four times a
year
um used to be face to face this year has
been a little challenging
uh but uh we have you know we have
adapted to the new environment and we've
been running virtual conferences
they are a week long they run from
monday through friday
and actually if you don't mind i have
some slides here that i can
you know show and and demonstrate a
little bit
of uh
what it looks like as far as from a
structural viewpoint because that's
really sort of the
that's really important to understanding
what goes
on during this conference week
from the evening sessions all right no
no no
yeah it's a it's a very interesting it's
a very interesting time i will say that
uh
coming from academia industry this is
omg is the most interesting confluence
of the two
approaches i've ever seen it has the the
idealistic
and uh uh you know let's do incredible
things of academia
and it has the pragmatic we need to get
things done of industry all over the
same place and it's it's fantastic but
uh this is the this is the structure of
uh omd as a as an sdo um
and we have the from the top down we
have the board of directors which is our
our business oversight uh they are
elected from our membership we have the
architecture board which is
a technical oversight board again
elected from the membership
uh we then have a split between our two
technology committees domain and
platform and domain
is uh focused on specific industries
such as
finance healthcare space exploration
uh one that's near and dear to my heart
you might notice in the background
um just a ton of uh of
uh very industry focused task forces and
then on the other side we have the
platforms which
are analysis and design um artificial
intelligence these are technologies
and concepts that cross-cut across a
number of industries
so these task force organization lets
you
let you focus on specific industries or
on horizontal
technologies the
the task force is meet all week um
and they uh they will discuss their
particular agendas
um if they have documents that need to
be reviewed they will bring them to
the architecture board for review during
the week
the architecture board will then
recommend whether or not a
um a
documented technology something should
be recommended it will go back to the
technology committee
and they will actually vote on whether
to move it forward um
it's kind of a bit of a back and forth
and and we can go into that later if
you'd like
but um yeah it's it's four days of
everybody running around bouncing from
meeting admitting
making sure that they're collaborating
and in our communication with each other
and then on friday everything comes
together
and we have the plenary session which is
where the technical committees meet and
do the final
votes and and move things forward
that's always kind of an interesting day
because you get to see everything that
has happened that week
and everything that is going to be
happening at the next meeting
uh it's a wonderful way of kind of
catching up and getting prepared for the
next cycle
um and we have a uh webinar actually
tomorrow
that uh we're going to be doing that so
if anybody's interested to find out more
uh hop over to the omg.org website and
we will
uh you can find the link there for uh
yeah
we'll be talking tomorrow cool so very
good
maybe as a side information for our
german listeners so we have
even a german board of director member
so uber kaufman is on the board of
directors
maybe listeners know him
and you mentioned also the architecture
board and i think it's an interesting
fact
what uh yeah
what requirements are prerequisites are
set for
architecture member boards uh people
so yeah so the architecture board is
um it's a wonderful group of people
these are
individuals who have been nominated by
their peers within the group
to basically represent omg's
technical review so it's
um they look at they do a technical
oversight they look at every document
that comes through
they make sure that it fits sort of
within our larger specification
ecosystem
so that we don't have groups that are
stepping on each other's toes
or you know we're not leaving gaps
within our ecosystem we want to make
sure that
that uh what comes out is
fit to purpose and is also
uh high quality um
so it's a it tends to be a bit of a
gauntlet for folks coming through
uh and christian i know you've you've
been through it
yeah um it these are exceedingly bright
people but it's they're nominated by
their peers
and they're elected by their peers there
are five architecture board members
from the domain technical committee and
five from the platform technical
committee
uh they put a tremendous amount of time
and effort into
into every meeting cycle um but uh yeah
we have an election every year
and it's it's a good group it's a lot of
fun i'm the chair of the architecture
board
and uh it's it's a task i greatly enjoy
okay so is it true that they need a
confirmation letter of their companies
that they get spare time
for their work yeah actually it's
they dedicate so much time that one of
the
one of the things that we require is a
letter from their employer
saying that they are allowed to use up
to 25
of their official employment time to
work on this
um it's it's a lot i mean when you
have well my first
meeting as an architecture board member
my very first document was
a 1600 page specification in a domain
that i had never
worked in
i don't think they were hazing me but
i'm still not sure
it was it was a couple of uh
it was a couple of weeks of dedicated
effort to get through that document and
give it the
the uh attention to detail that it
needed um
it's it's a ton of work and it continues
on
even after the meetings uh right now we
have
multiple architecture board members who
are working with groups to
make sure that their uh their documents
and what they're producing is of
top-notch quality
and uh meshes well with everything else
that we have
right um coming back to the technical
meetings so where are the meetings held
in most cases right now
right now eventually okay yeah
um so every march we try and have a
meeting
in western virginia in the washington dc
area
and that's sort of our our one uh
regular
meeting location um every december we
try and do one on the west coast of the
us
uh usually california june and september
kind of bounce around
june alternates between somewhere in
north america and
somewhere in europe and then september
is free floating
it could be anywhere any year and we
leave that one wide open
but we try and hit the at least major
geographic areas
um we're talking about getting back to
asia which
about 10 years ago was was one of our
regular locations
um i believe june was actually
alternating between
europe and asia previously
um but yeah right now it's it's north
america and europe
although we really would love to expand
that back out again once
travel becomes possible
what was your favorite meeting location
ever oh probably brussels
brussels it was a nice meeting i
remember that one it was a nice meeting
it was
uh the uh that was one that my
that uh my wife was able to accompany me
on and gotten married the year before
so we had a few days in paris beforehand
and it was a good prep
yeah my highlight was nashville so i
loved the nashville meeting
with all the music in the top in
downtown
yeah it was great
nashville was a lot of fun
okay so but coming back to the
specification process
it's also a lot of fun well
i think it's more fun than that people
expect um
yeah the workflow it's very interesting
it's it's
the best training you'll learn a lot
um so uh
last year yes was last year we had a
german episode in this podcast about
the history of system so maybe that's
that's a good
example to explain the omg process so in
that episode we used a lot of
abbreviations like rfe rfp
and so on but we did not explain them
so it's maybe it's time to explain them
now
um if i remember correctly it was 2002
um when the omg published the request
for information the rfi
for uml for systems engineering also
known as
systematic so is is that the starting
point
uh of of a specification development and
and who starts the request for
information
it can be uh do you mind if i share my
screen again yes
please okay so
there's really five phases of
uh what happens with a specification at
omg
and we like to think of this as a
conversation this is a conversation
that's happening between
industry between our membership and
between the organization
and the very first thing you have to do
in getting towards the specification is
ask what's the problem
and so if there's you know a market
awareness of a problem or you know
problem arises in industry um
people could become aware of the problem
but they're really not quite sure the
shape of it
uh that's that blue layer across the top
is
is public in industry uh the yellow in
the middle is is omg membership and then
teal at the bottom is is uh the results
of our
our processes through the organization
so market becomes aware of a problem
um they can come to us as an
organization
and we will help them find a task force
that is dedicated to that
domain or that platform technology
somewhere that it fits
makes sense that they have access to
experts and the task force will form
uh questions about that particular
problem space and try and find out more
and then they will publish an rfi
request for information
that rfi then goes back out into
industry and at this point we're like
okay we we have an idea of what the
problem looks like
but we need to we need to you know
gather more information
and start to form the shape of a
solution
so we go out the rfi goes out the public
anybody in in the world can respond to
an rfi and we encourage that
as much as possible we want to get
everybody involved in the conversation
get as much information as we can so the
industry responses are gathered they
come back to the task force
the task force then uses that
information to help hammer out a set of
requirements
in other words what is the what is the
solution going to have to look like in
this problem space
what is it going to have to address
explicitly and concretely
and the task force uh defines those
requirements
and then authors an rfp or request for
proposals
that then goes back out into industry
and that's where i think a lot of people
start to hear about uh omg processes is
probably at the rfp
stage but there's a there's that entire
early section
of the conversation where we really
encourage people to get involved because
they get to help
shape not just the solution but the
shape of the problem
and you know as system engineers you
know
that uh defining the problem is often a
major part of this
of defining the solution so it's
it's this back and forth between you
know these three different
uh these three different groups of the
public the task forces
and the organization um but yeah that's
uh
the rfi and the rfp the rfp goes out
into
into the public um anybody can
at that point say that they have a an
intent
to contribute intellectual property or
so or
a solution towards a specification and
that's where we
gather what we call letters of intent
very
you know obviously named um anybody in
the world can
file a letter of intent it's not a
contract it's simply a you know raising
your hand and saying hey we
we think we'd like to help out on this
at that point the those who have filed
letters of intent
uh conform into submission teams
and this is where sysml v2 is right now
is that submission team works together
outside of the omg processes this is
their own private
their own private doing uh they
work together to try and form a solution
amongst themselves
and the wrinkle is that only omg members
can actually
formally submit a proposal which is why
that next box is
partially blue and partially yellow it's
uh
you don't have to be an omg member to be
part of the submission team but you must
be an omg member as a company to
actually
submit the specification proposal into
the
omg processes um you know have your
your company on the copyright and all
that good stuff
so there's a there's also a
being an omg member in that capacity
also gives you a tremendous voice
in what happens to the specification
later on the process
that you don't have if you are simply a
member of the submission team
so proposals come in they go to the task
force that issue the rfp
the task force evaluates the submission
or submissions if they get more than one
and they oversee the authoring of a
final
specification that specification
is now put out in sort of a beta testing
format
we call it a beta specification for a
reason uh it goes out into the public
anybody can download it they can kick
the tires they can test it out
and they provide feedback to
us to what is called a finalization task
force
or an ftf and that ftf
takes the issues that are filed we use
we use jira as a
tracking system and they address
each and every issue that comes in
they're not allowed to just ignore
things
it must be reconciled in one way or
another
even if the reconciliation is deferred
we're not going to do this right now
we'll do it later
but each and every issue that comes in
from the public must be addressed
and at that point we have a o
specification
we've got a 1.0 a 2.0 um
and it goes back as a formally
published specification of the omg now
it's out there for people
to download uh to implement to adopt in
their industry
but we're not done because there's
always the chance that there may be a
bug
so we want to make sure it's a stable
solution moving forward
and that's where the revision task force
is chartered it's an rtf
uh for short and it acts much like the
finalization task force but in an
ongoing basis so we'll have a 1.1 rtf
a 1.2 rtf etc etc as the specification
evolves through time
we make sure that there's always a group
that is ready and willing to
receive and accept and address any
issues that are found
and that bumps up the the minor version
number
at which point it goes right back into
the next rtf
so this is a this is an ongoing
discussion what's the problem what's the
solution is it suitable is it robust and
is it stable
and at some point in time we usually
realize that we can do more or industry
comes to us and says you know what we
think we can do more
and we start the whole process over
again um
but it's uh you end up with a 2.0
3.0 etc so this is the this is the
overall
general view of of uh the evolution of
the specification and i am hand
waving away every single omg process in
this because those all happen between
the gold and the teal down there at the
bottom
um
there's a ton there as well but
i will stop there unless you guys want
me to continue
are there any timing constraints so um
between an rfi and rfp there must be at
maximum only one year or something like
that
there are there are there are
constraints we have the
the infamous pnp policies and procedures
document which outlines
the entire timeline everything from
uh you know an rfi should have a
guideline of
uh six to 12 months to give companies
sufficient time to respond
one thing that a lot of people forget is
that companies also need to
have their uh their legal department
usually sign off on their response
and that tends to be the biggest the the
biggest delay that we see
so uh when you have engineers in the
room and they're like oh yeah
we'll give them three months it'll be
fine no no no no
the engineers will be ready in three
months legal department may take longer
so uh we try to say you know
nine to 12 months for an rfi um the rfp
when it goes out
uh the absolute shortest time that you
can do
is six months it's possible
um you have to really put your ducks in
a row and make sure that everything is
lined up
exactly right because the deadlines
are uh very firm and
they center around our conferences um
and the conferences while they are every
three months they are not
exactly every 91 and a quarter days
so um sometimes there's a
there's a you know there'll be a week
earlier or a week later than expected
and uh that can cause some issues but
for the most part
we uh yeah it's we try and make sure
that uh
everything goes out with sufficient time
such that folks in public and industry
have plenty of time to
gather their thoughts put together a
solution or a response
and uh get it back to us in
with uh copious amounts of time
what's the longest time between rfp and
the submission for example system will
be two the rfp was december 2017
right so three years ago but it's still
running
it yeah it can it can it can still run
the um
when it comes to you know small very
focused specifications
um we've done it in as little as 18
months from beginning to end
from issuance of an rfp all the way to
the final adoption
of an ftf 18 months which is
fast uh when we know that it's going to
be an exceedingly
large complicated uh
specification lexus mlv2 um then yes
it's it's just basically make sure that
everybody has the time that they need
one of the nice things is that once you
get past
the initial submission stage and that
submission goes into the final in sorry
into the task force
for review uh there you enter the
revised submission stage and that's
where
everything gets hammered out that can
actually be
shortened at any time that the task
force says yep
we're done we gave ourselves a year but
we did it in three months we're done
they can move forward so we have some
flexibility built in but
yes it can be a very fast or a very long
process
depending on the complexity of the
solution that's being hammered out
okay so for
our live watchers you can also use
uh the chat the live chat and
ask some questions that we will refer to
jason uh if you have some
and in the meantime i would have another
question
so let's assume i'm not a member my
company my employer is not a member but
i want to check that out
can i just sign up for a meeting and
how can i do the the omg experience
[Laughter]
well the omg experience wow that's
that's
for those of you who haven't been to
conferences it is um
it's nine in the morning to five at
night of extremely intense
technical work lots of discussion uh
argument it's it's lively it's
it's very serious and in the evenings
it's not
it's an incredible and incredible
experience um but yeah if anybody wants
to get involved
uh a couple of ways first of all that
entire blue track across the top of the
uh the prior slide responding to our rfi
getting involved with the submission
team uh hammering out
you know issues on a specification and
filing issues with us
all of that anyone can do at any time
that is completely open to the public
you can be
part of the conversation through that
route if you want to come to the omg
uh there's a couple of different ways
you can do it
one is wait a couple of different ways
you can do it without becoming a full
member let me move it that way
we frequently have what we call meet and
greets and these are usually domain
focused mini conferences that happen
during our regular
technical committee meetings they'll
usually happen in the evening
and we will have guest speakers and it's
a way to come and find out what
a what omg is doing on a particular
topic or in a particular domain
it's a great networking opportunity
they're low-cost they are exceedingly
lively
and it's just a lot of fun it's a great
way to kind of get your feet wet
um sometimes uh we
we will offer i don't want to make any
promises sometimes we will offer uh
folks a guest pass for a day or two if
there's a particular meeting that they
really would like to sit on on
they of course don't have any voting
power in those meetings
um but uh yeah they can come see what
it's all about and uh try and decide
you know what level of interaction they
would like to get
but of course there's also become a
member and when you become a member
they you have a voice with an omg you
have
an official vote and we have kind of an
interesting
and unique feature of omg and that is
it's one vote per company not
one vote per person which means
that ibm and microsoft have exactly the
same
amount of official voting power as a
one-person consultancy
this is kind of unique for an sdo
normally it's normally it's uh it's done
on a per
representative basis and we do it on a
per company basis
and we feel that this really helps
elevate
the voices of uh individuals
um from smaller companies who may
otherwise not get an
opportunity to be heard in a larger
environment
so this is it's it's a
it's a feature not a bug
[Laughter]
we're really proud of that a little bit
uh you said that omg is a member driven
organization so all the specification
work
is done by the members and i think
that's
that's an interesting point because the
members do not get any money for that
well it's vice versa they must pay for
that they can work for the obj so to say
um and well they have to spend a lot of
time
um in the specification work i think
because most of them
do this because it's it's their passion
and life blood so
um but are there other ways to
to keep this process running so that
that
they work on standards like like system
lv2 which is a very complex one that's
able that the people
work in their spare time in most cases
uh for for some years on understand that
so
but yeah thanks what attracts people
well i think it's like you said it's
passion it's these are
these are members all individuals who
are here because they want to be
and because they see the value of having
uh specifications standards um
they see the value of that because it's
uh
you know it it helps lay foundations for
innovation later
uh if you know everybody had to choose
their you know their appliances based on
the electrical plugs they had in their
house based on the plug
vendor that the house builder selected
when it was originally built it would be
insane
but we have standardized plugs and
it makes things easier so people come
here because
they see specific problems that they
would pretty much like to get out of the
way and for their industry
and say we would love to stop spending
time on this particular problem
everybody's beating their head against
this wall let's just get together
solve it once and for all and move on to
the next
thing because that's the fun part
so it's it is it's people who are
passionate
about not only uh working on the
specific problems
that come to us at omg but because they
want to get to what's next
they want to get to the next interesting
thing um
and that's a i think it's a passion that
everybody there shares yeah
yeah there's always a special energy
there the meeting so i think it's
absolutely earliest
it really is it's uh it's always a bit
hopeful
and uh um yeah i really miss the
face-to-face meetings right now
yeah yeah i agree so i would like to
come
back to the point or tim do you have an
additional question
maybe one last question about about the
members
sometimes people say omg stands for old
man group so
there are many old people maybe i'm also
one of them so
but is it real is
most members of or persons at the omg
meetings or in the groups are
old or is it not true anymore
um i would say it's getting less true
thankfully the uh
but yeah it's it's been
it's been an issue because
the folks who generally have the most
expertise in the industry to see the
large-scale problems
and to see the possibilities of those
large-scale solutions do tend to be
those who have
more years in the industry they do tend
to be
skew a little bit older and um
that's it's great when it is a you know
a base of expertise and a base of
wisdom for lack of a better word but
we absolutely are reaching out and
making sure that we
continue to have folks come in from
younger
and younger demographics because there
is
no there's no age restriction on
innovation
and there's no age restriction on uh
solving problems and being part of this
conversation
so we're you know we encourage everybody
to come be a part of the conversation is
really the
the easiest way to put it um there's
uh there's a space here for pretty much
anybody and everybody
and the folks who are a little bit older
love to mentor so
it's a it's a fantastic opportunity for
folks who may be
earlier in their careers to come
get first-hand advice and first-hand
knowledge from folks
who have who have been there and seen
that
so it's it's a fantastic place for
everyone
so one way to attract younger people
would be to include academia and
universities
so is there a special program for them
actually there is uh we have our
academia working group which is always
looking for ways to do
outreach uh we also have a special
membership level for our universities
and uh it's one membership again since
we do
one membership per company uh one
membership and i believe
it is a whopping sum of five hundred
dollars u.s
covers the entire university all faculty
all staff and all students
so anyone who wishes to come in under a
university banner
that's a fantastic way to do it we work
with a number of graduate departments
and we have just started actually
we announced it right before everything
shut down so our timing was
excellent uh we are starting poster
sessions
where we are inviting uh hopefully
um universities around the areas that we
are going to be physically located at
uh to work with us and help get their
graduate students and their
undergraduates
in front of you know a community of
experts
that are extremely interested to see
what's next and this is a great
opportunity for them
so um that's information on that is
available
on our website as well um oh yeah one
one quick note if anybody
ever wants more information about what's
going on at omg
uh you can email us at info
omg.org so short sweet
to the point uh mail us and we'll be
happy to answer any questions that you
have
but uh yeah that academic outreach is is
something we
we're feeling uh rather strongly about
and uh we think it has a
tremendous amount of opportunity for us
okay
and we have a question from the audience
dominic
asks can national agencies be members of
omg and if yes
are are conflicts of national interests
ever be a problem in technical meetings
oh good one uh yes national agencies can
be
uh can be omg members in fact we have a
government
level for exactly that purpose
i don't think that we've ever had a
conflict of interest
bubble up and be exposed without our
environment
the folks who come from government are
all
you know professional exceptional at uh
making sure
that uh what goes on uh what they bring
to our environment
is is appropriate um
no i'm trying to think i don't think
we've had a conflict of interest of that
particular kind
uh it's we're we're not
a because we're not a standards
development organization we don't have
nations as our our members
so we don't have to have to worry about
particular you know issues around that
um but yeah we have member nist
national institute of standards and
technologies here in the us
is one of our members i believe that the
well i'll just stop exposing my
ignorance and instead say
nist yes we actually absolutely have
never and i know that we have others
as well so what membership level is jpl
is it governmental or is it oh good
question
i honestly don't know i'd have to look
that up let's look that up
yeah tim other questions i
don't have any more questions
so i i would have one little question i
would like to come
back to the small companies and
the the individuals
self-employed people um
isn't that too expensive for them or how
how do you
do you do you have different membership
levels
and how do you manage that
we do actually now that thank you for
asking that that's a good point
the because one of the things that we
like that we feel strongly about is
elevating
uh smaller voices um we have
uh different tiers of membership level
uh everything from contributing which is
our
sort of all-in-one package you can it's
the the highest level
uh you can vote in and contribute
intellectual property to any task force
at any moment at any time join any
voting
list it's really the the you know all
you can eat buffet
um we have that down to what we call
observer
which is you can come to the meetings uh
you're welcome to be part of the
conversation
um however you cannot you cannot submit
intellectual property to a specification
and you cannot
vote um but you can still be part of the
conversation
which is where a lot of people start so
we have everything in between
and we also scale our membership levels
based on the revenue of the company so
if it is a small company and you would
like to come in
at say observer that's a very small feat
if you're a very large company and you
would like to come in at contributing
that's a much larger fee but we try and
scale it to the
the size and the uh the abilities
of the of the member company coming in
okay great
so i see no more questions on the live
chat
i have no questions anymore tim
still no questions no we are already 50
minutes on the line so
correct time is running
times are running and i hope we could
give our listeners a good insight
or into omg and if there are
more questions leave us a comment here
on youtube
on spotify on amazon music google
podcasts
and apple podcasts yeah
these are the locations where you can
hear and watch us
and yes thank you very much for your
time jason
yeah thank you very much for having me
on this has been it's been a lot of fun
thank you
we appreciate it and yeah unfortunately
we can't give you
a next episode's date we are still in
uh in in finding
a date fall for the next episode
um so feel free to
subscribe to the channel do not uh
so so you are getting informed about our
next meetings and i think
the last thing we could do is to say
trust us we are systems engineers
thank you goodbye