okay so welcome
to another episode of our mbse podcast
and
another episode of our mbse around the
world
series and this time we are in china
our guest is chung li and since we are
not good at pronouncing chinese names
we call him liu so i first
met leo free for free three years ago i
guess
at the mess conf in shanghai and then
again during a business trip
so usually the mess conf the modeling of
embedded systems conference
which i co-organize is held in munich uh
in germany but we are open to other
locations so we were in china a few
years ago
and this year by the way the mess conf
will take place virtually due to corona
and you find more details at massconf.de
so but back to our guest so leo
is uh of course active in the field of
mbse
uh but he can best tell you about that
himself so leo please introduce yourself
okay
thank you uh thank you team and
christian
hello everyone my name is leo
thanks for the uh team and christmas
invitation it's great honor to be here
today my uh i'm leo ceo
of syscraftlab in 2017
i created a sysgraph lab
so we are providing nbc consulting
service
and mbs product and also
project uh landing yeah so okay
yeah cool so leo
what are the typical car industries in
china that
use mbse and they who
who are your customers typically okay
in china the typical industries using
mbsc
are aerospace enterprises and also
auto industry and high-tech
companies yes we can take
many different kinds of customers
i guess we have a very so typically we
in germany think we have a
large automotive industry but i think in
china it's much much larger than
in germany so we have lots and lots of
um
automotive vendors yeah okay
um and what is the
what is typically the the purpose of
mbse
in in that projects is it used to for
the communication between the
stakeholders or
to specify the product or it's uh
typically purpose to simulate
the system so what's the field of
application of mbse
okay in my opinion i think there are
four main
purpose the first is complex system
architecture management
the designer can use use mbse to
represent
system architecture so they
they can build a complex system
this is the first one second is i think
communication between the stakeholders
but i think many designers didn't see
the value
of the mbse so they need
a use diagram a picture
or models to communicate
but i think different
designers in different
domains they they may
not usually use mbse to
to communicate so i think uh they
there need more improvement
and the third i think um is for rapid
design
and validation of conceptual design
process
a treat of multi-conceptual solutions
mbse is very useful and
the fourth i think design knowledge
management for example knowledge
representation knowledge accumulation
knowledge reuse models in mbse
as a carrier of design knowledge
design experience design date especially
relationships of knowledge is very
important
so and experienced
designers can abstract refine
and represent knowledge into different
kinds of models and
and diagrams it's very easy for
knowledge reuse so and knowledge
engineering
and knowledge management is a old topic
but i think mbse is very useful
in this old topic but we we need more
practice and application
of mbse and the last one i think
mbse is very useful for evolution
of cognitive process for complex
design from the perspective of
cognitive science design is a
evolutionary process you can also see
design
as a sparring up upward process
models and diagrams is very useful and
helpful
for the process of deep thinking so you
can
like um animation or
simulation and the animation
is a process of different pictures
all we call frames design is a similar
precise
so i think mbse is very useful you can
print
your thinking into different models
or diagrams so you can think deeper and
deeper
so this is a recognitive precise
mbs is very useful yeah
and and these five uh
perspective is my personal cognition
okay yeah okay and um
what would you estimate how well is mbse
used in china already
although we did a lot of practice but
the channel still has a long way
to go so we need to study
or learn from foreign
wonders or customers how they
practice mbse so i think we need a lot a
lot of
um and to study from the deferring
and counterparts i think
yeah well i think you're
not alone with that so mbse is in most
countries i would say at the
at the beginning of the adoption um
although it is there for well around 20
years or so
it's hard to say where was the starting
point of mbse
uh well it would also be interesting to
do a podcast about that but
yeah but in mo in most industries
it's the projects are at the beginning
of course there are some exceptions and
and then it looks very interesting
what you can do with mbsd so that's wow
okay um yeah another important part of
course is
is the education of mbse so
what do you think what what is the level
of education
in of mbse in china is it for example
taught
at universities already okay
i think mbs education is still uh
at a relatively elementary
level and many universities don't have
mbse courses yeah
and there are not many courses that
teach
mbse in universities at
present and we need to strengthen it
further i think but we we have
many trained trainings for for customers
for
for the the um
the different domains
we will provide some some training
that's also yeah that's it
okay and maybe
a side question so are other tools
taught in in university like for example
matlab or simulink
or something which is more
yeah yes for example
simulation some simulation tools
entered has entered the universities but
the nbc
truth is just the beginning
and at the present got it yes
yeah we we try we try
try to enter for example shanghai john
university
and we cooperate with the
gyoton university teachers so we want to
provide
our tool to the students students can
practice
at the mechanical engineering courses
they can use mbs tools to present a
small system
and b build a system architecture
and so and i think it's just the
beginning
right now yeah okay
and i was wondering uh are there
is there a local chapter of incosia in
china and do you
have some mbse working groups where
people come together
to exchange information on mbse
yeah yes i i hope that there
and there are so many working groups we
can collect and
communicate or study learn from each
other
but there are not many high quality
working
groups in china i entered in
um i went to united states
i they take and take part in the
some meetings in in there
but in china i think they are not very
high quality so we we
we need to improve it
yeah i remember the last time i was
there or
at the best conference that yeah we had
my friends at
the university in shanghai i don't
remember the name of the university but
yeah there
yeah uh i also taught talked to some of
the professors there and
uh yeah they also mentioned that mbse is
not taught at the universities but
uh if i remembered correctly they said
that
uh the unified modeling language so the
uml and the software engineering domain
is is very common in china can you
do you know that
yeah yes i i i joined the
different meetings or some groups
to to discuss how to use mbse
but the the chinese um counterparts
i think need improve their their
professional skills or learn
to different modeling language
so um
i think not not very so many and
like mexico meetings
in china yeah okay yeah so
do you think it makes sense to do
another mbse conference in china
is it yes
welcome to china we can call organize
the meetings like mexico yeah i'm very
happy to do that
yeah that was great it was good fun and
very interesting
had a good time there
yeah so um
it seems you have the typical challenges
of mbse
but uh maybe there are some specifics so
can you tell us a little bit about the
the challenges you observe uh of mbse
uh to adapt that in in the companies in
china so what are their problems
yeah uh i think there are many child
challenge
challenges in china for
uh for customers i think the
further uh maturity
uh of chinese market chinese customers
need to
improve their professional skills
in terms of mbse especially in
current digital air error
how to re restructure
the research and
development development process of
complex
system is a big challenge and for
vendors technology accumulation
and export exploration
we know that other countries have been
doing
mbse practice for many years
but for chinese vendors is still
students
i think we need we still need to learn
good good experience from foreign
counterparts how to integrate different
technologies and technical solutions in
global
in global it's also a big challenge
so we when we developing this graph
modeler so we found different
um vendors all tech
technology and companies from
other countries so how to integrate
these
different technical solutions is very
is a very big challenge
and for mbse ecosystem and
in china i think china need need
need construct of open ecosystems
for mbs researchers
vendors and customers it need a lot of
work
to do yeah
i think this is all challenges for
chinese and vendors and customers
yeah okay
yeah so you mentioned uh the modeling
tool the sysgraph modeler
so could you give us a short
overview of the tool and maybe for our
listeners of the podcast
this is the point where you should
switch to the youtube video
uh that you can see what leo will show
us but he will also tell us
what we can see there okay no problem
i can share my screen yeah you're
welcome
okay
okay okay focus
and this is a video uh we
for two years ago we did this project
so you you can look the whole
uh interface and there is
a model 3 here is a
diagram of our table
so you can see
first we can import requirements
from excel
so and the requirement is represented
as a table so you can
see different requirements
and here is the requirements tree the
how to
decompose requirements into different
abstraction of level
and you can also see the requirements
diagram designer can
drag requirements elements
into the diagram
you can also drag the requirements from
model 3.
so you can drag it into the
diagram you can also create
different relations relationships
between requirements
so now we create another requirement
diagram
you drag a requirement
and you can also show the relationships
of this requirement so you can see
the other new requirements is showing
in this network diagram
okay in the model 3 we can build a
different
package
now we can conduct a
requirements relationship
so you can choose the first requirement
you can also check
which tab you want to send
so the uh um our product can show the
relationships between
different level requirements
so you can see how to
decompose plaques
over overall requirements
and you can also show the relationships
between
requirements and structure
and here we just show the system
system architecture you can see how to
decompose a a system block
there there are so many subsystems or
subsystem systems of systems
how to decompose a um
systems
and we can also show the requirements
the relationship
between requirements and structure
what is the pxs system is it a
ah it's a name of a
structure in in
nuclear domain okay
and here we can see the requirements and
you can link the requirements and
into the structure
so you can see what's the relationships
between requirements and
structure
and now we can create a
[Music]
table here requirement yeah
so you can see uh a block
[Music]
how many ports it has ah okay
so it's an interface control document
yes
yes we
yes we can see uh uh ibd
diagram so you can see uh in a
blog um how how this block
is composed and be composed of
different blocks
[Music]
so here this table can show the
interface between different blocks
housing can connect
and here is a par diagram
so we integrate matlab
there is a matlab file so you can drag
drag this file into our product
so it analyzes
and and as a
computational model
can you execute input and output
and can you execute it yes
so when you input different values
and it can compute
but the computation is done by matlab
right that's
the background as a
computational engine
and here we can see the
block how to satisfy a requirement
it's amazing even if everything is in
chinese
i can understand what what what is shown
because of
yeah because it's the smell compliant in
its shapes
and i know assist male and now is
uh sits about 2.0
so maybe this male has a very big
difference yes 2.0
yeah yes yes that will be a big change
yeah do you plan to implement
system l version 2 um yes we
we are we are studying uh cis male 2.0
so we are evaluating eight
uh okay whether we can support to 2.0
very good yeah and we can also
export the model on date into
excel
so that's the icd table in excel
yeah yes we can export the all
uh all of the model in our product
yeah if customer customer customer
need some date we can we can
export it
and do you have a rest interface
also for the tool so that you can access
via web services
now currently we didn't provide
web service api or services to
to to other and customers
okay that's all this is a very simple
brief
uh introduction of our our product
yeah very good so last thing we saw is a
document generation then right
yes yeah very good
fantastic yes okay we
we spent we spent about two or three uh
three years to to develop this product
so it's very um not
very um maturity
material yes we need a lot of
work to do and based on customers
requirement
and now we are trying to to
to discuss with our customers
we provide some customer customer
customized development for our customers
and how many people are developing on
this um
about 15 people
whoa yeah we are as a small team
yeah spent nearly
two two years two and a half years
all right yeah very good and is
the tool also available in in english
and so in other languages or is it only
available in chinese
um currently we're just providing a
chinese version uh if
uh if some foreign customers
uh want to um have a try we
we can provide an english version for
them
okay
and you said that you create customized
versions
of your tools so
is it only a configuration or is it a
real customized so
with special programmed stuff for for
the customer
sorry so is it if you have a customized
version
for one of your customers is it only a
special configuration or is it
uh do you have to write source code for
them
and to create a specific version for the
customer
okay and now we we don't provide a
source code to to our customers
based on our product but if our
requirement
is new we can provide not based on
our product we can provide source code
to customers
okay yeah and
uh is this graph the the only system l
modeling tool in china so
a chinese modeling tool yes
currently we are chinese too okay
yeah very good so
if we can have more discussions
like today we are very happy to
provide our service to foreign customers
so we can discuss together
how we can have more meetings like today
so we are very happy to provide our
services
to to foreign customers
yeah okay yeah maybe someone is
interested who's watching us
okay um
i have one more question about the tool
uh how's
the the model stored is it the file
on on the on your hard disk or is it in
a database
or is it on a server okay and now
our modeling tool is a
single singly
and it's just a software we start our
model and date
in the disk
yes and we
we we did a lot of um research
we tried to store our data into
no secure database for example
neo4j we can store our model into
a knowledge graph
we did a lot of research and demo
for that but now we didn't um
integrate it into our product
okay but but basically it's
possible then for example to store it in
neo4j
but for example yeah yeah
yes we did a lot of demos for that
we also integrate speech recognition
we the customer can ask a question
and then we translate it into different
text and we
analysis it we can search in
neo4j and give the answer answer to
customers
we did a lot of demos for that very
interesting yeah
yeah i read you uh also did some work in
the
not specific for this group but you you
also worked in the field of artificial
intelligence right
yeah yes that's what i feel well yeah
before this graph i um play a role of
ai researchers fellow
in a company for many years so we tried
two different
ai technologies for example and
machine learning and and and
knowledge graph so we did a lot of
research
but um if you want to landing the
ai in real project it's very
um a little difficult for
fun now right now yeah yeah
yeah i think it's in the beginning but
uh yes
it's it's a starting topic so i i uh
read more and more about it about ai in
combination with mbse
and so there's even a conference or a
workshop
here in europe uh it was held in in
spain
two years ago and last year it was due
to covert only virtually
uh so it's also supported by cosy
that's a that's a really interesting
combination
yeah yeah absolutely
yes so yeah if you want to and do ai
research you need um
more more date or models but for fse the
customers
it's just beginning to accumulate
models so you can represent your
knowledge experience into
model so you you need to accumulate
more models and dates but for
more chinese customers i think it's just
a beginning
for mbse there are not many
models not many data
in models so we have a long road to
to to to go i think
and after that you can do
many uh artificial intelligence
proprieties no we don't have very models
yeah i think that's an issue to have the
data for for ai technologies
yeah well but it will come
definitely
uh okay uh do you have any questions
online question are there any
live channels no live questions i think
we are a little bit early today
for the european listeners it's very
late for you
leo
[Laughter]
so we have no live questions today yeah
but thank you for being with us
was very interesting for me yeah thank
you so much
thank you for calling my attention yeah
yeah next time i'm in shanghai i will
call you
i'm very calm
yeah yeah yeah we met at the best conf
and then during a business trip i did
and i was on a vacation in shanghai but
then we
had no time to to match unfortunately
i was never in shanghai i also only was
once in
uh i don't know if i pronounced it right
in shenzhen
yeah um uh that was very
interesting uh to see and
yeah maybe i i make it to shanghai at
some time
is doing a lot of mbse projects
okay cool yeah so it's time for an mbse
conference in shanghai
[Music]
absolutely okay so tim
do you want to wrap up what do we have
yes
again and well normally
we
at the end we already published the the
next topic and the next date
but this time we don't have one so but
we are in the planning phase so we have
many many options
uh but nothing is final yet so
uh listen to our channels on linkedin
facebook
twitter and so on uh so we will publish
the next
episode as soon as we have the date
fixed and the guest of course um
yeah so yeah thanks to leo again
uh great to meet you again at least
virtually
and then the final thing christian
is of course like always
trust us we are systems engineers
good bye bye bye thank you
bye bye shall you bye bye thank you