Welcome to the 16th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
Today we take a look at
modeling of a sequence diagram
A sequence diagram depicts the exchange
of messages between properties
represented by the so-called lifelines
Let's look at it in our model
Our sequence diagram shows
a simple scenario
of our MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree
Actually the tree does not
include so many scenarios
but it's just a tree
The model element represented
by the whole sequence diagram
is called an interaction
Here the interaction is owned
by the system context element
The user sends a "SwitchOn" signal to
the "Enjoyment Control Unit"
It is an asynchronous message
Then the internal operation
"startFlashingProgram"
is called which starts a loop
to switch on and off the "Fairy Lights"
And in parallel, the lights enjoy a child
You can use sequence diagrams
for several purposes
For example, specify a test case
specify a communication protocol
demonstrate an example and so forth
So much for the 16th door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 16th of December
Goodbye
Bye-bye