welcome to the 16th store of our mbse
podcast advent calendar today we take a
look at modeling of a sequence diagram
a sequence diagram depicts the exchange
of messages between properties
represented by the so-called lifelines
let's look at it in our model
our sequence diagram shows a simple
scenario of our mbse podcast christmas
tree actually the tree does not include
so many scenarios but it's just a tree
the model element represented by the
whole sequence diagram is called an
interaction here the interaction is
owned by the system context element
the user sends a switch on signal to the
enjoyment control unit it is an
asynchronous message
then
the internal operation start flashing
program is called which starts a loop to
switch on and off the fairy lights and
in parallel the lights enjoy a child
you can use sequence diagrams for
several purposes for example specify a
test case specify a communication
protocol demonstrate an example and so
forth
so much for the 16th store of our nbc
podcast i'm red calendar and we wish you
a great 16th of december
goodbye bye