hello fellow systems engineers and
welcome back to a new podcast episode
we have a guest for the topic today
which is about ontologies and doll
and our guest today is fabian neuhaus
fabian would you like to introduce
yourself
hi um thank you very much for inviting
me my name is fabi my house
i work usually at the university in
marketbook and then could be the life
department
and i'm currently located in the
wonderful
city of portsmouth in the italian alps
where i am on a research project working
with colleagues here in
italy great so
and what exactly do you do at the
universities with magnavox or now in
bolton
well i mean i have the
mixed pleasure of teaching a computer
logic and uh theoretical computer
science but
uh my research areas are mostly in
ontology
all kinds of topics related to
ontologies
i and of course also
i was part of the group who developed
all i guess
that's also relevant for you inviting me
yes sure sure yeah fun fact
aside is that we are we three are all
germans
but we never met in germany only in the
united states at the omg meetings
well yeah so now we'll listen to three
germans trying to speak english for yeah
yeah so our listeners are used to it
like this laughing out loud shows also
so um so you're at a
computer science department but you are
not a computer scientist right you're a
philosopher no
indeed yes i'm a philosopher by training
phd in philosophy
and slowly migrated and i even worked as
a postdoc in a philosophy department in
buffalo for a while
and then slowly migrated first to list
which people might know as a
standardization
organization of the us and then came
back to work here in rugby book
and yeah so this is
why i have i mean ontologies are very
interdisciplinary area
not only because the ontologies
themselves are typical about something
else than computer science
right but also because
it draws a lot from logic from
philosophy um
well from other areas as well even in
linguistics
so that's you know by people like me who
don't really
originally come from computer science uh
often
migrate there and otherwise in the other
direction a lot of ontologists who are
really engineers or computer scientists
are very well versed in
uh philosophy so the very
interesting group of people who work in
this area yeah hopefully we'll
we are coming back to this philosophic
background of ontologies
uh in some minutes but um
a simple question to you uh what are
ontologies about
for somebody to explain it for somebody
who
never heard this term
well so there's an academic answer an
authority is
a fair specification of
some conceptualization and that's an
example for the
mission that doesn't help anybody
because
if you don't know what an ontology is
you you know for sure don't know what
the concept is
nobody knows that really and
so if i have to explain
what an ontology is i usually start off
with a glossary and say well think of a
glossary
and now you kind of rip the glossary
apart
in you know different pieces and because
you reorganize it completely
um so the first thing is you you know a
lottery typically has
um different is focused on terms
and ontologies are not so much focused
on terms but more on the concepts or
classes
that are important so you know
in in english for example you have
different words for sweets
right and uh well in the uk i think it
would be they would be called sweets in
the
u.s it will be called candy and in
australia
australian english it would be called
lollies and then the
glossary you might get different entries
for each of them
it's alphabetically ordered so the
glossary
typically is alphabetically ordered so
you want to find
s under s you will find sweets under the
l you find lollies and
maybe they're cross references and then
on in our ontology that kind of
the labels aren't that important but the
concept are important so
there will be one entry and we'll say
maybe it will don't even have a word for
it but
rather a number and say this concept is
called in australia
lollies and in uk it's called sweets etc
cetera in german it's called
and then french is you know okay so it's
called in french right
it's it's really the the concept in the
center not so much the word
okay and
can can you also say that uh
the relationship between those terms uh
are a part of an ontology
definitely yeah so the the the first
thing if you would want to go from a
glossary is kind of focus more on the
concepts and disambiguate
the the words and the next thing is you
basically order the concepts
hierarchically so you get a taxonomy
that would be in my opinion that still
would be an ontology
but that would be the next step so that
you you know
uh for example you would have a link
between the concepts of
um or the class of sweets to the class
of confectionary because confectionary
is the superclass
of sweet right and in different kinds of
you would have different sub classes of
sweets so basically instead of having
ordered alphabetically you get a in this
particular case
it would be a graph maybe a tree
structure ideally a tree structure but
most likely a graph of um
of concept and that's that would be
so that would be the taxonomy and some
people already would say taxonomy is
kind of an ontology i'm
you know well the borderline case and
then you would maybe add some additional
relationships like
you could talk about what are the
ingredients
right so you would have not just uh you
would have links between concepts like
you know the main ingredients of the
sweet is sugar
you for other things you would have
password relations
so a layer cake has different uh
belgian praline has uh has a filling
right um so additional information and
all of this things i should say
are not expressed just by you know
arrows on a piece of paper but in some
logical language so that would be
distinguishing
uh characteristic from
let's say uml diagrams
you know most of what i just said you
could do in the email class diagram
but the language which you're using here
is is going to be underpinned by some
logic the reason for that is that the
neonatology so just coming to what's the
purpose of it you want to have
interoperability
between not only humans and humans but
also between humans and machines and
machines and machines
so you want to capture the semantics
um in the machine interpretable way
so that is where i would say the
real ontology starts so everything you
know if you just think of
you start with the glossary so basically
you add the your order differently you
look as
you can look at the concepts you put in
additional
relationships and then you do all of
that
in the language which is a logical
language and if you have done that you
have mythology
okay so what what's the difference
between a concept and a term
is there a difference so you said that
that
sweets and candy is not it's not a
concept that's
these are terms in a glossary for
example and
now they're grouped in a concept but
where's
the difference between concept and term
well if
you have two sentences or let's say
we take bread roll
bread roll and butcher i mean for the
english speakers is one translation of
breadfall in german
so uh each of them are words in
this case different languages but the
express shared
something which is a clear concept
right that's the it's basically that
watch when you go from one sentence
if you went translate well you know the
justification why you choose that
translation and you wouldn't say you
know something completely different
is because you say well this one means
the same in english as it means in
german so
you can maybe i shouldn't use the word
concept i could have just said meaning
the problem is meaning is even more
weight
or problematic many
multi-faceted than concept i mean
concept
is hard to understand meaning is even
harder to to get
okay we could have a whole i mean a
whole podcast on
what's this meaning uh of the of the
sentence it's uh it's a very fascinating
and really multifaceted topic
so this is often and that's probably
also
you know sometimes people say
mythologies are used to capture
the meaning of the terms
and that's true and false at the same
time
because it really depends on what you
mean by meaning
okay so
let's assume we have an ontology
what can i do with it
well it depends it depends really on the
opponent you have
that's uh let's look at a particular
example so the most
successful ontology out there in terms
of users i think and also of
influence is the gene ontology
now the gene ontology from a magician's
point of view which i'm
more or less is a rather boring monology
because it doesn't have nice axioms it's
not very strongly exomatized compared to
other approaches
but it's it is successful because
um it's it's uh involves
solving a really big problem for the
biologists
and in still solving the problem um that
they faced when they
produced a lot of data so the the
problem they i mean in the 90s when
when they started to develop it they had
this huge amount of genomic data
right and every so you
you could look at the genome of mice and
of
various plants and of course of humans
and you
and you could uh find out that you know
this
genome is able
to express this kind of protein and
that's protein
placed in these roles in these kinds of
processes and
they were generating tons of i mean tons
of papers
and nobody could read these papers
anymore i mean there is too much
and if you were an expert in mouse
stuff you wouldn't be able to be to link
it to the
to the stuff which was done on plants
but the same genes are involved in some
sense of
the same and of course and ultimately
we're interested in humans because it's
all medically irrelevant
so in order to organize knowledge
they developed the gene ontology which
is a controlled vocabulary
which you can use to annotate
the literature and annotate the data
from from the very and
that allowed them uh first of all
to just get hold of the literature so we
oh fabian you're breaking openly to find
relevant
oh sorry but i can't do anything about
it yeah we know you're back
um okay
so the and but the the important thing
it was to them that they could then
automatically integrate
the various uh
databases they had about results
and without i mean each database
of this you know was individually owned
or whoever created it
and of course everybody has their own
database schema fitting for their
computer system in their environment but
um the andrologies allow them to
basically
integrate that data without having to
physically change them from it you know
the way their database worked
that was that was the next you know that
was the
immediate payoff and now they have tools
which basically just
automatically you know you you for
example analyze
um what kinds of proteins are available
in some
you know snippets of tissue and it will
automatically use that information about
what is there to
link it to the processes to biological
processes
which are mentioned in the ontology and
then will automatically tell you okay
what is going on
here and this so you you it's basically
now used for knowledge generation and
that's just one
one of many users so it's really
making data enjoyable it's one of the
main
use cases now you mentioned the example
of genes
i remember i i started to read a book
from barry smith about bfos and i think
it was
the example is it possible or do i mix
up things
um it could be i mean barry i used to
work for barry and i used to work for
barry when he
uh started the oboe well i mean
he was one of the many founders i mean
he's
he was the german told you expect
so it would be make absolute sense that
uses that example as well
okay
i think autologies are also used in the
context of
semantics web right so i think that was
the first time i heard of ontologies
yeah so the semantic web is an
interesting case for
when you have something in mind
and the idea fails but the
results are still useful so the semantic
web the
the idea was created the the original
idea was before google
and we didn't find anything on the
internet so the idea was basically you
would
put metadata on your on your websites
and then which is representing this
web ontology language and then
clever agents would use automatic
reasoning in order to decide
whether what you're currently looking at
uh
if you look for something that a
particular website
would be good for you you know whether
it has the answer
and that's original vision i think it's
safe to say
failed i mean google just solved that
problem
using completely different technologies
but
um but the uh first of all the
the technology was was developed there
like all the weaponry language of ldf
and other things
were suddenly used very useful so
partially used in the biology world but
also linked up
data was then the next development where
we said okay it's not so much about the
semantic web in the sense original sense
but more
linking linking data sets
so um yeah and in that case the in this
semantic web is you have rdf which is
represent just a way of representing the
data in forms of triples
and um typically what the iris that are
used in these triples
come are coming from the control
vocabulary that's
then an ontology but the ontologies
that you see in that domain and that's
why i said
said you know what you can do with an
ontology kind of depends
what how your ontology looks like the
ontologies that you that are used in a
semantic web are typically looking quite
differently
from the ones but
yeah and maybe um another question
before we come to doll
so we mentioned in the beginning that
ontologies have a
philosophic background and
maybe you can give us in some sentences
a hint what what the origins or what the
roots
of authorities are and why are they in
to fight in philosophy
well philosophers were always interested
in the question what
what is there and i mean the natural
philosophy
uh the inheritance of that natural
philosophy are now sitting in the
physics department still wondering what
is there
you know talking about string theory and
uh
and the of course philosophers in the
greek world like our startups didn't
really do
string theory uh but uh you know had
similar questions and then came up with
categorizations
of uh of uh you know what is there
and um these categories
um these the idea of categorizing and
thinking systematically
what categories of things there are is
um is something which helps you to
organize the ontology so you know
that's typically when i teach my
students uh ontology i start with them
telling them the technology like here's
all now
that's like giving somebody you know
chessboard
and say telling them yeah this is how
the pieces move that doesn't mean that
you know
really how to play chess you know now
you have just you need to
fill the ontology with content and the
question is always where do i start you
know where
how do i um how do i organize the
content in the ontology
which is and uh
so many people use upper level ontology
so called upper level ontologies which
give you kind of a
structure which you can reuse like the
basic formula
you mentioned earlier from barry smith
and the um
the the this this upper level ontologies
are typically
inspired from philosophy so
there is i mean i'm um also
i have the lofty title of vice president
of the international association of
uh consul for ontology and its
applications and
we are regularly uh organizing a
conference this year again
by the way um where
four applied controlledly and basically
a third of the people
or the papers that are submitted there
are usually more philosophical
and then other people looking more at
the
you know how do you apply this then for
more
you know specific so that's really an
interesting thing where
the more philosophical domain can
interact with
uh you know people who have concrete
problems
that they want to solve
okay um a few days ago i
i found a website about the iof
the industrial ontologies foundry do you
know
that one um it looks very interesting
i know of it but i have not been
involved i know
people who are involved in it but sorry
not
okay i know bearish this is involved
michael gruner got involved
okay so this is really a serious thing
i have things though okay it wasn't true
it looked very interesting but i thought
well just the website well the people
who are involved are definitely
very serious people yeah okay very good
know what they're doing
yeah there's also a subgroup
systems engineering so that's uh yeah
sounds very interesting
so okay maybe
we switch over to doll and uh
from my point of view i can use doll
when
tim thought about a concept and i
thought about a concept
and they have some links and we want to
bring it together
is this correct can i use dole for this
well if you just talk about the
individual concepts
i would just that that just would
typically that means you you want to
build an ontology together and then you
don't need doll then you built this
ontology together um
now doll is a language
a meta kind of meta language which is
designed
to be help people to reuse ontologies
not
to build individual ontologies but you
will use some
the problem with ontologies or one
problem with ontologies is that they are
typically
rather expensive to build because it
requires domain expertise
they are usually monolithic
and um that makes it hard
to reuse for them to be reused because
they're these monolithic
blobs and doyle
is um was intended to be used to
structure your ontologies to modify
existing ontology so that you can adapt
them for your
purposes and then use building
existing building blocks and them
together
two bigger ontologies
and um also define
constraints on the interaction between
different modules so that
when somebody changes one module
you can have checks whether this change
uh
you know interacts with the rest of the
modules in a way which is not intended
so that's that's um that's one aspect
the other aspect is that we are have
the situation that many more languages
are used in reality or in in the world
than just
owl or one single language and they have
good
good reasons for using different
languages and
doll also wanted to tackle that
basically enable people to
develop heterogeneous ontologies and um
models and specifications that's in the
title
right so the um but it's not uh
yeah if you think of something like
um i'm not sure whether you're aware of
the
time and date vocabulary it's an omg
standard
yeah yeah yeah that is
they also had that idea that we use
basically different languages
um um
definitely owl and common logic
numerical and class diagrams but also
sbvr
the problem there is if you just have
these languages next to each other and
modules in different languages next to
each other you don't um you don't know
whether they fit
if somebody changes something in one
module and somebody changes something in
the other module
there's no formal connections between
those i mean even
you even can have a problem within
different uml
diagram types you know if you have a
complex model using different diagram
types
that as we see the connections between
these diagrams is relatively loose
and so the one other
problem adults designed to tackle is
using this
several languages at the same time
modules in different languages
in the context of systems we currently
have the challenge now we have system
version one and now we work on system l
versus version two
so theoretical we could use dull
to define a mapping between social lv
one and this might be two or to
validate that the system will be one
concepts are also in system rv2
no because system l is not a very
compliant language
so dollar ism is working for
ontology languages or modeling languages
which have a
formal semantics because ultimately
about the meaning of things
the these constraints that you check
well you they need to be clearly and
formally mathematically defined
and that you do with the that you only
have with the
um if you have a formal semantics so i
know that there are
i mean there are parts of uml
which for which you have that it's not
part of the official uml center but
there's fuml
and the doll
standard itself has some
mapping from uml to
chrome logic which provides this form
former semantics
but as far as i know nobody ever has uh
tried to do that for the whole
system so in order to do this formal
mapping
you you know never in computer science
nobody you know you don't get anything
for free
you if you want to have if you ever want
to have a machine check
whether what you did is nonsense you
need to
formally declare what is you know the
meaning or semantics of your language
if you don't have that you can't check
you can't use these logical tools to
check it
so right unfortunately it's not that
easy
maybe we have to clarify what doll
stands for
i guess some of our listeners are not
aware what
omg the distributed ontology modeling
and specification language so arguably
the
acronym should be more complex but
you know it's hard to pronounce uh
pronounce it if you put all
the other letters in there
and it's an omg specification right
it's an oven yes it has been
it's an official omg specification since
2018.
and is it also planned uh that it will
be an
iso specification so some omg
specifications are
uh also iso no not iso specification but
iso standards
well let's let's put it this way we
started all
trying to do the speci you know
standardize the content of the dollar
standard in iceland
and we were so frustrated with the iso
process that we went
to omg so
i myself don't feel the inclination to
go back to iso it just
you know like
but there's a relationship between omg
and isola so many omg specifications are
iso standards
and that process is much easier
uh than to start from the scratch at iso
so uml is an iso stand that system is an
iso standard
so maybe could also be an iso standard
if somebody wants to do it fine
i i uh not i mean um
yeah it's it's really not my highest
priority really
because i mean ultimately ultimately um
you know i'm working academics so i'm
i'm kind of in the
in the business of creating new ideas
and
you know working on the same old ideas
is not very
appealing to me so um
and we're also non-academics
organizations involved in the dollar
specification
with the business interests in the
dollar standard
i mean the pure academic no
i mean the texting requirement or to
to understand that that you have support
of
of uh industry um i mean one uh
i mean i wouldn't want to start to list
them because i forget
and surely forget somebody and then
there will be inside
obviously mentioned in the omg standard
itself has supported it
uh but uh you know for example i to just
name one person because she was
particularly
as lisa campbell um he uh
you know this standard would have never
happened without her
he was extremely supportive and helped
us
and you know she's of course has her own
company
plans to use bulk
so they plan to use dollar do they
already have a
doll tool no i think the only doll tool
i mean the yeah the only doll tool which
tries to capture the whole standard is
something we developed in
macro book but uh that's an academic
tool that's
not um you know it's not something you
would
give out for into an industry so we are
hoping that that industry will adopt uh
solve at least parts of the i mean the
whole standard is really a little bit
challenging i think
i have to admit um you know things grow
but many import the functionalities
which
um allow you basically to
to support a modular development of
ontologies
i think is actually something which
which is not that complicated
implemented
okay maybe we can switch
to a question which
again regards systems engineering
because we are the
mbse podcast and we are
very aware of that you are not a systems
engineer
but yes um in in the field of systems
engineering you
hear the term ontologies very often and
yeah what i would like to discuss with
both of you is um
could be ontologies helpful for systems
engineering for example to bring
together the concept of different
engineering domains
or to bring together the concepts of
different processes in in the systems
engineering process
so could could that be a way to use
autologies
well to me
um so i'm working among other things
with
uh people who uh
well i'm working with the open energy
modeling community that's open energy
ontology
um so this is probably closer to your
community than
maybe the biology they are you know
like it says in the title they are
interested in models or energy systems
usually on the level of you know let's
say cities or countries
uh not much individual plants
and um whenever you have five of them in
a room
don't even need five we have three in
the room and
they try to communicate with each other
they use different terminology i mean
it's
it's just that's that's the fact of life
in all disciplines i mean i've worked
with many different
different disciplines just that's you
know anthropologies are always
you're always working with some other
domain experts
and um as soon as um they
i mean one important thing they they
uh you know the most basic thing they
have to do is create a scenario when
they're doing the modeling
and you know use the scenario
as input for the model now you would
think that
they would know what the scenario is
they could
you know it took them forever to come up
with the definition of the scenario
which which half satisfies
most of them and it's kind of important
for them because one of the things is
that they want to re
compare the results of
what they are simulating so the idea of
what is a scenario what's part of the
scenario what is parameters but how do
parameters
relate to the scenario although that
needs to be controlled if you have a
controlled environment to exchange
information about the results of your
modeling
models now i'm not sure you know
i assume that is the problem that will
resonate with
any um any engineering problem if you
have a complex product
different people model different aspects
of it people different people
story about different aspects right some
people design it some people have to
uh think about the components
get get the components others have to
assemble it all of that leads to
different perspective on the same
products
and all of these people have different
have an impact
incomplete view of the product and of
the whole process
and they have to exchange information
and
use different terminologies so
you always have that ontologies are
basically that that's the the main
purpose of ontology is trying to get
interoperability between
people and their computers with but i
think that
was a sorry tim but i think there was a
very
a very good example um with a project of
an interdisciplinary project with
different engineers
because it's exactly not
sufficient to just create a glossary
yeah but i asked myself how
how really can an ontology help them so
for example if i look at the roadmap of
this industrial ontology foundry
and the systems editing working group
according to the roadmap they
would like to pick uh iso standards like
15 to 88
that's a system changing iso standard
and 42
0 10 for example and create an systems
ending ontology
and so if i have a systems editing term
like
system architecture for example i can
look in the in the iso standard
and find a definition which is very well
not very helpful i would say that it
says a system architecture
are fundamental concepts of a system
which sounds true but
not helpful so what really is it and
now i can look in the system generating
anthology and then i get a clear answer
or how i i don't know how it would work
[Music]
but if it was developed by a clever
ontologist they would have
realized that that isn't a helpful
definition and hopefully
um put in a better definition but i mean
that's
you know obviously
you know that you don't need to you know
you could also improve the
quality of the glossary you don't need
an ontology for just adding a better
definition
not the the so
one reason why
glossaries often don't work especially
if you don't
you aren't in a hierarchical situation
but you have different people
who are not you can't tell people what
to do
uh is that people don't like to give up
their terminology
so an anthology by just not working i
mean
um let's say that people use different
terms for the same thing
of course in an ideal world you could
just tell everybody use the same word
and then you will understand each other
right but
that's not going to happen i mean
there's just people like their
terminologies and they are not you know
unless you force them
uh you're not and usually you don't have
the authority to do so
they will just use the terminology you
want since an ontology
will basically have an usually an
alphanumeric identifier for the concept
and then different labels you can have
in
the gui you choose the labels which are
suitable for for the person who's
you know working with the gui and uh
you know they they you can display one
set of labels to one group and another
set of
labels to other group and everybody is
happy they don't complain
because they see the terminology they're
used to and they're still
working together so this is purely on
the human to human level
but more importantly you usually have
data associated with
it all right with the with the things so
you're using the you will use the
control vocabulary
in different ways either to annotate
just the
relational database or maybe you even
have an um
a graph database or you have a idf
triple store
and represent the in that case the
triple store and the basically the
ontology terms are directly in the data
um so you by just using these
um uh by using the
uh ontology you can easily integrate
the various data stats
without you know loss of or
without any problems but it's very hard
to do that in an audio format it's much
easier to show
[Laughter]
on the human to human level if i would
like to use an ontology
um it's typically by using a tool
and i look in the tool to to read an
anthology so it's it's not another pdf
to find something
typically your you your end user won't i
mean
you won't see the ontology i mean unless
you
i can't think of many reasons why you
want somebody to see the ontology
it's more that it's working in the
background
so the let's let's say
let me give a completely different use
case let's say you want just to
use an ontology to support semantic
search so
somebody uses uh and let's say you have
a lot of photos annotated with terms on
anthology
you're locking your the thing you're
looking for is cute
dogs right in the picture
in the answer and so if you if you have
an ontology behind it you can
enrich it semantically by you know if
there is
any german shepherds and picture
annotated with german shepherd
that ontology knows german shepherds or
dogs you can use it
um you uh you know enrich the
original search that is a very stupid
use of an ontology
in this case you don't even need any
agreement or
controlled vocabulary but that's an
example of the use of an anthropology
where the end user would never know that
there is an ontology
which is that you know the entries are
just happy to see
you talk whether that there was label
dog or
german shepherds didn't care right so i
think
usually anthologies are not displayed
to be
to the end user okay
so we are already
42 minutes on our way
yes so 42 is a good time 42 minutes
42 is a great number
yeah so thank you very much fabian for
being with us
answering our questions uh without
without
yeah tim um what can we expect for the
next weeks
uh we have a
an episode scheduled for may 25th
if i remember it correctly um
[Music]
there's no title yet but we will publish
it soon
and you already know the guests and we
all will also publish that soon
and maybe we have a episode before that
um so we have to figure out if you get a
guest
and a date um yeah so that's the plans
for the next
four weeks all right so
don't forget to subscribe to the channel
so you would not
uh would not miss another episode
and um so
like always we just can say trust us
we are systems engineers goodbye
bye