[Music]
so
[Applause]
[Music]
welcome to the next episode of the mbse
podcast
yeah today there are only two people on
the screen so that's because tim is my
guest today and we will talk about let's
say a hot system l2 topic for all the
sysml1 practitioners
so if you are already using suseml1 you
might have the question what happens
when sml 2 comes up and can i go on
using my ssmlv1 models and
can can i translate them can i translate
them back maybe and that's what we want
to talk today with
tim
yeah and as you might might know tim and
i we are both
members of the system submission team
and tim has also a track lead and it's
exactly the track lead which
which thinks and uh yeah it handles the
topic of
the system l v2 or 1 2v2 transformation
so tim
how how did you become direct lead
of this track
and the first work i think began in 2014
or so if i remember it correctly
uh
we had a podcast about it uh about the
history of system i think it was the
first second one right correct correct
but it wasn't german i think no i don't
know
well in any case it's been a very long
time uh so when the system lb2
submission team was officially set up
after the the omg published the request
for proposal the rfp for system will be
2 in
um it was quite apparent that the chairs
of the system lv1 would also work on the
transformation
so even i became the track lead so i'm
not the only triplet uh even i are the
track leads for the transformation and
well which is named track number three
okay so that means that the necessity
necessity or for model transformation or
translation or whatever it is we will
talk about this later on um was
identified very early and it
was
a mandatory requirement i guess in the
system lv2
right
yeah right yeah so the the system lv2
rfp is a list of requirements for system
lv2
um and to be precise there's a
requirement to develop a system lv2
profile for uml
and that requirement also says that
an equivalent function capability can be
demonstrated by mapping the uml meter
classes and the system stereotypes
between system lv2 and v1 so in short by
a system we want to v2 transformation
so
well that that was the starting point
and we started with the development of
the smart v2 profile in 2017 so
five years ago um
but that's uh
the the system lv2 profile for uml or
yes you mean track four ah okay yeah
yeah uh track three so it's uh
well like the smelly one it's a uml
profile it was the idea to develop as a
small v2 profile of course it's it's
only a subset of this as well v2
um
so yeah we started with that and well it
was not very easy
uh because this isn't uh we too abstract
syntax
so the the data structure of the
elements is quite different from system
lv1
so we had to do some
well very
terrible twisting to define this is
maybe two elements as stereotypes of um
and
um
well that would have been a very huge
task for the tools to present these
strange
stereotypes to the user so that the user
can really work with it so
yeah that was
a big challenge that time and well
and on the other side we might have been
able to turn well a few blind eyes and
for example just rename the system uh
we won block to part definition and
versus maybe two profiler which is
roughly the equivalent this is maybe two
part definition and block
um
but then we we would mix up the
terminology well so the the content
concepts are similar but they're not the
same and it would be fuzzy to call
something part definition which it
actually is not so
yeah
so in retrospect i would say that
developing this maybe two profiles
it's not reasonable possible to do that
and another problem is we we had very
few resources for the development
uh and at that time there
uh well only the two of us and the
transformation was still on our to-do
list so
i think it was about two years or three
years ago
that we decided to concentrate only on
the transformation then
okay and that that means that
nowadays there are more than you two
guys
no
it's it's basically just if and me um
working in track free um
and well both of us have a full-time job
which
we earn our money um so
yeah it's uh the lack of resources is a
big problem
from time to time we get some help from
others so for example in our weekly
telecons um typically ed joins us at
side of this
uh and helps us with some questions we
have about the system i'll be two meter
model no yeah okay
okay very interesting how this this
stuff is organized but uh let's go a
little bit in in on the technical
background now so
what's behind this v12v2 transformation
yeah so the the official delivery of our
work is quite boring
it's uh it's a transformation
specification which means paperwork no
it's it's a pdf
which is finally a part of the standard
uh but but we also develop a pilot
implementation of the transformation so
it's not the system will be two part
implementation it's it's another one
implementation of the transformation
because otherwise it won't be possible
to verify it no
these complex rules of mappings and etc
so we need to to test it
um so well the challenge was then how to
do that and in general how to do that
and of course uh with the lack of
resources we have
is
to develop
to software engineering stuff and so on
so our solution um
is
a tool chain
so we we specify the transformation
in a class model
uh with ocl constraints
and we use the cameo systems modeler
tool and the chamber cloud server for
that so
um
so thanks to the soul
for supporting this this will be to work
they also support the other teams with
their tools very helpful
and with openmbe
um
we completely generate then the
specification pdf document uh from this
model um
and by the way the complete system maybe
two specifications generated with
openmbe
and our our transformation is
only an nx
in one of the documents
a couple of episodes ago we had
christelle from laserjpl as i uh and he
talked
about openmbe yeah and i think we also
talked about the doctrine mechanism yeah
right
yeah so um well that's the toolchain how
we define the transformation and create
the the document
uh well it's pure model based um
and we use the same model
um
to which we use to generate the
specification document to generate the
the code for the pilot implementation
okay and
so first we we export the model to xmi
to get access to it
in eclipse
eclipse cannot directly access the
timber cloud server and so on and then
we use the the eclipse
epsilon technology
these are java based
uh scripts for um
for model engineering tasks
and we use epsilon to generate uh atl
code from the transformation model
and atl stands for atlas transformation
language uh which is used for
model-to-model transformation that's
it's a
framework to do that so and we create
of the atl code so it's not necessary to
do any
manual updates um so we export
from
from from cameo to xmi and then uh we
click a button to generate the atl and
then
that's it well then we can run the atl
code to transform this maybe one models
to assist my region
okay and did you already try to
to do it also from let's say an
enterprise architect or rhapsody xmi
so would would this work in theory and
in practice
um
well in theory it works
because the input format of our
transformation is xmi and which is an
omg standard so if the modeling tool
like enterprise architect or rhapsody
can export the model to uh xmi which is
conformed with the standard
and we can use it as an input for
transformation um
yeah yeah we have not tried that um
because we we don't need it enough for
our work and well again the lack of
resources but
would be quite interesting to do that
but it cost only
uh
half an hour also to test this yeah i
think there are plenty of guys who who
would model a
yeah a system l1 model in in the tools
and and provide you the xmi
yeah so but well we need as an input we
need xmi conform to the standard and of
course
the the system l model in the xmi must
also be conformed to the system standard
yeah yeah so my fear would be that
you get in the same
troubles
why xmi exchange does not work between
tools
so but but maybe i'm wrong prove me
wrong please prove me wrong
okay so we have a model to model
transformation input is xmi so what what
is the target format then
uh so the the pilot implementation uh
maps yeah system lv1 xmi to system lv2
xmi
so the target format is again xmi and
system lb2
is not based on uml anymore but
on the kernel modeling language carmel
and but carmel and sysmol v2
are still based on moth the meter object
facility and xmi is a serialization of
morph so
we can
serialize the small v2 models to xmi so
our target format is again xmi
okay and is there already some kind of
validation suite for the system lv2 xmi
uh no
no so we
we get the xmi and that's
it
yeah and it's i guess yeah it's it's as
terrible human readable as it is in
system lb1 because yeah it's xml
and
if you can't validate can you verify it
yeah that's a challenge
the xmi is
well it's more a machine readable format
than a human readable format
of course a small xmi yeah you can check
some things but
even small models create very large xmis
so that's a nightmare
um
yeah and we solved that by again with
the eclipse
epsilon technology um
we have developed another tool
uh an xmi to system lv2 textual notation
transformation so
we take the system v2 xmi
um and transform it to system v2 texture
notation
and now we have a human readable format
and we can use it
as an input for the system v2 pilot
implementation which checks if the
syntax is correct um and we can even
generate the graphical notation then
again with the pilot implementation so
finally we can see the diagrams of
system lv1 input models and the diagrams
of this v2 output model
as far as they are available in the
jupyter notebook implementation or
the plateau ml thing right okay and of
course there are lots of issues but for
example in in system everyone often
elements have no name
an association and has no name and so on
but
if we
create the system lv2 texture notation
then we need a name
for the elements
okay so um i just saw we have uh the
first question in our live chat
so we have a question from mark and
he asks do you foresee other data
formats taking the place of xmi for
example json-ld
uh so not for the transformation
that will be based on
the transformation of our pilot
implementation the transformation itself
which will be part of the standard is uh
well transformational rules written in
ocl
um
but for seasonal v2 yes yeah there's of
course for example the json format and
the context mouse this is my v2 api
and
it's
ongoing work to define and
exchange format
yeah yeah okay i think this is very very
important to
to distinguish
yeah
but
to be to be honest there both are
exchange formats so xmi could be an
exchange format but
yeah a json-based exchange format is
is available in the api
services specification or the pilot
implementation so
there you can you can have a look if you
did not already
okay so um
[Music]
where have we been we have been ah okay
we get xmi out and then you transform it
in the system lv2 syntax and the
textural syntax you check it if it's uh
syntax is okay and so on
um but there there's still some doubt is
it correct so
how do you do you handle this manually
yeah so well the the system will be two
pilot implementation can verify if if
it's valid system lb2 but of course it
cannot verify if it's the correct output
of our transformation
um so well in the end we have to
manually validate if it's the expected
output okay no no no
um
it reminds me of our paper about doll
and and so on but it's another topic
it'll all
also be
interesting in this area but uh yeah
yeah it's a
completely different topic yes and and
lack of resources and oh yeah oh yeah
okay so um
by the way we had an episode about doll
correct yeah with fabulous yeah yes
exactly
okay so um
let's let's have a closer look to the to
those two languages so um
i think
some of our listeners already know that
uh and you also uh told us before
that
we do not rely on the uml anymore we
rely on kermal now
and that also means that the concepts of
the languages are different and um
now
there might arise the question
is there
is there a concept in system else two
for every ssml one concept it says
successor and and so to say system l2 is
uh like system l1 plus extra stuff or
how can i imagine that
well the goal is that we can map
everything
uh so that systematic tool
covers everything
so every capability of the smell we want
um
and for most of the system we won
elements well the mapping is quite
apparent so
a package and system lv1 is mapped to
our packages as well v2
um it's even the same name
or a block is mapped to part definition
and so forth
um
but
some system lv1 elements have
rarely used properties for which there's
no
direct corresponding element and the
small v2
so for example this is where we one
block has a boolean property named is
encapsulated which can be used to
indicate that the block is used as a
black box
it has not an impact it's just the
scripture if not to say it's
encapsulated it's a black box don't look
inside
and in this way v2 there's no
corresponding element so
um and what we do
for such properties is that we define
in systematic two then user specific
metadata
which is attached to to the model
element so
um
so we use this for is encapsulated we
transform the block to part definition
and attach this meter data with the
encapsulated information
ah okay yeah yeah because it's
encapsulated it's not a
property of a block it's a property of
the stereotype block right the property
of the stereotype block yeah
okay yeah yeah
yeah so we can resolve that
one but currently there are some
elements where we don't know yet how to
map them
okay
and do you have
other
other examples so
yeah so for for the elements we cannot
map
for example
um
in systematic one um
we have the the actions uh in the
activity world
and uh system v1 or respectively uml
that he finds around
many 30 to 40 different action kinds not
like the call behavior action
actions and signal action
and so on action
um
and we can map the commonly used ones
like call behavior action but still need
to analyze the mapping for for some
others so
um
another example is package merge
you cannot map package much at the
moment so you see it's mainly the more
exotic constructs that worry us but uh
well
also for for them we need a solution
and did you did you find a completely
missing language concept and if yes how
how would this be translated
um
i don't think there are completely
missing concepts
there are some missing elements i like
this encapsulated and
we can resolve that
but completely missing concepts i don't
think that there are any but however we
i must admit that we have not analyzed
the whole language in detail yet uh so
for example the interaction
uh so the sequence diagram stuff is
still on our to-do list so we think we
can map it well there are corresponding
concepts in systematic too uh but i'm
not sure about all the details so the
detailed elements of of interaction if
they can be mapped
okay
okay and
uh our
so so you already mentioned it so the
behavioral models of system l2 are
examples of this right so um
yeah let me think
so they are defined differently than in
in seasonal v1 you can you can
model the same
thing but
it's different yeah
yeah so you have in the end the same
semantic of your
the constructs are completely
different now so for example the system
will be two uh
we want activities
they are based on the
token semantics
and the token semantics does not exist
in system lv2
um
activities exist in system lv2 uh well
they are named action definitions and
this will be too but they are not based
on a token
right mm-hmm
correct so we we map now the system l
uh we want activities to system early
two elements
uh that represent then the same flows of
the same meaning
the model but a completely different
construct so
yeah yeah okay got it got it
okay so um
let's
switch a little bit to an another
view on on this uh on this topic so um
we'd already talked about we want to
translate something from one language in
another one some
times we said oh we have to
transform it somehow so
what what do we have a transformation or
translation
yeah that's a good question
and
it depends how you define a
transformation and translation
so
for me translation is more
more a one-to-one mapping like you find
in natural language dictionaries for a
word in language a you find a word in
language b
or maybe also some alternatives or so
um
so i can translate and translate
the words
very well then but if i would translate
a whole text
in this way
the result is typically
bumpy to wrong
like the the computer-based translations
many years ago
yeah
so
then i need an additional transformation
so which means i have to build other
constructs in the target language which
depends on on the context
do you have an example for this
uh
yeah maybe a good example to stay with
the natural languages are perhaps
sayings
some can be translated uh others
well for others it's rather
very funny confusion yeah yes so
for example
well it's easy to understand the
following if you know english and german
but you know one language is difficult
but for example the english saying it's
raining cats and dogs
that would probably be understood if
translated directly into german but
would be very
irritating yeah yeah translating it
literally would uh yeah
yeah so in german you would say in
german as
cuban which translates directly into the
english
it rains out of
buckets which is also a picture which
might be a little bit
more natural than writing cats and dogs
but yeah it could also be irritating
yeah yes exactly yes and there are many
more examples um and which reminds me of
the great conversation i had with john
siegel of the omg many years ago
we wrote many emails on technical stuff
but we also often introduce ourselves
each other to sayings in english and
in german if what happens when you
translate them directly it was very
funny um
okay but another example is in german
the coup from ice cream
which means in english to get the cow
from the eyes
which means uh solving the problem yeah
yes exactly
okay nice nice so but we did not i think
we did not answer you did not answer my
question is it is it a transformational
translation
uh so for for the sayings you need a
transformation i would say
the translation so that which is for me
more the direct mapping uh that does not
work so yeah
transformation and for sml
and for system it's a transformation
it's also a transformation okay yeah
yeah so um
yeah i guess so transformation so
although some
some elements can be very directly
mapped like package to package and so on
um
we i think we have all we always have to
create more elements in the target so in
system lv2
uh so for example each element is is in
the name space
now and in system v1 this is defined by
a property so if if a block a
is
in a package
then this is specified in the property
of the package in the media level
and in system v2 it is a relationship
called membership
additionally so it's
it's yeah that's that's a good example
here
yeah yeah okay cool
and
and this transformation uh is it a
one-way street or can i also get sysmail
v2 models into system lb1
um
no you can't so so our transformation
which will be part of the
system rv2 standard this is a one way um
and
well if the system v2 is is much more
expressive than system lv1
so
many constructs cannot be mapped at all
but
if we take
a system lb2 model
which contains only concepts of system
lv1
so for example a result of our
transformation
so we transform this way we want to
assist my v2 and would like to transform
this back to this maybe one
uh in theory this would partially work
but
there are cases where the reverse
mapping is not unique
okay and you can't ensure that
you really have the same semantics then
uh
or or do you have any any example to
clarify that
well an example uh
currently working on that one is um
are the power properties uh that's an
example and system will be one they're
typically defined using the composition
relationship
um
so we have these typical system
breakdown structure block definition
diagrams these trees
with the composition relationship which
is formerly an association
relationship
and
now it gets a little bit tricky
and it doesn't apply universally but
normally we do not map this composition
relationship so this association
to system lb2
so to put it simply a block
so we have a block a compositional
relationship and a part property
and this may be one becomes a part
definition and a participant will be two
so we we omit the association
okay
um
so that's the one way but now uh in
systematic one
it's it's rarely used but you can define
part properties without this composition
relationship that's allowed since the
smell
1.5 or 1.4 i don't remember exactly okay
never heard from that i don't know but
it's allowed you can do that
and if i do the transformation with such
a model
it would create the same system v2 model
from it as i have
this maybe one model with the
composition relationship so two
differences maybe one models lead to the
same system will be two model and you
cannot
okay yeah yeah okay there
and we have this
ambiguity okay cool yeah
and i i guess there's some more examples
but mm-hmm
yeah yeah and that's what what you what
you said before yeah we have much more
expressiveness in so small v2
so yeah you would have an ambiguity and
it's just another one
okay cool um but i guess you do not only
test uh block a to b and a block has a
part property and that's it so so what
kind of example models do you use
right yes so so we have tons of those
very small models
um
where each model is has only a very
small set of elements so for example an
empty block that's block a
and then we have another model a block
with some properties and so forth
we use those models to develop the
transformation
right sure test one specific aspect
but for the real validation we need a
test suite um and
well again the lack of resources
but also the reuse of already existing
things so we decided to use the
model interchange working group test
cases for this purpose
um
the my wic test cases model education
working group uh they were developed
several years ago or maybe 10 years ago
almost 10 years ago i think in an
omg working group
to test the the exchange of models
between tools
wasn't here
wasn't it even at sharing this group
uh
yeah and any case he was involved but
i'm not sure if
maybe he also was the chair of that
group yeah i i remember
really
and and they had well almost the same
requirement that we have a complete
coverage of the model elements
as complete as possible so
uh so it's a nice example of reusing and
not reinventing the wheel yeah yeah so
we use those test cases now they are
available
um as camille models but also as xmi
models um
they're already there on the omg servers
and we use those
test cases now for our transformation
okay and
do you also
handle those cases those arrow cases so
to say then
when when something cannot be
transformed
um
also well this it's it's not part of the
transformation specification
um it's a task of the transformation
tool
um
and our pilot implementation cannot do
it so far and we will probably not
include
any convenience functions for the time
being due to our time constraints we
have lack of resources and time
constraints
okay but it could be a requirement in
the specification that implementations
should do so
yeah sure that could theoretically exist
but well there's not
there's a requirement but no not yet
well the specification uh also does not
tell modeling tools what to do when the
user models nonsense or so another
same so we always assume that the input
is not garbage
okay okay
and
different question but
some of our listeners know already the
pilot implementation of
the language itself and
the api services so is there also a
publicly available uh transformation
implementation
um no unfortunately not so currently it
is it's a private github repository so
it's not public yet
and well the reason it is not that it is
a secret or so
the reason is well we already mentioned
lack of resources uh to make it public
uh we could have
we would have to provide a documentation
that cost time
and well and probably we get quite a few
questions then uh that we should answer
now so installation problems and and so
on so
um
but i can really imagine that we will
make the pilot implementation public in
the future so
maybe someone will use it
as a basis to turn it into a more
serious tool that's only a pilot
implementation it's not
uh planned to be a serious tool so for a
real project
so i could imagine that uh
that you could
could publish it as a web service so i
upload my system lv1 xmi and i get an v2
xmi as a response would that be suitable
yeah so technically it would be
possible to do that so if anyone is
interested in working on it well
it might work out and
as a as a prototype or like a pilot
implementation thing um you can use our
pilot transformation pilot
implementation for that
but i don't think for us here just um
web service
and i think it would cost quite a lot of
effort
i don't know is it is it scriptable so
you said you're using a tool chain
uh from from eclipse tools so
i don't know
uh i don't know if it's possible i
maybe it's possible so it's
uh it's atl the atlas information
language code that we have in the end
that is used i don't know if it's
possible to script it
um sounds
sounds for me like
you have some some inputs outputs and so
on and you just have to
yeah
to bring them
in a command line
script and
yeah
would be worth looking at it
okay cool
[Music]
let me
let me think what
what we talked about so we've talked
about um
the pilot implementation and
yeah um
are there already tool vendors who are
interested in this transformation
uh
yes so it's currently it's not nothing
is available
but we talked with eastvan raj from ink
ferry
at the last omg meeting in washington um
by the way we had also a podcast with
eastman
together with enrique from vitek some
time ago
well we already covered a lot of stuff
oh yeah
so yeah and east one uh respectively
inquiry his company uh plans to build a
commercial transformation tool that
transforms system lv1 models to system
lb2 um and in particular large models so
oh okay
well i think it could make sense to do
another podcast with him
finish his tool
or at least a prototype of the tool yeah
yeah
yeah okay
so
um
i think that was already
a lot of stuff
and
um
yeah if if if you like topics like this
one uh
consider to subscribe to this channel
and leave us a comment how you like it
i
really am
i'm really proud of having more than 500
followers on youtube now
and
we
we want to say thank you to our
listeners
we never thought that we will have such
a big community uh
when we when we started we we said ah
let's begin and if less than 10 people
are listening to it we can leave it
again but wow it's it's really nice to
see uh yeah in the beginning if i
remember correctly we
would like to listen to a podcast but
there was no mse podcast so we decided
yeah
okay so tim uh
what's up in the next episode
yeah so the plan is uh to talk um again
about system lv2 well this is my tools
on its final run so it makes sense to to
cover it
uh now a little bit more extensive and
our guest will be outside of it so
that will be quite interesting um
to get a very good insights into system
we too yeah so to say he is a kind of
the father of of of susan lv2
yes yeah yeah one of the fathers yeah
there are many fathers and then
yeah
yeah definitely so
i think he can answer every question
okay
and well system we choose a very large
topic so well we have to check out what
what we finally asked him
we put the focus on
yeah yeah and the plan is to to submit
versus my v2 specification end of this
year to the omg so if the omg then
adapts it
um
then system lb2 will be published uh one
or two years later okay after the
finalization task force so
okay
yeah did we already say the date
for the next episode yeah we
uh well yeah yeah we scheduled the day
today with ed
so it's still quite hot it's june the
6th it's a monday
yeah it's in about same time six weeks
and maybe we do another episode in
between but uh
yeah you will
you will get informed when you subscribe
to this channel
exactly
yeah and then well finally after so much
sophisticated stuff uh do not forget
trust us we are systems engineers
bye-bye
goodbye