Welcome to the 23rd door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
Today we show you some more aspects
of the next generation
modeling language SysML v2
Yesterday we showed a
simplified Physical Architecture
of our Christmas tree in SysML v2
Today we will briefly
look at requirements
the modeling of variants
and the SysML v2 API
First, let's open our
Jupyter Notebook again
A quick reminder of what we already have
It is a simple Physical Architecture
that specifies the parts of our
Christmas tree and their connections
Now we look at the requirements
We import a part of the requirements
from the International Christmas
Tree Standard, ICS242526_12
which is modeled here with
only one requirement
The ICS242526_12 requirement
"ReqTreeHeight"
is a requirement definition
It specifies the name "ReqTreeHeight"
the requirement text after the doc keyword
and an attribute "treeHeight"
to formally specify the constraint
that the height of the tree
must be between 150 and 200
In the package "TMPCT_Requirements"
we use the defined
ICS242526_12 requirement
Our TMPCT_Requirement
"Height of the Tree"
is a usage of the requirement
definition "ReqTreeHeight"
In addition we specify
a requirement ID "REQ1"
and redefine the "treeHeight" attribute
by setting it to the value
of the appropriate value property
of our Christmas tree
The visualization of the requirements is
not very exciting among other things
because we have not used relationships
Next, we have a brief look at
how to model variants
because this is a hot topic in MBSE
First, we take our
"TMPCT_PhysicalArchitecture" again
The variability is defined in
two additional packages
In the "TMPCT_Variations" package
we define an abstract
"christmasTreeVariations" part
that contains the variations
which constrain the allowed variants
The keyword and concept
variation in SysML v2
is similar to the concept
of a variation point
For example, we specified that
our part "christmasTreeStar"
can have one of the three variant
"ecoStar", "premiumStar"
or "standardStar"
We also defined another variation for
the part "christmasTreeStand"
In addition, we defined
a constraint that specifies
if the "premiumStar" variant is selected
you must select the "largeStand" variant
the variants are defined in another
package "TMPCT_Variants"
very simple we just defined the parts
Only the "premiumStar" part
owns another part "ledLight"
The visualization of the model depicts
some new special SysML v2
notation elements for the variants
It shows the specified variance
of a variation by a relationship
Finally we defined two products of our
MBSE Podcast Christmas Tree
The "echoTree" subsets the abstract part
"christmasTreeVariations"
and selects the "ecoStar" and
the "standardStand" variants
the "premiumTree" selects the
"premiumStar" and the "largeStand" variant
We close this episode with a
brief look at the SysML v2 API
We can publish our model to
a SysML v2 repository server
which is provided by
the company Intercax
To have everything in one model
we put all our previous packages
into one package called TMPCT
The publish command posts
the model to the Intercax server
where we can access our
model via the SysML v2 API
Through the Swagger UI
you can use the API in the browser
As an example
we show how to view the list of
projects in the SysML v2 repository
With the project number you could then
get to the comments via the API
And via project and commit number
then the elements of the model
So much for the 23rd door of our
MBSE Podcast Advent Calendar
And we wish you a great 23rd of December
Bye-bye