welcome to the 23rd door of our mbse
podcast advent calendar today we show
you some more aspects of the next
generation modeling language system v2
yesterday we showed a simplified
physical architecture of our christmas
tree in system lv2
today we will briefly look at
requirements the modeling of variants
and the system lv2 api
first let's open our jupyter notebook
again
a quick reminder of what we already have
it is a simple physical architecture
that specifies the parts of our
christmas tree and their connections
now we look at the requirements
we import a part of the requirements
from the international christmas tree
standard ics 242526-12
which is modeled here with only one
requirement
the
ics-2054-2526 requirement rec tree hate
is a requirement definition it specifies
the name rectory hate the requirement
text after the doc keyword and an
attribute 38 to formally specify the
constraint that the height of the tree
must be between 150 and 200.
in the package tmpct underscore
requirements
we use the defined ics 24 26 27
requirement
our tmpct requirement height of the tree
is a usage of the requirement definition
rec tree height
in addition we specify a requirement id
rec1
and redefine the tree height attribute
by setting it to the value of the
appropriate value property of our
christmas tree
the visualization of the requirements is
not very exciting among other things
because we have not used relationships
next we have a brief look at how to
model variants because this is a hot
topic in mbse
first we take our tmpct physical
architecture again
the variability is defined in two
additional packages in the tmpct
variations package we define an abstract
christmas tree variations part that
contains the variations which constrain
the allowed variants the keyword and
concept variation in system v2 is
similar to the concept of a variation
point
for example we specified that our part
christmas tree star can have one of the
three variants aqua star premium star or
standard star
we also defined another variation for
the part christmas tree stand
in addition we defined a constraint that
specifies
if the premium star variant is selected
you must select the large stand variant
the variants are defined in another
package tmpct variants very simple we
just defined the parts only the premium
star part owns another part led light
the visualization of the model depicts
some new special system lv2 notation
elements for the variants
it shows the specified variance of a
variation by a relationship
finally we defined two products of our
mbse podcast christmas tree the echo
tree
subsets the abstract part christmas tree
variations and selects the ecostar and
the standard style variants
the premium tree selects the premium
star and the large stent variant
we close this episode with a brief look
at the sysml v2 api
we can publish our model to a sysmlv2
repository server which is provided by
the company intercax
to have everything in one model in one
model we put all our previous packages
into one package called tmpct
the publish command posts the model to
the intercax server where we can access
our model via the system lv2 api
through the swagger ui you can use the
api in the browser as an example we show
how to view the list of projects in the
system lv2 repository
with the project number you could then
get to the comments via the api and via
project and commit number than the
elements of the model
so much for the 23rd door of our amazing
podcast advent calendar and we wish you
a great 23rd of december
bye bye